窈窕淑女
主演：奥黛丽 赫本
雷克斯 哈里逊
编剧：亚兰 艾勒纳
制片：杰克 华纳
导演：乔治 库克
女：太精彩了
WOMAN: Splendid.
车夫1：抱歉 先生 我车上已经有客人了
VALET 1 : Sorry, sir, I've already got one there.
[聊天的声音]
[CHATTERING]
车夫1：过来 先生 过来
VALET 1 : Over here, sir, over here.
车夫2：过来
VALET 2: Coming through.
[车夫2的口哨声]
[VALET 2 WHISTLES]
车夫1：过来 先生
VALET 1 : Over here, sir.
车夫1：让下路
VALET 1 : Make way.
伊莉莎：弗雷迪 噢 已经太晚了
ELIZA: Freddy, oh, it's already very late.
[聊天的声音]
[CHATTERING]
[人们的抱怨声]
[PEOPLE MURMURING]
男：把它展开 赶紧盖好
MAN: Move it, darn it.
[汽车喇叭声]
[HORN HONKING]
弗雷迪 去叫辆马车来
[MRS. EYNSFORD-HILL] Freddy, go and find a cab.
你想让我得肺炎吗？
Do you want me to catch pneumonia?
男：当心点儿 笨蛋
MAN: Watch out, daffy.
他居然叫我是笨蛋
[IN COCKNEY ACCENT] He calls me a daffy.
别光站在那儿 弗雷迪 去叫辆出租车来
Don't just stand there, Freddy. Go and find a cab.
好的 我这就去叫 我这就去叫车
AII right, I'II get it. I'II get it.
男：我都被淋湿了
MAN: I'm getting wet.
[费雷迪的口哨声]
[FREDDY WHISTLES]
男：抱歉
MAN: I'm so sorry.
[咕噜声]
[GRUNTS]
走路要看路 先生 走路要看路啊
Look where you're going, dear. Look where you're going.
真是太抱歉了
I'm so sorry.
两束紫罗兰掉进泥水里了
Two bunches of violets trod in the mud.
这可是一天的收入
A full day's wages.
弗雷迪
EYNSFORD-HILL: Freddy.
弗雷迪 还不快去叫辆出租车
Freddy, go and find a cab.
好的 妈妈
Yes, Mother.
噢 他是你儿子 对吧？
Oh, he's your son, is he?
噢 您要是愿意像一位母亲应该做的那样替他赔我
Well, if you'd done your duty by him as a mother should,
你可不能任他就这样糟蹋了一个可怜女孩儿的花儿
you wouldn't let him spoil a poor girl's flowers
却什么都不赔就这么跑了啊
and then run away without paying.
噢 接着做自己的生意去吧 姑娘
Oh, go about your business, my girl.
要是你不赔钱那就别想离开这儿
And you wouldn't go off without paying either.
有两束紫罗兰掉进泥水里了
Two bunches of violets trod in the mud.
我的天
Good heavens.
- 先生 您看这雨像是要停了吗？ - 我恐怕还要下
- Sir, is there any sign of it stopping? - I'm afraid not.
- 现在越下越大了 - 噢 天哪
- It's worse than before. - Oh, dear.
如果越下越大的话 那就表示雨快停了
lf it's worse, it's a sign it's nearly over.
高兴点吧 上校 买一束可怜女孩儿的花吧
Cheer up, captain. Buy a flower off a poor girl.
抱歉 我没零钱
I'm sorry, I haven't any change.
噢 半克朗我还是能找开的 给 这只要2便士 [克朗 英国旧币单位 =0.25镑=5先令=60便士 ]
Oh, I can change half a crown. Here, take this for tuppence.
我已经说了 非常抱歉 我没有...
I told you, I'm awfully sorry, I haven't--
噢 等等 噢 找到了
Oh, wait a minute. Oh, yes.
这儿有三个1便士的硬币 给你吧
Here's three ha'pence, if that's any use to you.
谢谢您 先生
Thank you, sir.
听着 你得当心点儿 收了钱最好给他一朵花
Here, you be careful. Better give him a flower for it.
在那柱子后边有个家伙
There is a bloke here behind that pillar
把你说的每句话都记下了
taking down every blessed word you're saying.
我同一位绅士说话又不算做了什么错事
I ain't done nothing wrong by speaking to the gentleman.
我有权在街边卖花
I've a right to sell flowers if I keep off the curb.
我可是个品行端正的女孩儿 请大家帮帮我
I'm a respectable girl, so help me.
我除了求他从我这里买一朵花儿之外再没说别的
I never spoke to him except to ask him to buy a flower off me.
男1：- 别再说了 - 怎么这么吵？
MAN 1 : Don't start. - What's all the noise?
好像有个侦探要抓他
There's a tec taking her down.
我靠双手正直的生活着
I'm making an honest living.
男2：是谁在那儿大喊大叫的？
MAN 2: Who's doing all that shouting?
- 这是怎么回事？ - 嗯...
- Where is it coming from? ELIZA: Well...
噢 先生 别让他控告我 他们不知道那对我意味着什么
Oh, sir, don't let him charge me. They don't know what it means to me.
他们会毁掉我的名誉让我流落街头…
They'II take away me character and drive me on the streets
只因为我同一位绅士说了话
for speaking to gentlemen.
慢着 慢着 慢着
There, there, there.
谁要伤害你 你这个傻女孩儿？你把我当成什么人了？
Who's hurting you, you silly girl? What you take me for?
我向圣经起誓 我一个字儿也没说过
On my Bible oath, I never spoke a word.
闭嘴 别说了 我看上去像是警察吗？
Shut up. Do I look like a policeman?
那你干嘛记下我说的话？
Then what did you take down me words for?
我怎么知道你有没有乱写呢？
How do I know you took me down right?
让我看看你都是怎么记的
You just show me what you wrote about me.
伊莉莎：噢
ELIZA: Oh.
这是什么？这根本就是不正常的字
What's that? That ain't proper writing.
- 我看不懂 - 我可以
- I can't read it. - I can.
“我说 上校 请买一束可怜女孩儿的花吧”
"I say, captain, now buy a flower off a poor girl."
噢 就因为我叫了他“上校”
Oh, it's because I called him "captain."
哦 我没有冒犯的意思
Oh, I meant no harm.
先生 求您不要让他就因为那样一个词就控告我
Sir, don't let him lay a charge against me for a word like that.
我不会指控的
I'II make no charge.
真的吗 先生 如果你是位侦探 你没必要保护我
Really, sir, if you are a detective, you needn't begin protecting me
免受一位年轻女士的骚扰 除非我要求你那样做
against molestation from young women until I ask you.
谁都知道这个女孩没有恶意
Anyone could tell the girl meant no harm.
他可不是什么侦探 他是位绅士
He ain't no tec. He's a gentleman.
看他穿的靴子
Look at his boots.
你们都是从塞尔西来的吧？
How are all your people down at Selsey?
谁跟你说我们是从塞尔西来的？
Who told you my people come from Selsey?
别介意 但他们确实 告诉 我了
Never mind. They do.
你怎么会到东面这么远的地方来？
How do you come to be up so far east?
你出生在里森 格鲁夫吧
You were born in Lisson Grove.
噢 我离开里森 格鲁夫又怎么不对了？
Oh, what harm is there my leaving Lisson Grove?
那儿甚至连猪都住不下去 而且每周我都得花4到6镑？？
lt weren't fit for a pig to live in and I had to pay 4 and 6 a week--
随便你住哪儿 可不要再大吵大嚷了
Live where you like, but stop that noise.
行了 行了 他不会抓你了 你有权住在自己想待的地方
Come, come, he can't touch you. You've a right to live where you please.
- 我是个品行端正的女孩儿 我是认真的 - 是的 没错 没错
- I'm a good girl, I am. - Yes, yes, yes.
说下我是从哪儿来的？
Where do I come from?
豪斯敦 [英国城市]
Hoxton.
噢 谁说不是呢？ 啊 你什么都知道啊 说得一点没错
Well, who said I didn't? Blimey, you know everything, you do.
这位先生 你能替我叫一辆出租车吗？
You, sir, do you think you could find me a taxi?
不知道你有没有注意到 雨已经停了
I don't know whether you've noticed, but it's stopped raining.
你可以搭乘一辆去汉普顿法院的公共汽车
You can get a motor bus to Hampton Court.
对了 那正是你住的地方吧 说得没错吧？
Well, that's where you live, isn't it?
真是无礼
What impertinence.
嘿 说说他又是从哪儿来的吧 你好像能预言的样子
Hey, tell him where he comes from, you wanna go fortune-telling.
切尔滕纳姆 [英格兰西南部城市]
Cheltenham,
哈罗 [伦敦市郊地名]
Harrow,
剑桥还有 呃 印度？
Cambridge and, uh, lndia?
极为正确
Quite right.
啊 他不是侦探 他就是个爱管闲事的
Blimey, he ain't a tec, he's a blooming busybody.
容我问一句 先生 你是靠在音乐厅里表演这个为生的吗？
lf I may ask, sir, do you do this sort of thing for a living at a music hall?
嗯 我也曾考虑过 说不定有一天我会的
Well, I have thought of it. Perhaps I will one day.
他才不是什么绅士 否则怎么会欺负一个可怜的女孩儿
He's no gentleman. He ain't, to interfere with a poor girl.
我能问一下 你是怎么做到的吗？
How do you do it, may I ask?
简单来说就是语音学 研究语音的科学
Simple phonetics. The science of speech.
那是我的专业 也是我的爱好
That's my profession. Also my hobby.
任何人都能通过口音辨认出一个人是爱尔兰人还是约克郡人
Anyone can spot an lrishman or a Yorkshireman by his brogue,
但是我可以将一个人的生活地点缩小到6英里的范围内
but I can place a man within six miles.
而在伦敦我可以缩小到2英里
I can place him within two miles in London.
有时甚至可以缩小到两条街
Sometimes within two streets.
真该为自己感到羞耻 懦夫
Ought to be ashamed of himself, unmanly coward.
靠这个也可以谋生吗？
ls there a living in that?
噢 是的 可以说过得还相当不错
Oh, yes, quite a fat one.
让他忙他自己的吧 别再缠着我这个可怜的女孩儿了
Let him mind his own business and leave a poor girl--
你这女人！马上停止发出这可憎的哭声
Woman! Cease this detestable boohooing instantly
要不就另外找个同情你的地方待着去
or else seek the shelter of some other place of worship.
只要我愿意 我有权待在这儿 跟你一样
I have a right to be here if I like, same as you.
发出这样叫人厌恶与不舒服噪音的女人
Woman who utters such disgusting and depressing noises
没有权利出现在任何地方 连活着的权利都没有
has no right to be anywhere. No right to live.
别忘了你是个有灵魂的人
Remember that you're a human being with a soul
上天让你能够开口说话
and the divine gift of articulate speech.
你的母语
That your native language
莎士比亚 米尔顿 还有圣经都是用的这种语言
is the language of Shakespeare and Milton and the Bible.
别坐在那儿像个多胆汁质的鸽子一样咕咕咕的
Don't sit there crooning like a bilious pigeon.
啊噢！
Ow!
看看她 她是个生活在贫民区的人
[SINGING] Look at her A prisoner of the gutters
她嘴里发出的每一个音节都可以让你断定
Condemned by every syllable She utters
照律她应该被拖出去绞死
By right She should be taken out and hung
因为她冷血无情的谋杀了英语
For the cold-blooded murder Of the English tongue
啊噢！
Ow!
天哪！这是什么声音啊！
Heavens! What a sound!
这就是英国人 所谓的基础教育
This is what the British population Calls an elementary education.
噢 先生 我想你只是不幸挑错了例子
Come, sir, I think you picked a poor example.
是吗？
Did I?
听听这些站在苏豪广场的人们 [苏豪广场 伦敦苏豪区的一个广场]
[SINGING] Hear them down in Soho Square
全都不发H音
Dropping H's everywhere
英语任由他们喜欢怎么说都行
Speaking English any way they like
嘿 这位先生 你有上过学吗？
Hey, you, sir, did you go to school?
你把我 登 什么 傻瓜吗？
What do you take me for, a fool?
噢 没人教过他“当”该怎么念 可不是念“登”
Well, no one taught him "take" lnstead of "tike"
听听约克郡人 或者更糟糕的是 听听康沃尔郡的人的谈话吧
Hear a Yorkshireman, or worse Hear a Cornishman converse
我宁愿去听唱诗班
I'd rather hear a choir singing flat
就像一群鸡 在谷仓里咯咯叫 就像这个人一样
Chickens, cackling in a barn Just like this one
继续说
Garn.
“继续说”
"Garn."
请问 先生 你说刚才的那是什么词儿？
I ask you, sir, what sort of word is that?
就是“啊噢”和“继续说”连在一起 这就是为什么她只能生活在贫民区里
lt's "ow" and "garn" That keep her in her place
并非是由于她穿着破旧的衣服 以及满是污垢的面容
Not her wretched clothes And dirty face
为什么英国人 就不知道教会自己的孩子该怎么说英语呢？
Why can't the English Teach their children how to speak?
语言也分阶级 虽到如今 有些过时了
This verbal class distinction By now, should be antique
如果您也像她那样说话 先生 您也会过得跟她一样的
lf you spoke as she does, sir lnstead of the way you do
于是 您现在可能也是个卖花儿的
Why, you might be selling flowers too
请原谅
PICKERING: I beg your pardon.
从一个英国人说话的方式 就能断定他是什么档次的人
An Englishman's way of speaking Absolutely classifies him
当他说话的时候
The moment he talks
便已经让其他英国人开始鄙弃他
He makes some other Englishman Despise him
我恐怕我们再也不会有一种同样的语言
One common language I'm afraid we'II never get
噢 为什么英国人就是不能
Oh, why can't the English learn to
向那些英语说得刺痛你耳朵的人们做个好榜样
Set a good example to people Whose English is painful to your ears
要换做是苏格兰人还有爱尔兰人说的话 简直叫人想哭
The Scotch and the lrish Leave you close to tears
甚至在有些地方 英语已经彻底的不复存在了
There even are places Where English completely disappears
因为 在美国 他们好多年前说的就不是英语了
Why, in America They haven't used it for years
[皮克林的笑声]
[PICKERING LAUGHS]
为什么英国人 就不知道教会自己的孩子该怎么说英语呢？
Why can't the English Teach their children how to speak?
挪威人学挪威语 希腊人教自己后代说希腊语
Norwegians learn Norwegian The Greeks are taught their Greek
在法国每个法国人都背得出 法语的字母表
In France every Frenchman knows His language from A to Z
法国人事实上根本就不担心该怎么教
The French don't care what they do actually,
只要能正确发音就行
as long as they pronounce it properly.
阿拉伯人学阿拉伯语 就如同夏日的闪电一般快
[SINGING] Arabians learn Arabian With the speed of summer lightning
希伯来人几乎是令人恐怖的倒着学希伯来语 [希伯来语从右至左书写]
The Hebrews learn it backwards Which is absolutely frightening
说着正统英语 你却被当做怪人
Use proper English You're regarded as a freak
噢 为什么英国人...
Oh, why can't the English...
为什么英国人 就是不好好学该怎么说英语？
Why can't the English Learn to speak?
谢谢
Thank you.
你看见这个人 还有她那拙劣的英语了吗？
You see this creature with her curbstone English?
这样的英语不只会让她到死都生活在贫民区吗？
The English that'II keep her in the gutter till the end of her days?
这样吧 先生 在6个月之内 我会把她变得
Well, sir, in six months, I could pass her off
像一位公爵夫人一般出现在大使招待舞会上
as a duchess at an Embassy Ball.
我甚至可以让她得到一份工作 比如作一位小姐的侍女或是商店店员
I could even get her a job as a lady's maid or a shop assistant,
这些需要英语说得更好的工作
which requires better English.
喂 你在说什么？
Here, what's that you say?
噢 你这匹烂菜叶
Yes, you squashed cabbage leaf.
你简直是玷污了这些高贵的塔式建筑
You disgrace to the noble architecture of these columns.
你就是英语耻辱的化身
You incarnate insult to the English language,
我要把你变得如同希巴女王一样高贵 [希巴女王 一位阿拉伯半岛的女王 因敬慕所罗门王 与其生下一子]
I could pass you off as the Queen of Sheba.
[希金斯在咯咯笑]
[HIGGINS CHUCKLES]
噢 你也不相信他说的吧 上校
Oh, you don't believe that, captain.
一切皆有可能
Anything's possible.
我自己也在学习印度的土语
I myself am a student of lndian dialects.
是吗？
Are you?
你听说过皮克林上校吗 的作者？
Do you know Colonel Pickering, the author of Spoken Sanskrit?
我就是皮克林上校 你是哪位？
I am Colonel Pickering. Who are you?
我是亨利 希金斯 的作者
I'm Henry Higgins, author of Higgins Universal Alphabet.
我特意从印度来拜访你
I came from India to meet you.
我也打算去印度拜访你的
I was going to lndia to meet you.
- 希金斯 - 皮克林
- Higgins. - Pickering.
[两人在笑]
[BOTH LAUGHING]
- 希金斯 - 你住在什么地方？
PICKERING: Higgins. - Where are you staying?
卡尔顿
At the Carlton.
不行 你怎么能住那里 你还是搬到温珀街27A号来吧
No, you're not. You're staying at 27A Wimpole Street.
跟我一起住 晚上用餐的时候我们可以好好聊聊
You come with me. We'II have a little jaw over supper.
- 说的没错 - 印度土语一直都很让我着迷
- Right you are. - Indian dialects always fascinated me.
好心的先生 买束花儿吧 我得用来付房租呢
Buy a flower, kind sir. I'm short for me lodgings.
撒谎
Liar.
你说过你可以找开半克朗的
You said you could change half a crown.
你这嘴里应该塞满钉子
You ought to be stuffed with nails, you ought.
给你 这篮子里所有的花儿都给你 只要6便士 [这里边几乎就没有花儿啊 赫本您这就是敲诈啊!]
Here, take the whole blooming basket for sixpence.
希金斯：真是不依不饶
HIGGINS: A reminder.
到底有多少种？
How many are there actually?
你问什么有多少种？
PICKERING: How many what?
希金斯：印度土语
HIGGINS: lndian dialects.
不会少于
PICKERING: No fewer than 147 distinct languages
印度官方记录的147种
are recorded as vernacular in lndia.
噢
Ow.
啊
Ah.
男1：我们不该起身致意一下吗 先生们？
MAN 1 : Shouldn't we stand up, gentlemen?
一位妙龄的女士来到了我们中间
We've got a blooming heiress in our midst.
你不一直想找个好管家吗 伊莉莎？
Would you be looking for a good butler, Eliza?
噢 你不行
Well, you won't do.
这城里太无趣了 我想我得去趟巴黎
[SINGING] It's rather dull in town I think I'II take me to Paris
太太想去位于卡布里的城堡
The missus wants to open up The castle in Capri
我的私人医生建议我到海边避暑
Me doctor recommends A quiet summer by the sea
[合唱在声]
[CHORUS HUMMING]
这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
CHORUS [SINGING]: Wouldn't it be loverly
你今年打算去哪儿 伊莉莎？比亚里茨？ [比亚里茨 法国西南部城市]
Where you bound for this year, Eliza? Biarritz?
[男人在笑]
[MEN LAUGHING]
我所想要的只是一个这样的房间
[SINGING] AII I want is a room somewhere
夜里没有冷风侵袭
Far away from the cold night air
有一张大椅子
With one enormous chair
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
有好多的巧克力在等着我吃
Lots of chocolate for me to eat
炉子也烧得暖暖的
Lots of coal makin' lots of heat
温暖了我的脸 我的手 直到我的脚
Warm face, warm hands, warm feet
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
噢 如此惬意的坐在 这般温暖的房间里直到
Oh, so loverly sittin' Abso-bloomin'-lutely still
直到春季来临前我甚至都不会挪动一下 趴在窗台上
I would never budge till spring Crept over the windowsill
心爱的人将头枕在我的膝上
Someone's head restin' on my knee
尽其所能的温柔的
Warm and tender as he can be
庇护着我
Who takes good care of me
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
惬意 当然惬意
Loverly, loverly
多么惬意啊！
合唱：我所想要的只是一个这样的房间
CHORUS: AII I want is a room somewhere
夜里没有冷风侵袭
Far away from the cold night air
里边有张大椅子
With one enormous chair
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
有好多的巧克力在等着我吃
Lots of chocolate for me to eat
炉子也烧得暖暖的
Lots of coal makin' lots of heat
温暖了我的脸 我的手 直到我的脚
Warm face, warm hands, warm feet
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
噢 如此惬意的坐在 这般温暖的房间里直到
Oh, so loverly sittin' Abso-bloomin'-lutely still
直到春季来临前我甚至都不会挪动一下 趴在窗台上
I would never budge till spring Crept over the windowsill
合唱：心爱的人将头枕在我的膝上
CHORUS: Someone's head restin' on my knee
尽其所能的温柔的
Warm and tender as he can be
庇护着我
Who takes good care of me
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
合唱：惬意
CHORUS: Loverly
当然惬意
Loverly
合唱：多么惬意啊！
CHORUS: Loverly
[合唱在吹口哨]
[CHORUS WHISTLING]
[所有人都在笑]
[ALL LAUGHING]
[合唱在吹口哨]
[CHORUS WHISTLING]
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？ [呵呵 译者看到这里想笑]
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
合唱：惬意
CHORUS: Loverly
当然惬意
Loverly
合唱：多么惬意啊！
CHORUS: Loverly
这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Wouldn't it be loverly?
杰米：快走 阿尔菲 我们回去吧 这地方让我感觉很不好
JAMIE: Come on, Alfie, let's go home now. This place is giving me the willies.
回去？你这么急着回去干什么？
Home? What do you want to go home for?
快到5:00了
lt's nearly 5:00.
我女儿伊莉莎就快回来了
My daughter, Eliza, will be along soon.
她应该对得起
She ought to be good for a half a crown
疼爱她的老爸给她的半个克朗
for a father what loves her.
疼爱她？真是笑话
Loves her? That's a laugh.
你都多少个月没见过她了
You ain't been near her for months.
那又怎么样？
What's that got to do with it?
除了我给过她半克朗
What's half a crown after all I've give her?
你什么时候给过她什么东西？
When did you ever give her anything?
什么东西？我把一切都给了她
Anything? I give her everything.
我给了她作为一个人所能给出的最贵重的礼物
I give her the greatest gift any human being can give to another.
那就是生命
Life.
是我用奇迹将她带到这个世上 是我
I introduced her to this here planet, I did, with all its wonders and marvels.
阳光照耀着她 月光滋养着她
The sun that shines, the moon that glows.
让她可以在春日的夜晚下穿过海德公园
Hyde Park to walk through on a fine spring night.
在最繁华的城市伦敦里
The whole ruddy city of London
四处售卖她的鲜花儿
to roam around in, selling her blooming flowers.
这些都是我给她的
I give her all that.
然后我默默离开 让她独自享受这一切
Then I disappears and leaves her on her own to enjoy it.
要是这样都值不了半个克朗
Now, if that ain't worth half a crown now and again,
我就抽出腰里的皮带好好教训她
I'II take my belt off and give her what for.
你心肠真好 阿尔菲
You got a good heart, Alfie.
不过要要想从伊莉莎那儿要回那半个克朗的话
But you want that half a crown out of Eliza,
你最好编个更好的故事
you better have a good story to go with it.
阿尔菲（男）：就放心交给我吧 老弟
ALFIE: Leave that to me, my boy.
早上好 乔治
Good morning, George.
一个子儿都没有
Not a brass farthing.
阿尔菲（男）：早上好 阿尔基农
ALFIE: Good morning to you, Algernon.
一个子儿都没有
Not a brass farthing.
男1：请进吧 请进
MAN 1 : Move on, please. Come on.
把你那肮脏的屁股从这里滚出去
Get your moving ass out of here.
带着它滚
On with it.
男2：卖蔬菜 卖蔬菜了
MAN 2: Veggies. Get your veggies.
我们来了 新鲜的各种蔬菜
Here we are. Nice salad greens.
男3：新鲜的西班牙洋葱
MAN 3: Lovely Spanish onion...
男4：5镑...
MAN 4: Five pounds...
男2：这确实是 新鲜的蔬菜
MAN 2: This is it. Nice bunches of veggies.
- 随便选 - 她在那儿
- Take your pick. - There she is.
男5：都来看啊 西红柿 菜园里新鲜的西红柿
MAN 5: Tomatoes over here. Nice garden tomatoes.
女：红得诱人啊
WOMAN: Very tempting.
噢 伊莉莎 没想到在这儿碰见你
Why, Eliza, what a surprise.
一边去吧 查理 你对我来说太老了
Hop along, Charlie, you're too old for me.
- 你连谁是你女儿都认不出来了么？ - 那你要怎么才能找到她
- Don't know your own daughter? - How you gonna find her
- 你不会认为她长得像我吧？ - 我知道她的样子 走吧
- if you don't know what she looks like? - I know her. Come on.
我会找到她的
I'II find her.
伊莉莎 没想到在这儿碰见你
Eliza, what a surprise.
一个子儿都没有
Not a brass farthing.
噢 过来 伊莉莎
Here, you come here, Eliza.
我不会把自己辛苦挣来的钱
I ain't gonna take me hard-earned wages
给你拿去让该死的酒馆老板赚走的
and let you pass them on to a bloody pub keeper.
伊莉莎 你怎么忍心把我赶回你继母那里去
Eliza, you wouldn't have the heart to send me home to your stepmother
她连一滴酒都不给我 你就忍心吗？
without a drop of liquid protection, now, would you?
继母 是啊
Stepmother indeed.
噢 我愿意同她结婚
Well, I'm willing to marry her.
那是我自找的 我简直就是那个女人的奴隶 伊莉莎
lt's me that suffers by it. I'm a slave to that woman, Eliza.
就因为我不是他的合法丈夫
Just because I ain't her lawful husband.
别这样 给你老爸半克朗我就回去了
Come on, slip your old dad just half a crown to go home on.
嗯 昨晚我运气还不错
Well, I had a bit of luck myself last night.
是吗？
Yeah?
给你
So here.
不过以后别来缠着我要什么半克朗了
But don't keep coming around counting on half crowns from me.
谢谢 伊莉莎
Thank you, Eliza.
你真是个孝顺的女儿
You're a noble daughter.
啤酒 啤酒 金光闪闪的啤酒
[SINGING] Beer, beer, glorious beer
好好喝个饱
Fill yourself right up
女1：你知道她是从哪儿来的吗？
WOMAN 1 : Do you know where she's been?
女2：当然 我认识她 韦恩一直在打听她
WOMAN 2: Yeah, I know. Wayne is always asking.
[聊天的声音]
[CHATTERING]
就是那个 意大利人
That one, Ginny.
女3：别来烦我
WOMAN 3: Leave me alone.
[聊天的声音]
[CHATTERING]
希金斯：你看见这个人 还有她那拙劣的英语了吗？
HIGGINS: You see this creature with her curbstone English?
这样的英语不只会让她到死都生活在贫民区吗？
The English that will keep her in the gutter till the end of her days?
这样吧 先生 在6个月之内 我会把她变得 像一位公爵夫人一般出现在大使招待舞会上
ln six months, I could pass her off as a duchess at an Embassy Ball.
我甚至可以让她得到一份工作 比如作一位小姐的侍女或是商店店员
I could even get her a job as a lady's maid or a shop assistant,
这些需要英语说得更好的工作
which requires better English.
希金斯：你简直是玷污了这些高贵的塔式建筑
HIGGINS: You disgrace to the noble architecture of these columns.
我甚至可以让她得到一份工作 比如作一位小姐的侍女或是商店店员
I could even get her a job as a lady's maid or a shop assistant,
这些需要英语说得更好的工作
which requires better English.
[不会翻译]
[TUNING FORK HUMMING]
A.
E. U. A...
[哼着元音]
[HUMMING VOWELS]
现在说说 你刚才听到的元音一共有多少个？
Now, how many vowel sounds do you think you heard altogether?
我想有24个
I believe I counted 24.
- 差了100多 - 什么？
- Wrong by a hundred. - What?
准确的说 你刚才听到的里边有130个元音
To be exact, you heard 1 30.
现在 再听一遍
Now, listen to them one at a time.
一定要这样吗？我已经听了有一上午了
Must I? I'm really quite done up for one morning.
[希金斯在录元音]
[HIGGINS HUMMING VOWELS ON RECORDING]
请问芳名 请问小姐您的芳名
Your name, please. Your name, miss.
我的名字跟你有什么关系
My name is of no concern to you whatsoever.
请等一下
One moment, please.
噢 伦敦现在真是越来越脏了
Oh, London is getting so dirty these days.
皮尔斯：我是皮尔斯太太 是这儿的管家 有什么需要我效劳吗？
PEARCE: I'm Mrs. Pearce, the housekeeper. Can I help you?
噢 早安 太太
Oh, good morning, missus.
麻烦让我见下教授
I'd like to see the professor, please.
你能告诉我找他有什么事吗？
Could you tell me what it's about?
- 是有关个人的事 - 噢
- It's business of a personal nature. - Oh.
请稍等
One moment, please.
[希金斯在录元音]
[HIGGINS HUMMING VOWELS ON RECORDING]
希金斯先生？
Mr. Higgins.
什么事 皮尔斯太太？
What is it, Mrs. Pearce?
有位年轻的女士想要见您 先生
There's a young woman who wants to see you, sir.
年轻的女士？
A young woman?
她找我有什么事？
What does she want?
一位很寻常的女孩儿 先生 就是看上去很普通的那种
She's quite a common girl, sir. Very common indeed.
我本该让她离开的
I should have sent her away,
不过我想到也许你会想要把她的声音录下来
only I thought perhaps you wanted her to talk into your machine.
- 她的口音很有意思吗？ - 简直就是可怕 希金斯先生
- Has she an interesting accent? - Simply ghastly, Mr. Higgins.
很好 让她进来 让她进来吧 皮尔斯太太
Good. Let's have her in. Show her in, Mrs. Pearce.
那太好了 先生 很高兴听到您这么说
Very well, sir. lt's for you to say.
你真是走运 我让你看看是怎么录音的
This is rather a bit of luck. I'II show you how I make records.
我们让她说话 先把声音通过贝尔发明的声谱仪上
We'II set her talking and then I'II take her down first in Bell's Visible Speech,
转成波形图 然后我们就能通过留声机听到她的声音
then in Broad Romic, and then we'II get her on the phonograph
这样任何时候你想听她的声音都可以了
so that you can turn her on whenever you want
只要有了这张波形图
with the written transcript before you.
就是这位女士 先生
This is the young woman, sir.
早上好 尊敬的先生
Good morning, my good man.
我能有幸和您面对面的说上一句话吗？
Might I have the pleasure of a word with you face-to-face?
噢 不 不 不 这个女孩儿我昨天晚上就记录过了
Oh, no, no, no. This is the girl I jotted down last night.
她对我已经没用了 我已经得到了想要的关于里森 格鲁夫一带方言的所有记录
She's no use. I've got all the records I want of the Lisson Grove lingo.
我可不想在她身上再浪费一个录音筒了
I'm not gonna waste another cylinder on that.
现在 你请出去吧 我不想见到你
Now, be off with you. I don't want you.
别那么无礼 你都还不知道我为什么来呢
Don't be so saucy. You ain't heard what I come for yet.
你没告诉他我是乘出租车来的吗？
Did you tell him I come in a taxi?
别说这些了 女孩儿
Nonsense, girl.
你认为像希金斯先生这样的绅士会在意你是怎么来的吗？
What do you think a gentleman like Mr. Higgins cares what you came in?
噢 我们都是有自尊心的
Oh, we are proud.
噢 他不打算给教我了 他反悔了
Well, he ain't above giving lessons. Not him.
他之前说要教我的
I heard him say so.
好吧 我可不是来这儿 听你们说这些客气话的
Well, I ain't come here to ask for any compliment,
要不是因为我的钱不够的话 我也不会来这儿
and if my money's not good enough, I can go elsewhere.
不够什么？
Good enough for what?
付你的还是够了
Good enough for you.
现在 你明白了吗？我是来学习的 听清楚了
Now you know, don't you? I'm come to have lessons, I am.
我还会付学费 别搞错了
And to pay for them too. Make no mistake.
噢...
Well...
你希望我怎么回答你？
And what do you expect me to say?
好吧 如果你还算是位绅士的话 我想 你该先请我坐下
Well, if you was a gentleman, you might ask me to sit down, I think.
我不是说过了吗 我是来照顾你生意的？
Don't I tell you I'm bringing you business?
皮克林 我们是该请这个货物进来坐下
Pickering, should we ask this baggage to sit down
还是把她从窗户扔出去呢？
or shall we just throw her out of the window?
啊噢！我可不叫什么货物
Ow! I won't be called a baggage.
何况我还像任何一位女士那样要付给你学费
Not when I've offered to pay like any lady.
你为什么要这样做呢 小姑娘？
PICKERING: What do you want, my girl?
我...我希望自己能像一位女士一样在花店里工作
I-- I want to be a lady in a flower shop
而不是在托特纳姆考特路的街角卖花
instead of selling at the corner of Tottenham Court Road.
但除非我说话能更有教养些 否则他们是不会要我的
But they won't take me unless I can talk more genteel.
他说过他会教我 所以 我就来了
He said he could teach me. Well, here I am.
我准备付钱给他 也不要他白教我
Ready to pay him, not asking any favor.
可他却当我是垃圾一样的对待我
And he treats me as if I was dirt.
我知道你上课收多少钱 我愿意掏钱
I know what lessons cost as well as you do, and I'm ready to pay.
付多少钱？
How much?
现在你说话了
Now you're talking.
趁还可以反悔 我想你还是别吹牛了
I thought you'd come off it when you saw a chance of getting back
昨天晚上你那样作践我
a bit of what you chucked at me.
- 你现在有一位客人 不是吗 嗯？ - 坐下吧
- You'd had a drop in, hadn't you, eh? - Sit down.
如果你打算为此道歉的话...
lf you're going to make a compliment of it--
坐下！
Sit down!
坐下 丫头 照我说的做
Sit down, girl. Do as you're told.
你叫什么名字？
What's your name?
伊莉莎 杜利特
Eliza Doolittle.
你能坐下吗 杜利特小姐？
Won't you sit down, Miss Doolittle?
噢
Oh.
我当然会不介意
I don't mind if I do.
说说吧 你打算为接受这些课程付我多少钱？
Now, how much do you propose to pay me for these lessons?
嗯 我是知道行情的
Oh, I know what's right.
我的一位女士的朋友上法语课的花费是一小时18便士
A lady friend of mine gets French lessons for 1 8 pence an hour
是由一位真正的法国绅士教的
from a real French gentleman.
噢 就凭你总不好意思也要收一样的价钱吧
Well, you wouldn't have the face to ask me the same
只不过教我自己的母语 就收我学法语的价钱
for teaching me my own language as you would for French.
所以我最多出1个先令
So I won't give more than a shilling.
随便你要不要
Take it or leave it.
你知道吗 皮克林 如果你不把1先令仅仅当做1先令来看
Do you know, Pickering, if you think of a shilling not as a simple shilling
而是从这个女孩儿的收入百分比来看
but as a percentage of this girl's income,
这几乎相当于
it works out as fully equivalent
一位百万富翁拿出了60到70镑
of 60 or 70 pounds from a millionaire.
以圣乔治名起誓 这太多了 这是我收的最多的一次
By George, it's enormous. lt's the biggest offer I ever had.
60镑？
Sixty pounds?
你们在说什么？我上哪儿能弄来60镑？
What are you talking about? Where would I get 60 pounds?
我根本没说过要付你60镑
I never offered you 60 pounds.
- 把嘴闭上 - 可我根本没有60镑
- Hold your tongue. - But I ain't got 60 pounds.
别哭了 傻丫头
Don't cry, you silly girl.
坐下吧 没人想碰你的钱
Sit down. Nobody's going to touch your money.
要是你还是继续痛哭流涕个没完
Somebody's going to touch you with a broomstick
有人就要用笤帚打你了 坐下！
if you don't stop sniveling. Sit down!
[停止了哭泣]
[STOPS CRYING]
噢 不知道的还以为你是我父亲
Oh, anybody would think you was my father.
要是我真要教你 我会比两个爸爸还要厉害
lf I decide to teach you, I'II be worse than two fathers to you.
[伊莉莎的鼻子吸气声]
[ELIZA SNIFFLES]
给你
Here.
- 给我这个干嘛？ - 擦擦眼泪吧
- What's this for? - To wipe your eyes.
把脸上弄湿了的地方都擦擦吧
To wipe any part of your face that feels moist.
记住 这就是你的手绢而这就是你的袖子
And remember, that's your handkerchief and that's your sleeve.
别把它们搞混了
And don't confuse the one with the other
要是你想成为一名女店员的话
if you want to become a lady in a shop.
您跟她那样讲没用 希金斯先生
lt's no use to talk to her like that, Mr. Higgins.
她根本不明白你在说什么
She doesn't understand you.
- 噢 把手绢给我 - 这手绢是他给我的 不是你
Here, give the handkerchief to me. He give it to me, not to you.
希金斯 我很好奇
Higgins, I'm interested.
你夸口说你能让她变得像公爵夫人一般
What about your boast that you could pass her off as a duchess
出席大使招待舞会 嗯？
at the Embassy Ball, eh?
如果你真能办到 我得说你就是这个世界上最伟大的老师
I'II say you're the greatest teacher alive if you can make that good.
我打赌你办不到 否则这个试验的所有的费用由我承担
I'II bet you all the expenses of the experiment that you can't do it.
甚至连她的学费我也一并支付
I'II even pay for the lessons.
噢 您真好 谢谢您 上校
Oh, you're real good. Thank you, captain.
要知道 这赌注很难拒绝
You know, it's almost irresistible.
她的品味如此低俗
She's so deliciously low.
如此肮脏可怖
So horribly dirty.
我才不脏
I ain't dirty.
我来之前洗过脸还有手 真的
I washed my face and hands before I come, I did.
我愿意同您打这个赌
I'II take it.
我会将她从贫民区的邋遢女孩儿变为一位公爵夫人
I'II make a duchess of this draggle-tailed guttersnipe.
今天就开始 现在 此时此刻起 皮尔斯太太 带她出去把她弄干净
We'II start today. Now. This moment. Take her away and clean her.
要是洗不掉的就用砂纸
Sandpaper if it won't come off any other way.
- 现在厨房里还有火吗？ - 是的 不过...
- Is there a good fire in the kitchen? - Yes, but--
把她所有的衣服都拿去 烧了 给她订做新的
Take all her clothes, burn them, and order new ones.
在新衣服送来之前先用牛皮纸把她裹起来
Just wrap her in brown paper till they come.
你这样太不绅士了 你怎么能这样说话
You're no gentleman. You're not to talk of such things.
我可是个品行端正的女孩儿 我是认真的
I'm a good girl, I am.
我也知道你是什么样的人 真的
And I know what the likes of you are, I do.
你这种贫民区出来的人用不着在我们面前装什么矜持 年轻的小姐
We want none of your slum prudery here, young woman.
你只要学会让自己的举止像一位公爵夫人就可以了
You've got to learn to behave like a duchess.
现在带她出去 皮尔斯太太
Now take her away, Mrs. Pearce.
要是她跟你捣乱的话 你就好好教训她
lf she gives you any trouble, wallop her.
我会叫警察的 我发誓
I'II call the police, I will.
我没地方让她住
I've got no place to put her.
- 这样吧 让她住在垃圾箱里 - 啊噢!
- Well, put her in the dustbin. - Ow!
别这样 希金斯 你这样太不近情理了
Come, Higgins, be reasonable.
你必须合乎情理一点儿 希金斯先生 我说真的
You must be reasonable, Mr. Higgins, really, you must.
你不可以像这样作践别人
You can't walk over everybody like this.
我吗？
I?
我有作践别人？
Walk over everybody?
我亲爱的皮尔斯太太 还有我亲爱的皮克林
My dear Mrs. Pearce, my dear Pickering.
我从没想过要作践谁
I had no intention of walking over anybody.
我只是觉得我们应该对这个可怜的姑娘更好一点
I merely suggested we should be kind to this poor girl.
我表达得不太清楚
I didn't express myself clearly
因为我不希望不符合她的品味
because I didn't wish to hurt her delicacy.
或者是你们的
Or yours.
可是 先生 您不能就这样把一个女孩儿带回来
But, sir, you can't take a girl up like that
就好像你在海滩上捡了块石头一样
as if you were picking up a pebble on the beach.
为什么不行？
Why not?
因为您一点都不了解她
But you don't know anything about her.
她的父母呢？她说不定已经结婚了
What about her parents? She may be married.
接着说
Garn.
看呐 要是这个女孩儿能正确的说出“说下去”
There. As the girl very properly says, "Garn."
有谁会和我结婚？
Who'd marry me?
我以圣乔治之名起誓 伊莉莎
By George, Eliza.
大街上会布满了因你而自杀的男人们的尸体
The streets will be strewn with the bodies of men
在我将你重新打造之前
shooting themselves for your sake before I'm done with you.
听着 我要离开这儿
Here. I'm going.
他在说胡话 绝对是这样
He's off his chump, he is.
- 我可不想让这样的蠢货教我 - 噢 疯子 我是吗？
- I don't want no barmies teaching me. - Oh, mad, am I?
那好 皮尔斯太太 别打电话订什么新衣服了
AII right, don't ring up and order those clothes.
- 把她扔出去 - 不 希金斯先生 我可不能这样做
- Throw her out. - Stop, Mr. Higgins, I won't allow it.
回家去找你父母吧 丫头
Go home to your parents.
我没有父母
I ain't got no parents.
你听见了吧 她没有父母
There you are. She ain't got no parents.
有什么好奇怪的？没人会想要她
What's all the fuss? Nobody wants her.
她对任何人都是废物 除了我 带她上楼去
She's no use to anybody but me. Take her upstairs.
您打算拿她怎么办？让她做什么活儿付给她钱吗？
But what's to become of her? ls she to be paid anything?
噢 麻烦您理智一点儿 先生
Oh, do be sensible, sir.
她要钱干什么？她有的吃穿就够了
What would she do with money? She'II have food and clothes.
要是你给她钱 她就只会拿去喝酒
She'II only drink if you give her money.
噢 你真是个畜生 这是在胡说
Oh, you are a brute. It's a lie.
从来就没人见过我喝酒
Nobody ever saw the sign of liquor on me.
噢 先生 您是位绅士 求您让他别这样说我
Oh, sir, you're a gentleman. Don't let him speak to me like that.
你有没有想过希金斯 这个女孩儿也是有感情的？
Does it occur to you, Higgins, the girl has some feelings?
噢 不 我没想过 我们可不用担心她的感受
Oh, no, I don't think so. No feelings we need worry about.
嗯 你有吗 伊莉莎？
Well, have you, Eliza?
我同任何人一样有自己的感情
I got my feelings same as anyone else.
希金斯先生 我想我必须得知道这个女孩儿在这儿要待多久
Mr. Higgins, I must know on what terms the girl is to be here.
等你教完她 要拿她怎么办？
What's to become of her when you've finished your teaching?
您必须得看得更远一点儿 先生
You must look ahead a little, sir.
要是我们把她送回贫民区会怎样 皮尔斯太太？
What's to become of her if we leave her in the gutter?
- 请回答我 皮尔斯太太 - 那是她自己的事 用不着你管
- Answer me that, Mrs. Pearce. - That's her own business, not yours.
等我把她教完 我们就把她扔回去 之后就是她自己的事了
When I'm done, we'II throw her back, then it will be her own business again.
这样就没问题了吧 不是吗？
That will be all right, won't it?
你根本就没有同情心
You've no feeling heart in you.
你除了你自己什么都不关心
You don't care for nothing but yourself.
我受够了 我现在就要走 我是认真的
I've had enough of this. I'm going, I am.
你该为自己感到羞耻
You ought to be ashamed of yourself, you ought.
吃点儿巧克力吧 伊莉莎
Have some chocolates, Eliza.
我怎么知道这里边都放了什么？
How do I know what might be in them?
我听说有女孩儿被像你这样的人下了药
I've heard of girls being drugged by the likes of you.
为表示我的善意
Pledge of good faith.
我吃一半
I'II take one half
你吃另外一半
and you take the other.
你可以得到很多盒的巧克力 每天都你都会得到好几筒
You'II have boxes of them, barrels of them every day.
你可以拿它们当饭吃 嗯？
You'II live on them, eh?
我并不想吃 只是出于淑女的礼貌
I wouldn't have ate it, only I'm too ladylike
所以才没把它吐出来
to take it out of my mouth.
想想吧 伊莉莎
Think of it, Eliza.
想想巧克力 出租车还有黄金和钻石
Think of chocolates and taxis and gold and diamonds.
啊噢！我可不想要什么黄金还有钻石
Ow! I don't want no gold and no diamonds.
我可是个品行端正的女孩儿 我是认真的
I'm a good girl, I am.
希金斯 看来我必须介入 皮尔斯太太是对的
Higgins, I really must interfere. Mrs. Pearce is quite right.
要是让这个女孩儿在你手里待上6个月
lf this girl's gonna put herself in your hands for six months
进行所谓的教学试验
for an experiment in teaching,
她必须清楚的知道自己是在做什么
she must understand thoroughly what she's doing.
希金斯：嗯
HIGGINS: Mm.
伊莉莎 今后的6个月你将待在这儿
Eliza, you are to stay here for the next six months
学习如何像一位花店店员一样拥有美丽的谈吐
learning how to speak beautifully, like a lady in a florist shop.
如果你有好好做的话
lf you're good and do whatever you're told,
你就能睡在卧室里 还能得到很多好吃的
you shall sleep in a proper bedroom, have lots to eat
还会给你钱去买巧克力 让你出入都乘坐出租车
and money to buy chocolates and take rides in taxis.
但要是你不听话偷懒的话
But if you are naughty and idle,
你就得跟厨房里的黑蟑螂们睡在一起
you shall sleep in the back kitchen amongst the black beetles
还要被皮尔斯太太用笤帚打
and be walloped by Mrs. Pearce with a broomstick.
6个月之后
At the end of six months,
你将被带到白金汉宫
you shall be taken to Buckingham Palace
坐在车里 打扮得漂漂亮亮的
in a carriage, beautifully dressed.
要是被国王发现你不是个淑女
lf the king finds out that you're not a lady,
警察就会把你关进伦敦塔
the police will take you to the Tower of London
在那里砍掉你的脑袋
where your head will be cut off
以警告其他自以为是的卖花儿女孩儿
as a warning to other presumptuous flower girls.
但要是你没被揭穿 你就会得到
But if you are not found out, you shall have a present
7镑6先令的奖金并成为一名女店员
of seven and six to start life with as a lady in a shop.
要是你决绝这个提议
lf you refuse this offer,
你无疑就是最不领情的 坏女孩儿
you will be the most ungrateful, wicked girl
连天使都要为你落泪
and the angels will weep for you.
现在你满意了吧 皮克林？
Now, are you satisfied, Pickering?
我不明白你在说什么
I don't understand what you're talking about.
噢 我还要怎样解释才能让她明白 皮尔斯太太？
Oh, could I put it more plainly or fairly, Mrs. Pearce?
跟我来吧 伊莉莎
Come with me, Eliza.
没错 皮尔斯太太 就那样把她拖到浴室去
That's right, Mrs. Pearce. Bundle her off to the bathroom.
你真是太欺负人了
You're a great bully, you are.
要是我不愿意我就会离开这儿 我才不要让别人打我
I won't stay here if I don't like it. I won't let nobody wallop me.
别顶嘴 丫头
Don't answer back, girl.
伊莉莎：我要是不知道自己是为什么来的 我才不会来这儿呢
ELIZA: lf I'd known what I was letting myself in for, I wouldn't have come here.
我一直都是个品行端正的女孩儿 我才 我才不会被你骗呢
I've always been a good girl, I am, and I won't be put upon.
在6个月内
ln six months--
如果她有一双好耳朵还有一根灵巧的舌头 甚至只要3个月就行
ln three if she has a good ear and a quick tongue.
我要带她去任何地方 让她扮谁都行
--I'II take her anywhere and I'II pass her off as anything.
我能将这个不幸的野丫头变成一位王后
I'II make a queen of that barbarous wretch.
[水流声]
[WATER RUNNING]
伊莉莎：我这辈子都没有洗过澡
ELIZA: I've never had a bath in my life.
现在你可以真正的洗一回了
Not what you'd call a proper one.
要知道 如果你仪表不干净的话 你也不可能成为一位有内涵的好女孩儿
You know, you can't be a nice girl inside if you're dirty outside.
你就住这儿 这里就是你的卧室
I'II have to put you in here. This will be your bedroom.
噢 我可不能睡在这儿 太太 这儿对我这样的人来说太好了
Oh, I couldn't sleep here, missus. lt's too good for the likes of me.
这儿的东西我敢都不敢碰
I should be afraid to touch anything.
我现在还不是公爵夫人呢 你知道吗？
I ain't a duchess yet, you know?
噢 这是什么 这是你们洗衣服的地方吗？
Oh, what's this? This where you wash clothes?
这是我们自己洗澡的地方 伊莉莎
This is where we wash ourselves, Eliza.
现在我正要给你洗澡
And where I'm going to wash you.
你打算让我进那里边 然后把我弄得全身湿透？
You expect me to get into that and wet myself all over?
我不要
Not me.
我宁可死
I shall catch my death.
过来
Come along now.
过来吧 把身上的衣服脱掉
Come along. Take your clothes off.
别磨蹭了 丫头 听话 把衣服脱掉
Come on, girl, do as you're told. Take your clothes off.
- 快来 帮我把这些拿掉 - 啊噢！不 我不要
- Here, come on, help me take these. - Ow! No, I won't.
皮尔斯：- 都过来帮忙 - 不 我不要
PEARCE: Come out of that. - No, I won't.
皮尔斯：- 都来帮忙啊 - 不！
PEARCE: Everyone. - No!
我不要 把你们的手拿开
I won't. Take your hands off me.
- 不要 噢 我的天
- No. PEARCE: Oh, dear.
不 啊噢！
No. Ow!
- 不 我不要洗澡 让我走 伊莉莎 别动
- No, I won't. Let go. PEARCE: Eliza, keep still.
[伊莉莎在哭泣]
[ELIZA CRYING]
[哭泣]
[CRYING]
皮尔斯：- 就洗个澡 - 不
PEARCE: Take a bath. - No!
不要！
No!
我是个品行端正的女孩儿 我是认真的
I'm a good girl, I am.
皮尔斯：噢 要是你不洗澡的话 他们不会喜欢你身上的味道的
PEARCE: Well, they won't like the smell of you if you don't have a bath.
伊莉莎：这不行 这太不像话了
ELIZA: lt ain't right. lt ain't decent.
别拿走我的外套
Let go of my coat.
[伊莉莎尖叫]
[ELIZA SCREAMING]
伊莉莎：把你的手拿开
ELIZA: Take your hands off me.
皮尔斯：过来吧
PEARCE: Come here.
伊莉莎：- 不 - 我不会伤害你的
ELIZA: No. PEARCE: I won't hurt you.
伊莉莎：让我走
ELIZA: Let me go.
放手
Take your hands off me.
我是个品行端正的女孩儿 我是认真的
I'm a good girl, I am.
我说了 放手
Take your hands off me, you hear.
皮尔斯：伊莉莎 我不会放手的
PEARCE: Eliza, I won't have it.
我不会伤害你的
I wouldn't hurt you.
希金斯 恕我无礼
Higgins, forgive the bluntness,
既然我也参与此事 我认为自己应该对这个姑娘负责
but if I'm to be in this business, I shall feel responsible for the girl.
我希望你清楚不能
I hope it's clearly understood that no advantage
占她任何便宜
is to be taken of her position.
什么 那种事？好吧 我可以向你保证
What, that thing? Sacred, I assure you.
拜托 希金斯 你明白我的意思
Come now, Higgins, you know what I mean.
这可不是什么小事儿
This is no trifling matter.
对女人们而言你是一个有着良好品行的男人吧？
Are you a man of good character where women are concerned?
你有见过对女人们而言
Have you ever met a man of good character
品行良好的男人吗？
where women are concerned?
是的 那太常见了
Yes, very frequently.
噢 我可没见过
Well, I haven't.
我发现 只要我一旦同一位女人做朋友
I find the moment I let a woman make friends with me,
她就开始变得嫉妒 刻薄 多疑 极其惹人讨厌
she becomes jealous, exacting, suspicious and a damned nuisance.
此外我还发现 只要我一旦同一位女人做朋友
And I find the moment that I make friends with a woman,
我就开始变得自私且专横
I become selfish and tyrannical.
这就是为什么 我至今仍坚持单身的缘故
So here I am, a confirmed old bachelor and likely to remain so.
噢 毕竟 皮克林 我不过是这样一个男人
[SINGING] Well, after all, Pickering I'm an ordinary man
我所要的不多 只想能
Who desires nothing more Than just an ordinary chance
按照自己喜欢的方式生活 做那些自己喜欢的事
To live exactly as he likes And do precisely what he wants
我不过是个普通的男人 没有什么奇怪的想法
An average man am I Of no eccentric whim
只想过自己的生活 与世无争
Who likes to live his life Free of strife
做自己喜欢的事 就是他最想要的
Doing whatever he thinks ls best for him
噢 只不过是这样一个男人
Well, just an ordinary man
可要是让一个女人走进了你的生活 你平静的生活便被打破
But let a woman in your life And your serenity is through
她会重新布置你的家 从地下室直到屋顶
She'II redecorate your home From the cellar to the dome
然后继续开着迷人的玩笑 把你彻底的改造一遍
Then go on to the enthralling fun Of overhauling you
让一个女人走进你的生活 你等于自己面向了一堵高墙
Let a woman in your life And you're up against a wall
当你做好了打算之后 却发现她另有别的想法
Make a plan and you will find She has something else in mind
总不能什么都不做吧 于是你只能作别的
And so rather than do either You do something else
你根本就不喜欢的事情
That neither likes at all
你想聊聊基茨或是米尔顿 她却只想听你说你爱她
You want to talk of Keats or Milton She only wants to talk of love
你想去看场演出或是芭蕾 可她却整晚都忙着找手套
You go to see a play or ballet And spend it searching for her glove
让一个女人走进你的生活 你等于收到了永远争吵的请柬
Let a woman in your life And you invite eternal strife
让他们买结婚戒指 去给那些焦急盼望结婚的年轻女孩儿的小手带上吧
Let them buy their wedding bands For those anxious little hands
我宁愿让 牙医在我的牙齿上钻孔
I'd be equally as willing For a dentist to be drilling
也好过让一个女人走进自己的生活
Than to ever let a woman in my life
我是一个非常温和的人 平和而温厚
I'm a very gentle man Even-tempered and good-natured
从不惹人抱怨
Who you never hear complain
全身每根血管都 充满着人情味
Who has the milk of human kindness By the quart in every vein
我是个有耐心的男人 从头到脚
A patient man am I Down to my fingertips
我是那种永远不可能 也不会
The sort who never could Ever would
轻易出言冒犯
Let an insulting remark escape his lips
的非常温和的男人
A very gentle man
可要是让一个女人走进你的生活 耐心也就不复存在
But let a woman in your life And patience hasn't got a chance
她虽然会征求你的意见 你的回答即便简短
She will beg you for advice Your reply will be concise
她也会听得很认真
And she'II listen very nicely
可回头 就照着自己的想法乱来
Then go out And do precisely what she wants
你本是一个优雅光鲜的男人 总是细语轻声
You are a man of grace and polish Who never spoke above a hush
可如今突然从你嘴里说出的话 简直能够让水手都感到脸红
Now all at once you're using language That would make a sailor blush
让一个女人走进你的生活 就等于在自己身上插了一把刀
Let a woman in your life And you're plunging in a knife
让其他的男人们 往自己的脖子上套上婚姻的枷锁吧
Let the others of my sex Tie the knot around their necks
我宁愿接受 西班牙宗教裁判所新式的酷刑
I'd prefer a new edition Of the Spanish lnquisition
也好过让一个女人走进自己的生活
Than to ever let a woman in my life
我是一个安宁生活的男人
I'm a quiet-living man
喜欢静静的躺在自己的卧室里 度过漫漫长夜
Who prefers to spend the evenings ln the silence of his room
喜欢如同未被发现的坟墓一般 安详的气氛
Who likes an atmosphere as restful As an undiscovered tomb
我是一个爱沉思的男人 喜欢享受哲学的乐趣
A pensive man am I Of philosophic joys
喜欢冥想 沉思
Who likes to meditate, contemplate
远离俗世的疯狂 与非人的嘈杂
Free from humanity's mad lnhuman noise
一个安宁生活的男人
A quiet living man
可要是让一个女人走进你的生活 你就等于永无假期
But let a woman in your life And your sabbatical is through
她的朋友们如同一支 没有尽头的军队源源不断
ln a line that never ends Come an army of her friends
前来同她叽叽喳喳喋喋不休
Come to jabber and to chatter
跟她说 你在外边又怎么了
And to tell her what the matter Is with you
她有一个庞大 而喧闹的家族
She'II have a booming Boisterous family
挤到你面前 只想知道谁会继承你的遗产
Who will descend On you en masse
她会有一个说话声音大得像唱瓦格纳歌剧的母亲 随便一声就能把玻璃都震碎
She'II have a large Wagnerian mother With a voice that shatters glass
让一个女人走进你的生活
Let a woman in your life
[快速播放录音声]
[RECORDED VOICE PLAYING ON FAST-FORWARD]
让一个女人走进你的生活
Let a woman in your life
[快速播放录音声]
[RECORDED VOICE PLAYING ON FAST-FORWARD]
[录音声停止]
[RECORDED VOICES STOP]
我永远都不会让一个女人走进我的生活
I shall never let a woman in my life
男：滚出去
MAN: Get out of here.
杰米 你们也滚出去
The two of you get out too.
得了吧 杜利特
Come on, Doolittle.
记住 想喝酒就得付钱
And remember, drinks are to be paid for or not drunk.
谢谢你的招待 乔治
Thanks for your hospitality, George.
把帐单送到白金汉宫吧 走吧
Send the bill to Buckingham Palace. Come on.
好了 阿尔菲 继续留在这儿也没什么用了 我想该回去干活儿了
Well, Alfie, there's nothing else to do. I guess it's back to work.
什么？
What?
你最好别在我面前提那个词儿
Don't you dare mention that word in my presence again.
瞧瞧这些可怜的笨蛋
Look at all these poor blighters down here.
[笑声]
[LAUGHS]
我以前做那个 只不过是为了运动一下
I used to do that sort of thing once, just for exercise.
那可不值得 让你花上一整天的时间
lt's not worth it. Takes up your whole day.
噢 别担心 伙计们 我们很快就不会这样了
Oh, don't worry, boys. We'II get out of this somehow.
你准备怎么办 阿尔菲？
How do you think you're going to do that, Alfie?
怎么办？跟从前一样
How? Same as always.
信心 希望再加上一点好运
Faith, hope and a little bit of luck.
主赋予了男人 一双钢铁般的臂膀
[SINGING] The Lord above gave man An arm of iron
让他可以去做自己的工作 不知疲倦
So he could do his job And never shirk
主赋予了男人 一双钢铁般的臂膀 不过
The Lord above gave man An arm of iron but
只要一点点的好运 只要一点点的好运
With a little bit of luck With a little bit of luck
别人就会去做 那些不值得去做的工作
Someone else'II do The blinkin' work
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点的好运 你就永远都不需要工作
ALL [SINGING]: With a little bit ofluck You'II never work
主创造了酒 作为诱惑
The Lord above made liquor For temptation
以察视男人是否能远离 罪恶
To see if man could turn away From sin
主创造了酒 作为诱惑 不过
The Lord above made liquor For temptation but
只要一点点的好运 只要一点点的好运
With a little bit of luck With a little bit of luck
当诱惑来临 你便立即屈服
When temptation comes You'II give right in
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点的好运 你便立即屈服
With a little bit of luck You'II give right in
噢 你可以选择走 大道或是小路
Oh, you can walk The straight and narrow
但只要一点点的好运 你就会胡作非为
But with a little bit of luck You'II run amuck
女人 是神创造给男人结合的
The gentle sex Was made for man to marry
与他共同生活 替他做饭
To share his nest And see his food is cooked
女人 是神创造给男人结合的 不过
The gentle sex Was made for man to marry but
只要一点点的好运 只要一点点的好运
With a little bit of luck With a little bit of luck
你就能拥有一切 却不必被婚姻束缚
You can have it all And not get hooked
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点的好运 你就不必被婚姻束缚
With a little bit of luck You won't get hooked
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点天赐的好运
With a little bit of bloomin' luck
人们总会 朝你扔东西
They're always throwin' Goodness at you
不过只要一点点的好运 就可以躲开
But with a little bit of luck A man can duck
主创造男人 去帮助他的邻居
The Lord above made man To help his neighbor
不论什么地方 在陆地 在海中 或是在云里
No matter where On land, or sea, or foam
主创造男人 去帮助他的邻居 不过
The Lord above made man To help his neighbor but
只要一点点的好运 只要一点点的好运
With a little bit of luck With a little bit of luck
当他来找你的时候 你正好不在家
When he comes around You won't be home
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
[乐队演奏]
[BAND PLAYING]
只要一点点的好运 你正好不在家
With a little bit of luck You won't be home
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点天赐的好运
With a little bit of bloomin' luck
哈利：你是个妇女参政运动的支持者 阿尔菲
HARRY: You make a good suffragette, Alfie.
男：噢 干你自己该干的去吧
MAN: Oh, get along with you.
噢 那个走运的家伙又来了
Why, there's the lucky man now.
尊贵的阿尔菲 杜利特
The Honorable Alfie Doolittle.
你在伊莉莎的屋里做什么？
What are you doing in Eliza's house?
她以前住这儿
Her former residence.
你现在可以自己买酒了 阿尔菲 杜利特
You can buy your own drinks now, Alfie Doolittle.
你可真是掉进黄油桶里了
Fallen into a tub of butter, you have.
- 你在说什么？ - 你女儿 伊莉莎
- What are you talking about? - Your daughter, Eliza.
你真走运 阿尔菲 杜利特
You're a lucky man, Alfie Doolittle.
嗯 伊莉莎怎么了？
Well, what about Eliza?
噢！他还不知道呢 她自己的父亲都还不知道
Oh! He don't know. Her own father and he don't know.
[人们在笑]
[PEOPLE LAUGHING]
伊莉莎穿得漂漂亮亮的回来过一次
Moved in with a swell, Eliza has.
然后又自己乘计程车走了 就同画里一样时髦
Left here in a taxi all by herself, smart as paint.
- 之后三天都没回家了 - 接着说
- And ain't been home for three days. - Go on.
直到今天早上我才收到她的一封信
Then this morning, I get a message from her.
她要把她的东西全都送到
She wants her things sent over.
温珀街27A号
To 27A Wimpole Street,
由希金斯教授转交...
care of Professor Higgins.
[奥普金斯在笑]
[HOPKINS LAUGH]
- 想知道她都要搬走什么东西？ - 都什么？
- And what things does she want? - What?
她的鸟笼和中国折扇
Her birdcage and her Chinese fan.
[阿尔菲（男）在笑]
[ALFIE LAUGHS]
“不过”她在信里说
"But," she says,
“衣物什么的就不必送过来了”
"never mind about sending any clothes."
[所有人都在笑]
[ALL LAUGHING]
我早就知道她有出息
I knew she had a career in front of her.
哈利老弟 我们得一起庆祝下
Harry boy, we're in for a booze-up.
这回阿尔弗雷德 P 杜利特可走运了 [阿尔菲是阿尔弗雷德的简称]
The sun is shining on Alfred P. Doolittle.
男人被造出来 是为了供养自己的孩子的
[SINGING] A man was made To help support his children
这是 天经地义的事情
Which is the right And proper thing to do
男人被造出来 是为了供养自己的孩子的 不过
A man was made To help support his children but
只要一点点的好运 只要一点点的好运
With a little bit of luck With a little bit of luck
他们就会反过来 开始供养你
They'II go out And start supporting you
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点的好运 他们就会替你工作
With a little bit of luck They'II work for you
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点天赐的好运
With a little bit of bloomin' luck
[乐队演奏]
[BAND PLAYING]
噢 男人外出风流 是个罪过
Oh, it's a crime For man to go philanderin'
会让自己妻子那可怜的心 充满忧伤与怀疑
And fill his wife's poor heart With grief and doubt
噢 男人外出风流 是个罪过 不过
Oh, it's a crime For a man to go philanderin' but
只要一点点的好运 只要一点点的好运
With a little bit of luck With a little bit of luck
你会发现 即便是猎犬也嗅不到
You can see The bloodhound don't find out
只要一点点 只要一点点
With a little bit With a little bit
只要一点点的好运 她就不会发现
With a little bit of luck She won't find out
男：查理 过来 只要一点点
MAN: Charlie, over here. - With a little bit
只要一点点
With a little bit
只要一点点天赐的好运
With a little bit of bloomin' luck
您的信 先生
The mail, sir.
是账单的话就付钱 是邀请函的话就推掉
Pay the bills and say no to the invitations.
伊莉莎：A
ELIZA: A.
A
A.
[大喷嚏]
[SNEEZES]
A
A.
A!
您不能再这样训练那丫头了
You simply cannot go on working the girl this way.
让她翻来覆去的念字母表
Making her say her alphabet over and over
从太阳升起直到落下 甚至吃饭的时候都不停
from sunup to sundown, even during meals.
您这样会把自己累坏的 要什么时候才能结束啊？
You'II exhaust yourself. When will it stop?
当然直到她能正确念出来为止
When she does it properly, of course.
还有什么吗 皮尔斯太太?
ls that all, Mrs. Pearce?
这里还有一封信
There's another letter
是那个名叫厄斯拉 D 瓦林福德的美国富翁寄来的
from that American millionaire, Ezra D. Wallingford.
他是希望你能去他的 道德重塑社团 做演讲
He still wants you to lecture for his Moral Reform League.
噢 好吧 把它扔掉
Yes, well, throw it away.
这是他写给您的第三封信了
lt's the third letter he's written you, sir.
- 您总得给个答复吧 - 好吧
- You should at least answer it. - AII right.
把它放在桌子上吧 皮尔斯太太 我会试着给他回信的
Leave it on the desk, Mrs. Pearce. I'II try and get to it.
如果您愿意的话 先生 楼下有一位清洁工
lf you please, sir, there's a dustman downstairs,
自称阿尔弗雷德 P 杜利特 想要见您
Alfred P. Doolittle, who wants to see you.
他说她女儿在您这儿
He says you have his daughter here.
我早就跟你说过
PICKERING: I say.
嗯 让那个无赖上来
Well, send the blackguard up.
他也许不是个无赖 希金斯
PICKERING: He may not be a blackguard, Higgins.
胡说 他当然是个无赖 皮克林
Nonsense. Of course he's a blackguard, Pickering.
不管他是不是 我恐怕他会给我们找麻烦的
Whether he is or not, I'm afraid we'II have some trouble with him.
不 我不这么认为
No, I think not.
即便有什么麻烦 那也是我找他麻烦 而不是他找我
Any trouble to be had, he'II have it with me, not I with him.
杜利特到了 先生
Doolittle, sir.
希金斯教授？
Professor Higgins?
希金斯：过来吧
HIGGINS: Here.
哪儿？
Where?
噢 早上好 先生
Oh, good morning, governor.
我来是为件非常重要的事的 先生
I come about a very serious matter, governor.
在豪恩斯洛长大
Brought up in Hounslow.
母亲是威尔士人 我想
Mother Welsh, I should think.
你想要什么 杜利特？
What is it you want, Doolittle?
我想要回我女儿 就是这样 明白了吗？
I want my daughter, that's what I want, you see?
嗯 当然是这样 你是她父亲 对吗？
Well, of course you do. You're her father, aren't you?
我很高兴看到你还有那么点儿亲情
I'm glad to see you have a spark of family feeling left.
她就在里边 好的 马上把她带走吧
She's in there. Yes, take her away at once.
什么？
What?
把她带走
Take her away.
你认为我会替你照看女儿吗？
Do you think I am going to keep your daughter for you?
噢 这样做合理吗 先生？
Now, is this reasonable, governor?
这样占别人便宜公平吗？
ls it fairity to take advantage of a man like that?
这个女孩儿是我的 你占有了她
The girl belongs to me. You got her.
我该怎么办？
Where do I come in?
你怎么胆敢上这儿勒索我
How dare you come here and attempt to blackmail me.
也许就是你故意把她送这儿来的
You sent her here on purpose.
噢 你怎么可以这样指控别人 先生
Now, don't take a man up like that, governor.
警察自然会指控你
The police shall take you up.
这是有预谋的 以威胁手段进行勒索的阴谋
This is a plan, a plot to extort money by threats.
我要打电话报警
I shall telephone the police.
我有问你要过一个子儿吗？
Have I asked you for a brass farthing?
让旁边的这位绅士来评评理 我哪怕有一个字提到钱了吗？
I'II leave it to this gentleman here. Have I said a word about money?
那你来是为什么？
What else did you come for?
嗯...
Well...
一个醉鬼来能为什么？
What would a bloke come for?
做人得讲道理 先生
Be human, governor.
[笑声]
[LAUGHS]
阿尔弗雷德 你是故意把她送到这儿来的
Alfred, you sent her here on purpose.
相信我 先生 我没有那样做
So help me, governor, I never did.
那你怎么知道她在这儿？
Then how did you know she was here?
我会告诉你的 先生 如果你能让我说的话
I'd tell you, governor, if you'd only let me get a word in.
我这就要告诉你 我正想要告诉你
I'm willing to tell you. I'm wanting to tell you.
我正迫不及待的要告诉你
I'm waiting to tell you.
你看 皮克林
You know, Pickering,
这家伙确实有点语言天赋
this chap's got a certain natural gift of rhetoric.
请注意他说话时如林中鸟叫般的节奏
Observe the rhythm of his native woodnotes wild.
“我这就要告诉你 我正想要告诉你
"I'm willing to tell you. I'm wanting to tell you.
我正迫不及待的要告诉你”这就是他变形的威尔士口音
I'm waiting to tell you." That's the Welsh strain in him.
要不是你把她送来的你怎么知道伊莉莎在这儿？
How did you know Eliza was here if you didn't send her?
嗯 她送信说要取走她的行李 我正好听说了
Well, she sent back for her luggage and I got to hear about it.
还说所有的衣服她都不要了
She said she didn't want no clothes.
听到这些我会怎么想 先生？
What was I to think from that, governor?
请问你 作为一位父亲 我会怎么想？
I ask you, as a parent, what was I to think?
那么你是来趁她还活着赶来救她的吗 嗯？
So you came here to rescue her from worse than death, eh?
没错 先生 正是这样
Just so, governor, that's right.
那好
Yes.
皮尔斯太太
Mrs. Pearce.
皮尔斯太太 伊莉莎的父亲要带她走了
Mrs. Pearce, Eliza's father has come to take her away.
把她交给他 好吗？
Give her to him, will you?
噢 等等 先生 等等
Now, wait a minute, governor, wait a minute.
你我都是男人 不是吗？
You and me is men of the world, ain't we?
噢 我们都是男人 不是吗？
Oh, men of the world, are we?
- 好吧 你先出去 皮尔斯太太 - 我确实也是那样想的 先生
- Yes, you better go, Mrs. Pearce. - I think so indeed, sir.
嘿 先生
Here, governor.
我本以为你是抱着某种想法
I've took a sort of a fancy to you and--
[笑声]
[LAUGHS]
如果你想要这个女孩儿 那好吧 我也就不坚持要把她带回去了
lf you want the girl, well, I ain't so set on having her back home again,
不过我还是得把话说清楚
but what I might be open to is an arrangement.
我所要求的不过是一位父亲正当的权利
AII I ask is my rights as a father.
即便是这世上就你最后一个男人 您也不会指望我什么都不要就让她跟你走吧
You're the last man alive to expect me to let her go for nothing.
噢 我看得出您是那种正直的人 先生
Oh, I can see you're one of the straight sort, governor.
因此 您觉得5张1英镑的对您来说算什么？
So, what's a 5-pound note to you?
我的伊莉莎总值这个价吧？
And what's Eliza to me?
我想应该让你知道 杜利特
I think you ought to know, Doolittle,
这位希金斯先生把你女儿接到这里 用意是绝对高尚的
that Mr. Higgins' intentions are entirely honorable.
当然是这样 先生
Of course they are, governor.
要不是这样 我会要50镑的
lf I thought they wasn't, I'd ask 50.
你的意思是说你打算以50镑卖掉你的女儿？
Do you mean to say you'd sell your daughter for 50 pounds?
你连一点道德都没有吗 伙计？
Have you no morals, man?
不 不 我可买不起它们 先生
No, no, I can't afford them, governor.
要是您跟我一样穷 你也会这样的
Neither could you if you was as poor as me.
我想提醒你们 我并没有什么恶意
Not that I mean any harm, mind you.
但既然伊莉莎可以得到一些好处的话
But if Eliza is gonna have a bit out of this,
那我为什么不能呢 嗯？
why not me too, eh?
为什么不能呢？
Why not?
噢 从我的角度来看
Well, look at it my way.
我是什么？我问你 我是什么？
What am I? I ask you, what am I?
我是个不值得可怜的人 就是这样
I'm one of the undeserving poor, that's what I am.
现在 想想看这对一个男人意味着什么
Now, think what that means to a man.
这意味着他一生都要同中产阶级所谓的道德观对抗
lt means he's up against middle-class morality for all of time.
不论发生什么 我想要的就只是得到点儿好处
lf there's anything going and I puts in for a bit of it,
结果往往都是这样
it's always the same story.
“你不配接受救济 所以不会给你”
"You're undeserving so you can't have it."
可我真的需要 就如同那些最需要救济的寡妇一样
But my needs is as great as the most deserving widows
她们每周都能从6个不同的慈善团体得到救济金
that ever got money out of six different charities in one week
只因为死了同一个丈夫
for the death of the same husband.
我要的不应该比一个需要救济的人少 而是更多
I don't need less than a deserving man, I need more.
我吃得不比他少
I don't eat less hearty than he does.
此外我还要喝酒 很多的酒
And I drink, oh, a lot more.
我实话跟你说吧 我不是装作需要救济
I'm playing straight with you. I ain't pretending to be deserving.
不 我不需要救济
No, I'm undeserving.
我是说即便没有救济也可以生活
And I mean to go on being undeserving.
可我也喜欢接受救济 这就是事实
I like it, and that's the truth.
不过占便宜是人的天性
But will you take advantage of a man's nature
你会不付出代价就将别人的女儿带走吧
to do him out of the price of his own daughter,
想想他是怎样一手抚养 用自己的汗水供她吃穿
what he's brought up, fed and clothed by the sweat of his brow
直到她长大到
till she's growed big enough
你们两位绅士对她有了兴趣？
to be interesting to you two gentlemen?
噢 这样5镑都还不合理吗？你们想想看吧
Well, is 5 pounds unreasonable? I put it to you.
你们看着办吧
And I leave it to you.
你知道吗 皮克林 要是我们能把这个人训练3个月
You know, Pickering, if we took this man in hand for three months,
他就可以选择进入内阁
he could choose between a seat in the cabinet
或是威尔士的任一所教堂供职
and a popular pulpit in Wales.
我们最好给他5镑
We'd better give him a fiver.
我恐怕他不会拿去好好用的
He'II make bad use of it, I'm afraid.
噢 我不会的 先生 请相信我 我不会的
Oh, not me, governor. So help me, I won't.
只是为了让我和我太太能好好喝一台
Just one good spree for myself and the missus.
给我们的生活增添点乐趣 同时也让别人有活儿可干
Giving pleasure to ourselves and employment to others.
您会满意的知道 您的钱并没有被浪费掉的
And satisfaction to you to know it ain't been thrown away.
您不可能把它用在比这更好的地方了
You couldn't spend it better.
噢 真是没救了 给他10镑吧
Oh, this is irresistible. Let's give him 1 0.
不 我太太可不知道该怎么花掉这10镑 先生
No, the missus wouldn't have the heart to spend 1 0, governor.
10镑可太多了
Ten pounds is a lot of money.
会让人觉得该精打细算 这样就没有快乐了
Makes a man feel prudent-like, and then goodbye to happiness.
不 你只要给我要的数目就好 先生 不要少给1个便士 也不要多给1个便士
No, you give me what I ask, governor. Not a penny less, not a penny more.
我实在不支持这种不道德的事 杜利特
I rather draw the line at encouraging this sort of immorality, Doolittle.
你为什么不跟你所谓的那位太太结婚呢 嗯？
Why don't you marry that missus of yours, eh?
毕竟 婚姻没那么可怕吧 你之前也同伊莉莎的母亲结过婚
After all, marriage isn't so frightening. You married Eliza's mother.
谁告诉你我结过婚 先生？
Who told you that, governor?
噢 没人告诉我 是我自己推断的
Well, nobody told me. I concluded, naturally.
要是我们再听这人多说一分钟
lf we listen to this man for another minute,
我们自己的正义感就要消失殆尽了
we shall have no convictions left.
- 5镑对吧 我记得你说你要 - 谢谢您 先生 谢谢
- Five pounds, I think you said. - Thank you, governor, thank you.
你确定你不要10镑？
Are you sure you won't have 1 0?
- 不 不 也许下次吧 - 我再也不要了 我再也不要了 我再也不要了
- No, no, perhaps another time. - I won't, I won't, I won't.
我没听明白 女士
I beg your pardon, miss.
伊莉莎：我再也不要念这些该死的元音了
ELIZA: I won't say those ruddy vowels one more time.
啊 是伊莉莎
Blimey, it's Eliza.
噢 我从没想过 她弄干净了会是这样好看
Well, I never thought she'd clean up so good-looking.
她真是给我挣脸 对吧 先生？
She does me credit, don't she, governor?
嘿 你来这儿干什么？
Here, what you doing here?
噢 现在起 你别再说了
Now, now, you hold your tongue.
在这些绅士面前把你的嘴闭上
And don't you give these gentlemen none of your lip.
要是她给您惹了什么麻烦 先生
lf you have any trouble with her, governor,
就用皮带好好抽她几下
give her a few licks of the strap.
这样她就会学乖了
That's the way to improve her mind.
嗯 早安了 绅士们
Well, good morning, gentlemen.
- 加油 伊莉莎 - 啊!
- Cheerio, Eliza. - Mah!
你可算是碰见了
There's a man for you.
一位最优秀的哲学天才
A philosophical genius of the first water.
皮尔斯太太 回信给厄斯拉 瓦林福德先生
Mrs. Pearce, write to Mr. Ezra Wallingford
告诉他如果他想找一位演说家
and tell him if he wants a lecturer
可以同阿尔弗雷德 P 杜利特先生联系
to get in touch with Mr. Alfred P. Doolittle,
一位普通的清洁工 英国最具创新的道德学家之一
a common dustman, one of the most original moralists in England.
好的 先生
Yes, sir.
嘿 他来这里干嘛？
Here, what did he come for?
念你的元音去
Say your vowels.
我会念元音 我来之前就会念了
I know my vowels. I knew them before I come.
如果你会念了 那就念念看
lf you know them, say them.
- Ahyee e iyee ow you
[IN COCKNEY ACCENT] A, E, I, O, U.
停下
Stop.
- A, E, I, O, U
A, E, I, O, U.
我就是这么念的 A, E, I, O, U
[IN COCKNEY ACCENT] That's what said, A, E, I, O, U.
我都念了三天了
That's what I been saying for three days
我再也不想念了
and I won't say them no more.
我知道这很难 杜利特小姐 不过你要理解
I know it's difficult, Miss Doolittle, but try to understand.
解释是没用的 皮克林
There's no use explaining, Pickering.
作为一名军人 你很清楚 她现在需要的就是训练
As a military man, you know that. Drilling is what she needs.
现在起 别理她 否则就会转而向你寻求同情
Now, leave her alone or she'II be turning to you for sympathy.
那好吧 如果你坚持的话 不过请你对她耐心点儿 希金斯
Very well, if you insist, but have a little patience with her, Higgins.
当然
Of course.
现在念“A”
Now say "A."
你根本就没长心 绝对没有
You ain't got no heart, you ain't.
- A - A
- A. - A.
伊莉莎
Eliza.
我向你保证 今天之内你必须把你的元音念正确
I promise you, you'II say your vowels correctly before this day is out
否则就没有午餐 没有晚餐
or there'II be no lunch, no dinner
也没有巧克力
and no chocolates.
你等着吧 亨利 希金斯 你等着吧
[SINGING] Just you wait, Henry Higgins Just you wait
你会后悔的 可到那时就算你哭得一塌糊涂也太晚了
You'II be sorry But your tears will be too late
等你破产了 而我有钱了
You'II be broke And I'II have money
我会帮你吗？ 别开玩笑了
Will I help you? Don't be funny
你等着吧 亨利 希金斯 你等着吧
Just you wait, Henry Higgins Just you wait
你等着吧 亨利 希金斯 等你得了病
Just you wait, Henry Higgins, Till you're sick
尖叫着 快去请医生的时候
And you screams To fetch a doctor double-quick
我会马上出发 直奔剧院
I'II be off a second later And go straight to the theatre
呵 呵 呵 亨利 希金斯 你等着吧
Ho, ho, ho, Henry Higgins Just you wait
噢呵 亨利 希金斯
Ooh, Henry Higgins
你等着吧 等我们去海里游泳
Just you wait Until we're swimmin' in the sea
噢呵 亨利 希金斯
Ooh, Henry Higgins
你抽筋了 就在离我不远的地方
And you gets a cramp A little ways from me
就在你大叫你就要被淹死了的时候
When you yell you're gonna drown
我会穿好衣服回城去
I'II get dressed and go to town
呵 呵 呵 亨利 希金斯
Ho, ho, ho, Henry Higgins
你等着吧
Just you wait
有一天我会成为贵妇
One day I'II be famous
言行举止适当又高贵
I'II be proper and prim
三天两头就去圣 詹姆斯教堂
Go to St. James so often
我会称它圣 吉姆教堂
I will call it St. Jim
有一天晚上国王会说：
One evening the king will say:
噢 莉莎 我的老朋友
"Oh, Liza, old thing
我要让全英格兰
I want all of England
为了赞美你而歌唱
Your praises to sing"
下个星期的5月20日
[SINGING] Next week on the 20th of May
我宣布为莉莎 杜利特节
I proclaim Liza Doolittle Day
所有的人都会赞美 你的荣耀
AII the people will celebrate The glory of you
不论你有什么愿望或要求 我都很乐意替你实现
And whatever you wish and want I gladly will do
我以非常有教养的方式 回答说 非常感谢 国王
"Thanks a lot, king," says I ln a manner well-bred
我想要的就是亨利 希金斯的人头
"But all I want is Henry Higgins' head"
照你说的办 国王把桌子一拍说道
- Done - Says the king with a stroke
卫兵 快去把那个家伙带过来
Guard, run and bring in the bloke
然后他们就押着你 亨利 希金斯 走到墙边
Then they'II march you, Henry Higgins To the wall
然后国王会对我说： 莉莎 你来下令行刑吧
- And the king will tell me: - Liza, sound the call
当他们高举起他们的步枪
As they raise their rifles higher
我开始喊 准备 瞄准 开火
I'II shout, "Ready, aim, fire"
呵 呵 呵 亨利 希金斯
Ho, ho, ho, Henry Higgins
下地狱去吧 亨利 希金斯
Down you'II go, Henry Higgins
你等着吧
Just you wait
A
A.
好了 伊莉莎 再念一遍
AII right, Eliza, say it again.
“西班牙的雨 大都降在平原上”
[IN COCKNEY ACCENT] "The rain in Spain stays mainly in the plain."
[希金斯叹息]
[HIGGINS SIGHS]
“西班牙的雨 大都降在平原上”
The rain in Spain stays mainly in the plain.
我不就是这么说的吗？
Didn't I say that?
不 伊莉莎 你没有那么“说”
No, Eliza, you didn't "say" that.
你甚至根本就没说过
You didn't even say that.
每晚临睡前 你原本做祈祷的时间
Every night before you get into bed, where you used to say your prayers,
我要你用来念“西班牙的雨 大都降在平原上”
I want you to say, "The rain in Spain stays mainly in the plain,"
50遍
50 times.
如果你不打算冒犯主的耳朵 你就会练得更好
You'II get much further with the Lord if you learn not to offend his ears.
现在教你“H”的发音
Now for your H's.
皮克林 这真是太可怕了
Pickering, this is going to be ghastly.
冷静点儿 希金斯 给这姑娘个机会
Control yourself, Higgins. Give the girl a chance.
噢 好吧 我认为你不该指望她第一次就能念对
Oh, well, I suppose you can't expect her to get it right the first time.
过来 伊莉莎 看仔细了
Come here, Eliza, and watch closely.
看
Now.
你看见那个火焰没有？
You see that flame?
每次你正确发出“H”的音
Every time you pronounce the letter H correctly,
火焰就会晃动
the flame will waver.
要是你没有发出“H”的音 火焰就会静止不动
And every time you drop your H, the flame will remain stationary.
这样你就知道你有没有念对了
That's how you'II know if you've done it correctly.
过段时间 你的耳朵就能听出其中的差别
ln time, your ear will hear the difference.
从镜子里看更好
See it better in the mirror.
现在 听仔细了
Now, listen carefully.
在哈特福德 赫里福德以及汉普郡 飓风几乎从未出现过
ln Hartford, Hereford and Hampshire, hurricanes hardly ever happen.
现在 跟着我念一遍
Now, repeat that after me.
在哈特福德 赫里福德以及汉普郡 飓风几乎从未出现过
ln Hartford, Hereford and Hampshire hurricanes hardly ever happen.
在哈特福德 赫里福德以及汉普郡
[IN COCKNEY ACCENT] "ln Hartford, Hereford and Hampshire,
飓风几乎从未出现过
hurricanes hardly ever happen."
噢 不对 不对 不对
Oh, no, no, no.
你没长耳朵吗？
Have you no ear at all?
- 要我再念一遍吗？ - 噢 不用了
- Should I do it over? - No, please.
还是从头开始 先练这个吧
Start from the very beginning. Just do this.
开始：哈 哈 哈
Go: Ha, ha, ha.
哈 哈 哈
Ha, ha, ha.
继续 继续 继续
Go on, go on, go on.
哈 哈 哈
Ha, ha, ha.
这种情况在印度也有吧 皮克林？
Does the same thing hold true in lndia, Pickering?
他们确实有这个习惯 省略类似“H”这样的字母的发音
ls it truly a habit to them, their dropping a letter like the letter H,
而用把它用在其它根本不存在的地方 比如把“ever”念成“hever”
using it where it doesn't belong, like "hever" instead of "ever"?
为什么这些奴隶 在学英语的时候
Why is it that Slavs, when they learn English,
总喜欢加重“G”的发音？
have a tendency to do it with G's?
- 他们把“linger”念成“linger” - 哈 哈 哈
- They say "linger" instead of "linger." ELIZA: Ha, ha, ha.
等你好不容易把他们纠正过来 他们又把“singer”念成“singer”
And then they turn right around and say "singer" instead of "singer."
我注意到奴隶们都把它加在那些不需要的地方
I've noticed the Slavs using it where it isn't needed,
他们要学英语 就得先纠正他们“G”的发音
they learn English, they have to do it with their G's.
[希金斯用鼻子吸气]
[HIGGINS SNIFFING]
那姑娘 希金斯
The girl, Higgins.
继续 继续 继续
Go on, go on, go on.
- 继续 - 哈 哈 哈
- Go on. - Ha, ha, ha.
可怜的希金斯教授
SERVANTS [SINGING]: Poor Professor Higgins
Poor Professor Higgins
昼夜不分
Night and day
辛苦工作
He slaves away
噢 可怜的希金斯教授
Oh, poor Professor Higgins
整天
AII day long
都在奔忙
On his feet
上上下下直到双腿麻木
Up and down until he's numb
既不休息
Doesn't rest
也不吃饭
Doesn't eat
连面包片儿都不碰一下
Doesn't touch a crumb
再来一遍 伊莉莎
Again, Eliza.
您能邀请我来真是太好了
How kind of you to let me come.
[IN COCKNEY ACCENT] How kind of you to let me come.
不 太好了 是太好了 不是“太好鸟”
No, kind of you. Kind of you.
“好” 您能邀请我来真是太好了
Kind. How kind of you to let me come.
- 您能邀请我来真是太好了 - 不 不对
- How kind of you to let me come. - No, no.
太好了 太好了 听起来就像“一杯茶” 是太好了
Kind of you. Kind of you. lt's like "cup of tea," kind of you.
一杯茶 说：“一杯茶”
Cup of tea. Say "cup of tea."
- 一杯茶 - 不 不对
- Cup of tea. - No, no.
一杯茶
A cup of tea.
这蛋糕太好吃了 真的 我想知道皮尔斯太太是从哪儿买的
lt's awfully good cake, this. I wonder where Mrs. Pearce gets it.
嗯 完全是一流的
Mm. First rate.
那些草莓馅儿饼也很美味
And those strawberry tarts are delicious.
你有尝过那些蛋糕吗？
Did you try the plain cake?
[叹息]
[SIGHS]
再来一遍
Try it again.
- 你有尝过那些... - 皮克林
- Did you try the--? - Pickering!
再来 伊莉莎
Again, Eliza.
一杯茶
[IN COCKNEY ACCENT] Cup of tea.
噢 不对
Oh, no.
你就听不出差别吗？
Can't you hear the difference?
看 把你的舌头向前伸
Look, put your tongue forward
直到它抵住你的下牙为止
until it squeezes on the top of your lower teeth.
- 然后跟我念“一” - 一
- And then say "cup." - Cup.
- 然后念：“杯” - 杯
- Then say "of." - Of.
现在念“一 一 一 杯 杯 杯”
Then say, "cup, cup, cup, of, of, of."
- 一 一 一 杯 杯 杯 - 一 一 一 杯 杯 杯
- Cup, cup, cup, of, of, of. - Cup, cup, cup, of, of, of.
一 一 杯 杯
Cup, cup-- Of, of--
天呐 希金斯 这茶真好喝
PICKERING: By Jove, Higgins, that was a glorious tea.
你干嘛不连最后一块草莓馅儿饼一起吃了？
Why don't you finish that last strawberry tart?
- 我已经吃不下了 - 噢 我没空吃
- I couldn't eat another thing. - Oh, I couldn't touch it.
- 浪费是可耻的 - 噢 不会被浪费的
- Shame to waste it. - Oh, it won't be wasted.
我知道谁最爱吃草莓馅儿饼了
I know somebody who's immensely fond of strawberry tarts.
[希金斯在叫]
[HIGGINS CHIRPING]
啊噢！
Ow!
可怜的希金斯教授
SERVANTS [SINGING]: Poor Professor Higgins
Poor Professor Higgins
辛勤工作
On he plods
不畏困难
Against all odds
噢 可怜的希金斯教授
Oh, poor Professor Higgins
晚上9点
Nine p.m.
晚上10点
Ten p.m.
每天都直到午夜
On through midnight every night
凌晨1点
One a.m.
凌晨2点
Two a.m.
凌晨3点
Three
Four.
Five.
6颗弹珠
Six marbles.
现在 我要把这些念出来 并且每个词都要清楚的发音
Now, I want you to read this and I want you to enunciate every word
就好像你的嘴里没有弹珠一样
just as if the marbles were not in your mouth.
花盆里长满了黑色的苔藓 一层层 厚厚的叠在一起
With blackest moss the flower-pots Were thickly crusted, one and all
每个词儿都要念得像钟声那样清楚
Each word clear as a bell.
花盆里长满了黑色的苔藓...
[MUMBLING] With blackest moss the flower-pots...
我办不到 我办不到
I can't. I can't.
我说 希金斯 有必要放这些石子吗？
PICKERING: I say, Higgins, are those pebbles really necessary?
德摩斯梯尼们都是这么练的 [德摩斯梯尼 公元前384—322年 古雅典雄辩家 天生口吃 以口含小石子练习演说]
lf they were necessary for Demosthenes,
那伊莉莎 杜利特也要这样练
they are necessary for Eliza Doolittle.
继续 伊莉莎
Go on, Eliza.
花盆里长满了黑色的苔藓
[MUMBLING] With blackest moss the flower-pots
一层层 厚厚的叠在一起
Were thickly crusted, one and all
我一个词儿都听不懂 一个词儿都没有
I can't understand a word, not a word.
花盆里长满了黑色的苔藓
With blackest moss the flower-pots
一层层 厚厚的叠在一起
Were thickly crusted, one and all
希金斯 也许那首诗对于这姑娘来说有点儿太难了
PICKERING: Higgins, perhaps that poem is a little too difficult for the girl.
你为什么不试些更简单类似“猫头鹰与波斯猫”？
Why don't you try something simpler, like "The Owl and the Pussycat?"
噢 没错 那首真的很美
Oh, yes, that's a charming one.
噢 皮克林 这姑娘说的我一个词儿都听不清！
Well, Pickering, I can't hear a word the girl is saying.
[大口喝水]
[GULPS]
怎么了？
What's the matter?
有一个被我吞下去了
I swallowed one.
噢 没关系 我多得是 把嘴张开
Oh, it doesn't matter, I got plenty more. Open your mouth.
1个 2个
One, two.
放弃吧 希金斯教授
SERVANTS [SINGING]: Quit, Professor Higgins
Quit, Professor Higgins
请听到我们的恳求吧
Hear our plea
否则等到发薪日我们就 不干了 希金斯教授
Or payday we will quit Professor Higgins
念“A”不是念“I”
"A" not "I"
念“O”不是念“ow”
"O" not "ow"
这样的声音我们的脑子里一次 又一次的回响着
Pounding, pounding in our brain
念“A”不是念“I”
"A" not "I"
念“O”不是念“ow”
"O" not "ow"
不要念“云” 要念“雨”
Don't say "rine," say "rain"
西班牙的雨
The rain in Spain
大都降在平原上
stays mainly in the plain.
我不行 我太累了
I can't. I'm so tired.
我真的太累了
I'm so tired.
看在上帝的面儿上 希金斯 现在绝对都已经凌晨3:00了
For God's sake, Higgins, it must be 3:00 in the morning.
理智一点
Do be reasonable.
我一向很理智
I am always reasonable.
伊莉莎
Eliza,
既然我脑袋这么疼都可以坚持 你也行
if I can go on with a blistering headache, you can.
我的头也很痛啊
I got a headache too.
噢 拿去吧
Oh, here.
我知道你的头很痛 也知道你很累
I know your head aches. I know you're tired.
我知道你的神经就如同肉店里的肉一样痛
I know your nerves are as raw as meat in a butcher's window.
但想想你的梦想吧
But think what you're trying to accomplish.
再想想你现在苦练的是什么
Just think what you're dealing with.
是庄重而高贵的英语
The majesty and grandeur of the English language,
是我们所拥有的最宝贵的财富
it's the greatest possession we have.
人们心里流出的最高贵的思想
The noblest thoughts that ever flowed through the hearts of men
都承载在它非凡的 充满想象力的
are contained in its extraordinary, imaginative
有如音乐般的声音里
and musical mixtures of sounds.
而那就是你自己所要征服的 伊莉莎
And that's what you've set yourself out to conquer, Eliza.
你也必然要征服的
And conquer it you will.
[叹息]
[SIGHS]
现在 再来一遍
Now, try it again.
西班牙的雨
[WITHOUT COCKNEY ACCENT] The rain in Spain
大都降在平原上
stays mainly in the plain.
你刚才说的什么？
What was that?
西班牙的雨
The rain in Spain
大都降在平原上
stays mainly in the plain.
再来
Again.
西班牙的雨 大都降在平原上
The rain in Spain stays mainly in the plain.
我想她已经做到了 我想她已经做到了
I think she's got it.
西班牙的雨 大都降在平原上
[SINGING] The rain in Spain Stays mainly in the plain
以圣乔治之名起誓 她已经做到了 以圣乔治之名起誓 她已经做到了
[SINGING] By George, she's got it By George, she's got it
现在再来一遍 是哪儿在下雨？
Now once again Where does it rain?
平原上
On the plain
哪儿的平原被淋湿了？
And where's that soggy plain?
西班牙
ln Spain
西班牙的雨 大都降在平原上
ALL [SINGING]: The rain in Spain Stays mainly in the plain
太好了！
Bravo!
西班牙的雨 大都降在平原上
The rain in Spain Stays mainly in the plain
在哈特福德 赫里福德 以及汉普郡
ln Hartford, Hereford And Hampshire
飓风几乎从未出现过
[WITHOUT COCKNEY ACCENT] Hurricanes hardly happen
您能邀请我来真是太好了
How kind of you to let me come
现在再来一遍 是哪儿在下雨？
Now, once again Where does it rain?
平原上
On the plain
那该死的平原在哪儿？
And where's that blasted plain?
西班牙
ln Spain
西班牙的雨 大都降在平原上
The rain in Spain Stays mainly in the plain
[大家的笑声]
[ALL LAUGH]
西班牙的雨 大都降在平原上
The rain in Spain Stays mainly in the plain
[希金斯在笑]
[HIGGINS LAUGH]
皮克林 皮克林 噢嘞 噢嘞
Pickering. Pickering. OIé. OIé.
[希金斯和伊莉莎在笑]
[HIGGINS & ELIZA LAUGHING]
噢嘞
OIé!
[希金斯在哼]
[HIGGINS HUMMING]
嘿 皮克林
Hey, Pickering.
希金斯：呵！嘿！
HIGGINS: Ho! Hey!
[所有人都在笑]
[ALL LAUGHING]
所有人：噢嘞
ALL: OIé!
[所有人都在笑]
[ALL LAUGHING]
噢 天呐
PICKERING: Oh, dear.
Oh, dear.
我们取得了很好的进展 皮克林
We're making fine progress, Pickering.
我想是时候让她出去试试了
I think the time has come to try her out.
- 您感觉还好吗 希金斯先生？ - 是的 我很好 皮尔斯太太
- Are you feeling all right, Mr. Higgins? - Yes, I'm feeling fine, Mrs. Pearce.
- 你感觉怎么样？ - 非常好 先生 谢谢您
- How are you? - Very well, sir, thank you.
让我们带她去公共场合看她表现如何
Let's test her in public and see how she fares.
希金斯先生 我被一声可怕的巨响吵醒了
Mr. Higgins, I was awakened by a dreadful pounding.
你知道出什么事了吗？
Do you know what it might have been?
巨响？我什么声响都没听到
Pounding? I didn't hear any pounding.
- 你听到了吗 皮克林？ - 没有
- You do, Pickering? - No.
要知道 如果继续这样 皮尔斯太太 你最好去见一下医生
You know, if this goes on, Mrs. Pearce, you'd better see a doctor.
- 我想到了 我们带她去赛马会 - 赛马会？
- I know. We'II take her to the races. PICKERING: The races?
- 我母亲在阿斯科特赛马会有一个包厢 - 你是不是还是先同你母亲商量一下？
- My mother's box at Ascot. - You'II consult your mother first?
噢 没错 当然
Oh, yes, of course.
不 我想我最好还是让她大吃一惊比较好 现在我们还是去睡觉吧
No, I think I should better surprise her. Now let's go to bed.
明天早上第一件事 我们要出去给她买身衣服
First thing in the morning, we'II go out and we'II buy her a dress.
现在你继续练 伊莉莎
Now get on with your work, Eliza.
皮尔斯：不过 希金斯先生 现在已经是凌晨了
PEARCE: But, Mr. Higgins, it's early in the morning.
还有什么时间比在凌晨练习更好的吗？
What better time to work than early in the morning?
- 知道人们都上哪儿买女士穿的礼服吗？ - 惠特利 当然是去那儿
- Where does one buy a lady's gown? - Whitley's, of course.
- 你是怎么知道的？ - 大家都知道
- How do you know that? - Common knowledge.
我们不要给她买那种太过华丽的
Let's not buy her anything too flowery.
我讨厌那种礼服上这里一团那里一团的
I despise those gowns with sort of weeds here and weeds there.
我想买的是那种既简单得体又不失高雅的
I wanna buy something sort of simple and modest and elegant,
就是这样的
is what's called for.
也许得再配上一个蝴蝶结
Perhaps with a bow.
嗯 我认为这样看上去正好
Yes, I think that's just right.
[皮克林的笑声]
[PICKERING LAUGHS]
你练习得太努力了
You've all been working much too hard.
我想你马上就要挺不住了
I think the strain is beginning to show.
伊莉莎 我不管希金斯先生怎么说
Eliza, I don't care what Mr. Higgins says,
你必须得放下书去睡觉
you must put down your books and go to bed.
床啊 床 我不能上床去睡觉
[SINGING] Bed, bed I couldn't go to bed
我脑袋轻飘飘的 没办法躺下
My head's too light To try to set it down
睡觉啊 睡觉 今夜我无法入睡
Sleep, sleep I couldn't sleep tonight
就算给我王冠上所有的宝石
Not for all the jewels in the crown
我可以跳上一整晚
I could have danced all night
跳过了还想跳
And still have begged for more
我要展开自己的翅膀
I could have spread my wings
去做成千种
And done a thousand things
我从未做过的事
I've never done before
我永远都不会知道 是什么让我如此兴奋
I'II never know What made it so exciting
为什么就在一瞬间 我的心飞了起来
Why all at once My heart took flight
我只知道当他
I only know when he
同我跳舞的时候
Began to dance with me
我可以一直跳啊 跳啊 跳啊
I could have danced Danced, danced
一整晚
AII night
现在都3：00过了
SERVANT 1 [SINGING]: lt's after 3 now
你不认为现在
SERVANT 2 [SINGING]: Don't you agree now
- 她应该去睡觉 - 她应该去睡觉
- She ought to be in bed - She ought to be in bed
伊莉莎：- 我可以一直跳啊 - 你已经累坏了
ELIZA: I could have danced - You're tired out
伊莉莎：- 一整晚 - 你必须得去睡觉
ELIZA: AII night - You must be dead
- 我可以一直跳啊 - 你的面色苍白
- I could have danced - Your face is drawn
- 一整晚 - 你的眼睛通红
- AII night - Your eyes are red
- 跳过了 - 拜托了 是时候说晚安了
- And still have - Now say good night, please
- 还想跳 - 求你了 把灯关掉
- Begged for more - Turn out the light, please
你现在真该睡觉了
lt's really time for you to be in bed
- 我要展开 - 照我们说的
- I could have spread - Do come along
- 自己的翅膀 - 去做
- My wings - Do as you're told
- 去做成千种 - 否则皮尔斯太太就要骂人了
- And done a thousand things - Or Mrs. Pearce is apt to scold
- 我从未 - 你会起得很晚的 小姐
- I've never - You're up too late, miss
- 做过的事 - 可以断定 小姐
- Done before - And sure as fate, miss
你会着凉的
You'II catch a cold
我永远都不会知道 是什么让我如此兴奋
I'II never know What made it so exciting
为什么就在一瞬间 我的心飞了起来
Why all at once My heart took flight
- 我只知道 - 把你的书放下
- I only know - Put down your book
- 当他 - 还要接着练习呢
- When he - The work will keep
- 同我跳舞 - 该停下
- Began to dance - Now settle down
- 的时候 - 去睡觉了
- With me - And go to sleep
我可以一直跳啊 跳啊 跳啊
I could have danced Danced, danced
一整晚
AII night
我明白 亲爱的
I understand, dear
这是很大的成就 亲爱的
lt's all been grand, dear
但是现在是时候去睡觉了
But now it's time to sleep
我可以跳上一整晚
I could have danced all night
跳过了还想跳
And still have begged for more
我要展开自己的翅膀
I could have spread my wings
去做成千种
And done a thousand things
我从未做过的事
I've never done before
我永远都不会知道 是什么让我如此兴奋
I'II never know What made it so exciting
为什么就在一瞬间 我的心飞了起来
Why all at once My heart took flight
我只知道当他
I only know when he
同我跳舞的时候
Began to dance with me
我可以一直跳啊 跳啊 跳啊
I could have danced Danced, danced
一整晚
AII night
所有的公爵 伯爵 还有贵族都在这里
ALL [SINGING]: Every duke and earl And peer is here
所有应该到场的人都在这里 都在这里
Everyone who should be here ls here
这是多么盛大 华丽的景象
What a smashing Positively dashing spectacle
阿斯科特赛马会公开赛日
The Ascot opening day
所有的赛马都站在栏门前
At the gate are all the horses
只等一声令下便驰骋如飞
Waiting for the cue to fly away
么多么扣人心 精彩绝伦
What a gripping, absolutely ripping
阿斯科特赛马会公开赛日那天
Moment at the Ascot opening day
脉搏加速
Pulses rushing
面色涨红
Faces flushing
心在狂跳
Heartbeats speed up
我从未如此
I have never been so keyed up
像现在这样每一秒都感到紧张
Any second now
比赛马上就要开始
They'II begin to run
听 钟声响了
Hark, a bell is ringing
他们冲了出去 看呐！
They are springing forward Look!
比赛开始了
lt has begun
[万马奔腾]
[HORSES GALLOPING]
这是多么令人疯狂的时刻啊
What a frenzied moment that was
他们就 不知疲倦吗？
Didn't they maintain An exhausting pace?
多么紧张 绝对刺激
'Twas a thrilling, absolutely chilling
阿斯科特赛马会公开赛
Running of the Ascot opening race
女1：噢 不 不 这是真的
WOMAN 1 : Oh, no. No, it's true.
- 趁这个机会 - 啊
- This is the time. MAN: Yeah.
女2：是的
WOMAN 2: Yes.
我女儿是...
- Yes. WOMAN 3: My daughter's...
女4：他们有的是时间
WOMAN 4: They've had enough time.
您认为这次的比赛怎么样？
What did you think of the race?
希金斯：母亲
HIGGINS: Mother.
亨利 真让人意外
Henry. What a disagreeable surprise.
您好 母亲
Hello, Mother.
- 您看起来气色不错 - 你来这儿干什么？
- How nice you look. - What are you doing here?
你答应再也不来阿斯科特赛马会的 赶紧回去
You promised never to come to Ascot. Go home at once.
- 我不能那样 我来这儿是有事要办的 - 不行 亨利 你必须离开
- I can't, I'm here on business. - No, Henry, you must.
听着 我是认真的 你这样会冒犯我的朋友的
Now, I'm quite serious. You offend all my friends.
要是让他们看到你 我以后就再没脸和他们见面了
The moment they meet you, I never see them again.
顺便说一下 您穿的这身并不适合来阿斯科特赛马会
Besides, you aren't dressed for Ascot.
我换了衬衣了
I changed my shirt.
好了 听着 母亲 我有件事要交给你去办 一件有关语音学的事
Now, listen, Mother, I've got a job for you, a phonetics job.
- 我选了一个女孩儿 - 亨利
- I've picked up a girl. - Henry.
噢 别乱想 亲爱的 这与爱情没有关系 她是个卖花女
Oh, no, darling, not a love affair. She's a flower girl.
我要带她出席今年的大使招待舞会
I'm taking her to the annual Embassy Ball.
- 不过我想先带她出来试一下 - 你说什么？
- But I want to try her out first. - I beg your pardon?
- 拜托 你知道大使招待舞会的 - 我当然知道 那个舞会 不过...
- Well, you know the Embassy Ball. - Of course, I know the ball, but--
所以今天我请她到你的包厢里 你明白了吗？
So I invited her to your box today, do you understand?
- 普通的卖花女？ - 完全没错
- Common flower girl? - She'II be all right.
我已经教会她如何言谈得体
I taught her how to speak properly.
她的举止也受过严格的指导
She has strict instructions as to her behavior.
她只会两个话题
She is to keep to two subjects.
天气还有每个人的健康 “天气不错”以及“你好吗？”
The weather and everybody's health. "Fine day" and "How do you do?"
总之不能让她一个人应付
Not to let herself go on things in general.
你去陪她吧 亲爱的 有你在不会有问题的
Help her along, darling. You'II be quite safe.
不会有问题？在看比赛的时候谈论别人的健康吗？
Safe? To talk about one's health in the middle of a race?
噢 她总得谈点儿什么
Well, she's got to talk about something.
- 那女孩儿现在在哪儿？ - 她现在还来不了
- Where is the girl now? - She's being pinned.
我们替她买的有些衣服不合身
Some of the clothes we bought her didn't quite fit.
我告诉皮克林我们得把她一起带来
I told Pickering we should have taken her with us.
谢天谢地 你在这儿
EYNSFORD-HILL: Thank goodness you're here.
- 埃恩斯福德-希尔太太 - 下午好 希金斯夫人
MRS. HIGGINS: Mrs. Eynsford-Hill. - Good afternoon, Mrs. Higgins.
你认识我儿子吧 亨利
You know my son, Henry.
噢 你好吗？
Oh, how do you do?
- 我以前见过你 - 我不记得了
- I've seen you somewhere before. - I don't know.
噢 没关系 请坐吧
Oh, it doesn't matter. You better sit down.
- 勃克辛登女士 - 该死的他们都哪儿去了？
- Lady Boxington. - Where the devil can they be?
- 勃克辛登勋爵 - 哈！
- Lord Boxington. - Ha!
皮克林上校 您正好赶上喝茶
MRS. HIGGINS: Colonel Pickering, you're just in time for tea.
谢谢您 希金斯夫人
Thank you, Mrs. Higgins.
我能向您介绍一下伊莉莎 杜利特小姐吗？
May I introduce Miss Eliza Doolittle?
亲爱的 杜利特小姐
MRS. HIGGINS: My dear, Miss Doolittle.
您能邀请我来真是太好了
[WITHOUT COCKNEY ACCENT] How kind of you to let me come.
我很荣幸 亲爱的
MRS. HIGGINS: Delighted, my dear.
这位是勃克辛登女士
Lady Boxington.
-你好吗？ -你好吗？
- How do you do? - How do you do?
这位是勃克辛登勋爵
Lord Boxington.
-你好吗？ -你好吗？
- How do you do? - How do you do?
这是埃恩斯福德-希尔太太和杜利特小姐
Mrs. Eynsford-Hill, Miss Doolittle.
-你好吗？ -你好吗？
- How do you do? - How do you do?
这位是弗雷迪 埃恩斯福德-希尔
And Freddy Eynsford-Hill.
你好吗？
How do you do?
杜利特小姐
Miss Doolittle.
下午好 希金斯教授
Good afternoon, Professor Higgins.
第一场比赛太精彩了 杜利特小姐
The first race was very exciting, Miss Doolittle.
你错过了 我真替你可惜
I'm so sorry that you missed it.
你觉得会下雨吗？
Will it rain, do you think?
西班牙的雨 大都降在平原上
The rain in Spain stays mainly in the plain.
[希金斯轻敲]
[HIGGINS TAPPING]
不过在哈特福德 赫里福德 及汉普郡
But in Hartford, Hereford and Hampshire,
飓风几乎从未出现过
hurricanes hardly ever happen.
[弗雷迪在笑]
[FREDDY LAUGHS]
真是非常有趣
How awfully funny.
有说得不对的吗 年轻人？我打赌我念得很对
What is wrong with that, young man? I bet I got it right.
说得很好
Smashing.
天气会不会突然转凉？
Hasn't it suddenly turned chilly?
我可希望我们不会遇到毫无预兆的忽然降温
I do hope we won't have any unseasonable cold spells.
它们会让很多人得上流行感冒
They bring on so much influenza.
而我们全家人都很容易感染
And the whole of our family is susceptible to it.
我姑妈就死于流行感冒
My aunt died of influenza.
他们是这样告诉我的
So they said.
但我相信是他们把那个老太太“送走”了
But it's my belief they done the old woman in.
把她“送走”了？
MRS. HIGGINS: Done her in?
是啊 上帝保佑
Yes, Lord love you.
她怎么可能死于流行感冒
Why should she die of influenza
之前那年她得了白喉都挺过来了？
when she come through diphtheria right enough the year before?
当时她脸色都变成那种深蓝色了
Fairly blue with it, she was.
他们全都以为她已经死了
They all thought she was dead.
可我父亲 不停地朝她喉咙里灌杜松子酒
But my father, he kept ladling gin down her throat.
[希金斯在呻吟]
[HIGGINS GROANS]
然后她突然就活过来了
Then she come to so sudden,
还把勺子的勺碗咬了下来
she bit the bowl off the spoon.
[弗雷迪在笑]
[FREDDY LAUGHS]
我的天
Dear me.
所以 一个有这么大力气的女人怎么
Now, what call would a woman with that strength in her
可能死于流行感冒？
have to die of influenza?
为什么原本用来给她买新草帽的钱现在成了我的？
What become of her new straw hat that should have come to me?
[听不见的对话]
[INAUDIBLE DIALOGUE]
有人把它省下来了
Somebody pinched it.
所以要我说
And what I say is,
他们就是这样不断地省下钱 然后把她“送走”了
them that's pinched it done her in.
把她“送走”了？你是说 把她“送走”了？
Done her in? Done her in, did you say?
这是什么意思？
Whatever does it mean?
噢 这是个新的说法
Oh, that's the new small talk.
把某个人“送走”就相当于把他们杀掉
To do somebody in means to kill them.
可你不会真的认为你姑妈是被谋杀的吧？
But you surely don't believe your aunt was killed?
怎么不会？
Do I not?
他们为了一根帽针的钱也不会让她活着 更别说是帽子
Them she lived with would have killed her for a hatpin, let alone a hat.
可你父亲的办法也不对
But it can't have been right for your father
像那样朝她喉咙里灌烈性酒
to pour spirits down her throat like that.
那样也许会杀了她了
lt might have killed her.
不可能
Not her.
杜松子酒对她来说就像母乳一样
Gin was mother's milk to her.
而且 他朝自己的喉咙里也灌了不少
Besides, he poured so much down his own throat,
他知道这样做有好处
he knew the good of it.
你是说他喝醉了？
Do you mean that he drank?
喝醉 照我说 还差得远
Drank, my word, something chronic.
[弗雷迪在笑]
[FREDDY LAUGHING]
嘿 你偷偷笑什么呢？
Here, what are you sniggering at?
那个新说法
lt's the new small talk.
你说得太有趣了
You do it so awfully well.
噢 要是我说的没错 那你又偷偷笑什么呢？
Well, if I was doing it proper, what was you sniggering at?
我说了什么不该说的话吗？
Have I said anything I oughtn't?
希金斯：噢 不
HIGGINS: Oh, no.
没有 亲爱的
Not at all, my dear.
噢 不管怎样 您真是太宽容了
Well, lots of mercy, anyhow.
我一直都这么说...
What I always say--
我不知道在下一场比赛开始前 还有没有时间可以下注
I don't know whether there's time before the next race to place a bet.
- 走吧 亲爱的 - 我可不那么认为
- But come, my dear. MRS. HIGGINS: I don't suppose so.
我在7号下了注
I have a bet on Number 7.
要是您也会选它的话我会很高兴的
I should be so happy if you would take it.
这样您就会更加喜欢这场比赛
You'II enjoy the race ever so much more.
你真是太好了
That's very kind of you.
- 他的名字叫多弗 - 走吧 亲爱的
- His name is Dover. PICKERING: Come along, my dear.
他们再一次 在起跑线上准备
ALL [SINGING]: There they are again Lining up to run
他们紧握缰绳 做好了比赛的准备
Now they're holding steady They are ready for it
看呐 比赛开始了
Look, it has begun
[万马奔腾]
[HORSES GALLOPING]
加油
Come on.
加油啊 多弗 加油
Come on, Dover. Come on.
加油 多弗
Come on, Dover.
加油
Come on.
加油 多弗！
[IN COCKNEY ACCENT] Come on, Dover!
把你漂亮的屁股抬高点儿！
Move your blooming ass!
[所有人在笑]
[ALL MURMURING]
男：别慌 亲爱的 是啊
MAN: Don't upset yourself, my dear. WOMAN: Please.
噢 我的天
Oh, my dear.
你不是认真的吧 亨利
You're not serious, Henry.
你不会带算带她出席大使招待舞会吧？
You don't expect to take her to the Embassy Ball?
你不认为她已经准备好了吗？
Don't you think she's ready for it?
亲爱的 亨利 她那样子只配上货船
Dear, Henry, she's ready for a canal barge.
嗯 她的语言也许还需要再加强一下 不过...
Well, her language may need a little refining, but--
噢 我说真的 亨利
Oh, really, Henry.
要是你不清楚这整个计划有多么的不可能
lf you cannot see how impossible this whole project is,
那你绝对是在拿她耍孩子气
then you must be absolutely potty about her.
我建议你放弃 不要再让你自己还有这个女孩儿继续下去了
I advise you to give it up and not put yourself and this girl through more.
放弃？这是我所经历过的最为使人着迷的冒险
Give it up? It's the most fascinating venture I've ever undertaken.
皮克林和我从早忙到晚都为了它 里边倾注着我们的心血
Pickering and I are at it from morning till night. lt fills our whole lives.
教伊莉莎 同伊莉莎说话 听伊莉莎说话 打扮伊莉莎
Teaching Eliza, talking to Eliza, listening to Eliza, dressing Eliza.
什么？
What?
你们就像两个孩子在玩着你们活的玩偶
You're a pretty pair of babies playing with your live doll.
车来了
Here's the car.
弗雷迪：我说 先生...
FREDDY: I say, sir...
晚上好 先生
Good evening, sir.
晚餐准备好了吗？我饿坏了
Dinner ready? I'm famished.
马上为您准备 先生
lmmediately, sir.
皮尔斯：晚上好 希金斯教授
PEARCE: Good evening, Professor Higgins.
当她说起 她的姑妈怎样咬断了勺子
[SINGING] When she mentioned How her aunt bit off the spoon
她完全把我迷住了
She completely done me in
我的心已踏上 前往月球的旅程
And my heart went on a journey To the moon
当她讲到自己父亲 还有杜松子酒
When she told about her father And the gin
我从未见过 比这更为迷人的胡闹
And I never saw A more enchanting farce
当她叫喊着： “把你漂亮的...”
Than the moment when she shouted: "Move your blooming--"
- 有什么事 先生？ - 杜利特小姐在吗？
- Yes, sir? - Is Miss Doolittle in?
- 我该怎么通报呢？ - 弗雷迪 埃恩斯福德-希尔
- Whom shall I say is calling? - Freddy Eynsford-Hill.
噢 要是她想不起我是谁
Oh, if she doesn't remember who I am,
就跟她说我就是那个对着她偷偷笑的人
tell her I'm the chap who was sniggering at her.
好的 先生
Yes, sir.
- 能帮我把这个交给她吗？ - 好的 先生
- And will you give her these? - Yes, sir.
您要进来吗？
Wouldn't you like to come in?
他们正在用晚餐 您可以先等一下
They're having dinner, but you may wait.
不 不用 谢谢 我就是来她住的这条街上喝一杯的
No. No, thank you. I want to drink in the street where she lives.
好的 先生
Yes, sir.
我过去常在 这条街上散步
I have often walked Down this street before
过去脚下的人行道 总是那样的平稳
But the pavement always stayed Beneath my feet before
可忽然间 我弹起几层楼高
AII at once am I Several stories high
只因为知道这条街上 有你住着
Knowing I'm on the street Where you live
市中心里 有丁香树吗？
Are there lilac trees ln the heart of town?
在市里的任一个地方 你能听到百灵的鸣叫吗？
Can you hear a lark ln any other part of town?
有什么地方会从每道门里 都弥散出诱人的魔力吗？
Does enchantment pour Out of every door?
没有 只有有在这条 有你住的街上
No, it's just on the street Where you live
噢 这飘然的感觉
And, oh, the towering feeling
只因为知道你就在不远处
Just to know somehow you are near
那是种难以抗拒的感觉
The overpowering feeling
或许在下一秒 你就会出现在我眼前
That any second You may suddenly appear
即便人们停下看着我 也不会打扰到我
People stop and stare They don't bother me
因为在这个星球上除了这儿 别的地方 我都不愿意停留
For there's nowhere else on earth That I would rather be
任时光流逝
Let the time go by
我也不在乎 只要我能留在
I won't care if I can be here
这条有你住的街上
On the street where you live
皮尔斯：噢 先生
PEARCE: Oh, sir.
我很抱歉的转告您 先生
I'm terribly sorry, sir.
杜利特小姐说她不想见任何人 再也不想
Miss Doolittle says she doesn't want to see anyone ever again.
- 这是为什么？她真是叫人不敢相信 - 她就是这么对我说的 先生
- But why? She was unbelievable. - So I've been told, sir.
您还要我再转达什么吗？
ls there any further message?
好的 告诉她我会等她
Yes. Tell her that I'II wait.
噢 那可能要好几天 先生 甚至好几个星期
Oh, but it might be days, sir, even weeks.
你难道看不出来吗？我很乐意等
But don't you see? I'II be happier here.
即便人们停下看着我 也不会打扰到我
People stop and stare They don't bother me
因为在这个星球上除了这儿 别的地方 我都不愿意停留
For there's nowhere else on earth That I would rather be
任时光流逝
Let the time go by
我也不在乎 只要我能留在
I won't care if I can be here
这条有你住的街上
On the street where you live
说真的 希金斯 再这样继续下去是不人道的
lt really is, Higgins. lt's inhuman to continue.
你有意识到在6个星期的时间里 你还要教多少东西给这个可怜的姑娘吗？
You realize what you've got to teach this poor girl in six weeks?
你得教会她走路 说话
Teach her to walk, talk,
该怎样向公爵 勋爵 主教 大使表示问候
address a duke, a lord, a bishop, an ambassador.
这完全是不可能的
lt's absolutely impossible.
希金斯 我要告诉你 我决定取消这次的打赌
Higgins, I'm trying to tell you that I want to call off the bet.
我知道你是个固执的人 我也是
I know you're a stubborn man, but so am I.
这个试验结束了
This experiment is over.
除非国王下令
And nothing short of an order from the king
才能迫使我放弃
could force me to recant.
现在 如果你能原谅的话
Now, if you'II excuse me.
你明白吗 希金斯 打赌取消了
You understand, Higgins, it's over.
希金斯
Higgins.
希金斯 要是今晚在使馆里发生任何意外
Higgins, if there's any mishap at the embassy tonight,
要是让杜利特小姐陷入任何窘境
if Miss Doolittle suffers any embarrassment whatever,
这只能记在你的头上
it'II be on your head alone.
伊莉莎什么都可以做到
Eliza can do anything.
要是她被揭穿了呢？想想阿斯科特赛马会的事儿吧
Suppose she's discovered? Remember Ascot.
要是她又犯了别的什么可怕的错误呢？
Suppose she makes another ghastly mistake?
在舞会上可不会有马 皮克林
There will be no horses at the ball, Pickering.
想想看要是那样会有多可怕
PICKERING: Think how agonizing it would be.
噢 要是今晚真的发生什么 我自己也不知道该怎么办
Oh, if anything happened tonight, I don't know what I'd do.
你照样还可以回你的部队去
You could always rejoin your regiment.
这不是草率行事的时候 希金斯
This is no time for flippancy, Higgins.
6个星期来你训练这个女孩儿的方式
The way you've driven the girl the last six weeks
都相当的不体面
has exceeded all bounds of common decency.
看在上帝的面上 别踱来踱去了
For God's sake, stop pacing up and down.
你就不能找个地方坐下吗？
Can't you settle somewhere?
喝点儿淡酒 它能让你紧张的神经缓和下来
Have some port. lt'II quieten your nerves.
我可不紧张
I'm not nervous.
- 酒在哪儿？ - 就在钢琴上
- Where is it? - On the piano.
- 车来了 先生 - 噢 很好
- The car is here, sir. - Oh, good.
- 通知杜利特小姐 - 好的
- Tell Miss Doolittle. - Yes.
告诉杜利特小姐 我敢说那件该死的礼服根本不合适
Tell Miss Doolittle indeed. I bet you that damned gown doesn't fit.
我警告过你不要找那些法国设计师
I warned you about these French designers.
我们应该去找一家英国店铺 并不是所有人的眼光都和我们一样
We should've gone to an English shop, everyone would've been on our side.
- 要来杯淡酒吗？ - 不 谢谢
- Have a glass of port? - No, thank you.
你就这么有把握这姑娘能记住你给她填进去的一切？
Are you so sure this girl will retain everything you've hammered into her?
嗯 我们等着看吧
Well, we shall see.
要是她记不住呢？
Suppose she doesn't?
那我就赌输了
I lose my bet.
希金斯 在这件事上我最受不了你
Higgins, there's one thing I can't stand about you,
那就是你太过自以为是
that's your confounded complacency.
尤其是在这种时候 如此危急关头
At a moment like this, with so much at stake,
这太不礼貌了 你竟然拒绝来一杯淡酒
it's utterly indecent that you don't need a glass of port.
那姑娘怎么养了？从你的行为看好像她完全不重要
And what about the girl? You act as though she doesn't matter at all.
噢 胡说 皮克林 她当然重要
Oh, rubbish, Pickering. Of course she matters.
你以为这几个月我都在忙什么？
What do you think I've been doing all these months?
还有什么事情比得上将一个人
What could possibly matter more than to take a human being
通过改变她说话的声音
and change her into a different human being
将她变成一个完全不同的人更重要的？
by creating a new speech for her?
它将阶级与阶级之间还有灵魂与灵魂之间
lt's filling up the deepest gap
这道最深的鸿沟填补了起来
that separates class from class and soul from soul.
噢 她是如此重要
No, she matters immensely.
[脚步声]
[FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING]
杜利特小姐 你看起来真漂亮
Miss Doolittle, you look beautiful.
谢谢 皮克林上校
[WITHOUT COCKNEY ACCENT] Thank you, Colonel Pickering.
你不认为很漂亮吗 希金斯？
Don't you think so, Higgins?
不错 确实不错
Not bad. Not bad at all.
幕间休息（1MIN AND 30SECONDS）
男仆：休 德维尔夫妇
BUTLER: Mr. and Mrs. Hugh Deuvile.
名副其实的尊贵客人 詹姆士 克劳伦斯少将
Major General the right honorable Sir James Clarence.
格伦林侯爵夫妇
Marquis and Marquise of Glenning.
苏珊娜 德 隆利夫人
Lady Suzanna De Longly.
阿尔伯特爵士与德林夫人
Sir Albert and Lady Derring.
尊贵的阿奇博尔德爵士及凯瑟琳 赫琳夫人
Honorable Mr. Archibald and Lady Catherine Herring.
大师 大师
Maestro. Maestro.
- 您不记得我了吗？ - 不记得 你是谁啊？
- Don't you remember me? - No. Who the devil are you?
我是您的学生
I'm your pupil.
您的第一位 也是您最伟大的 最出色的学生
Your first, your greatest, your best pupil.
我是佐尔腾 卡帕西 那个天才儿童
I'm Zoltan Karpathy, that marvelous boy.
噢
Oh.
是我让您的名字传遍了整个欧洲
I made your name famous throughout Europe.
是您教我语音学的 您不可能把我忘了
You teach me phonetics, you cannot forget me.
你怎么不把你的头发剪短点儿？
Why don't you have your hair cut?
我可没有您那样仪表堂堂的外貌
I don't have your imposing appearance,
您那身材 还有面貌
your figure, your brow.
要是我把头发剪短了 就没人会注意我了
lf I had my hair cut, nobody would notice me.
你这些旧硬币是从哪弄来的
Where did you get all these old coins?
它们代表着各种语言
These are decorations for language.
特兰西瓦尼亚的女王今晚将要出席
The queen of Transylvania is here this evening.
出席这样的官方国际性的聚会 她可少不了我
I'm indispensable to her at these official international parties.
我会说32种语言 在欧洲的每个贵族我都认识
I speak 32 languages, I know everyone in Europe.
没有哪个冒牌货可以逃出我的眼睛
No impostor can escape my detection.
卡帕西教授
Professor Karpathy.
这位是希腊大使
The Greek ambassador.
希腊是我的故乡
Greek my foot.
他装作一点儿不会英语 可他骗不了我
He pretends not to know any English, but he cannot deceive me.
他是约克郡一个钟表匠的儿子
He's the son of a Yorkshire watchmaker.
[希金斯在笑]
[HIGGINS LAUGHS]
即便他故意将英语说得如此拙劣
He speaks English so villainously
他只要说出一个词儿就会暴露他的底细
that he cannot utter a word without betraying his origin.
我不会揭穿他 不过我要好好敲他一笔
I help him pretend, but I make him pay through the nose.
我要让那些冒牌货全都付出代价
I make them all pay.
抱歉 先生 有人请您上楼一趟
Excuse me, sir, you are wanted upstairs.
- 女王陛下要你过去 - 噢 失陪
- Her Excellency asked for you. - Oh, excuse me.
男仆：萨克森子爵夫妇
BUTLER: Viscount and Viscountess Saxon.
约克郡男爵夫妇
Baron and Baroness of Yorkshire.
盖伊爵士和斯科特 奥克兰夫人
Sir Guy and Lady Skot Ackland.
德梅鲁伯爵夫妇
The Count and Countess Demerau.
希尔雅德子爵夫妇
The Viscount and Viscountess Hillyard.
理查德 兰瑟爵士夫妇
Mr. and Mrs. Richard Lanser.
克兰德斯勋爵夫妇
Lord and Lady Clanders.
伊莉莎杜利特小姐 皮克林上校
Miss Eliza Doolittle, Colonel Pickering.
- 希金斯教授 - 晚上好 杜利特小姐
- Professor Higgins. - Good evening, Miss Doolittle.
女王陛下
Your Excellency.
- 杜利特小姐 - 您好吗？
- Miss Doolittle. - How do you do?
- 晚上好 上校 - 晚上好
- Good evening, colonel. - Good evening.
- 噢 上校 - 什么事？
- Oh, colonel. - What?
女士：今晚您身边的这位年轻女士可真迷人
LADY: What an enchanting young lady you have with you this evening.
- 谢谢 - 噢 她是谁？
PICKERING: Thank you. - Well, who is she?
噢 这是我同希金斯的一位表妹 抱歉
Oh, a cousin of mine. And Higgins. Excuse me.
希金斯教授
Professor Higgins.
远远地看一眼 她就如同生在花园中的花一样
Such a faraway look as if she's always lived in a garden.
说的没错 确实跟花园差不多
So she has, a sort of garden.
[聊天的声音]
[CHATTERING]
女1：那是她儿子吗？
WOMAN 1 : ls that her son?
女2：我可不相信...
WOMAN 2: I don't believe in...
女3：我要不行了
WOMAN 3: I shall die.
[几乎听不见的讲话声]
[SPEAKING INAUDIBLY]
亨利 必须马上带伊莉莎回去 这里有位语言专家
Henry must take Eliza home at once. There's a language expert here.
那种 你知道的 鉴伪专家
Sort of, you know, sort of impostorologist.
麻烦你再说一遍
I beg your pardon.
同皮克林上校一起的那位年轻女士
The young lady with Colonel Pickering.
去问问她是谁
Find out who she is.
遵命
With pleasure.
现在情况非常危险
The whole situation is highly explosive.
女1：我们只听最有权威的
WOMAN 1 : We heard on the best authority.
佐尔腾 再告诉我更多关于希腊大使的事
Tell me, Zoltan, some more about the Greek ambassador.
我很乐意 不过首先我想请你将我介绍给这位光彩照人的女士
Gladly, but first I would love you to present me to this glorious creature.
他真的是从约克郡来的吗？
Does he really come from Yorkshire?
[喇叭声]
[HORNS PLAYING]
男仆：尊贵的 特兰西瓦尼亚女王陛下
BUTLER: Her Majesty, the queen of Transylvania
同格雷戈尔王子殿下
and his Royal Highness, Prince Gregor.
[乐队演奏]
[BAND PLAYING]
很迷人 太迷人了
Charming. Quite charming.
这位是杜利特小姐 夫人
Miss Doolittle, ma'am.
男：真是个迷人的女孩儿
MAN: Such a charming girl.
女1：从她说话的时候我们就知道了
WOMAN 1 : We'II know when we hear her announced.
女2：看那身漂亮的舞会礼服
WOMAN 2: That's a beautiful ball gown.
[聊天的声音]
[CHATTERING]
女3：那是她的儿子吗？
WOMAN 3: ls that her son?
[聊天的声音]
[CHATTERING]
杜利特小姐 我的孩子希望能同你跳支舞
Miss Doolittle, my son would like to dance with you.
[女王说外语]
[QUEEN SPEAKING FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
[乐队在演奏华尔兹]
[BAND PLAYING WALTZ]
伊莉莎？
Eliza?
[几乎听不见的讲话声]
[SPEAKING INAUDIBLY]
[乐队停止演奏]
[BAND STOPS PLAYING]
[几乎听不见的讲话声]
[SPEAKING INAUDIBLY]
[朦朦胧胧的说话声]
[SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY]
[人们的低声碎语]
[PEOPLE WHISPERING INDISTINCTLY]
[男人在低声碎语]
[MAN WHISPERING INDISTINCTLY]
[希金斯在笑]
[HIGGINS LAUGHING]
简直太不可思议了
PICKERING: Absolutely fantastic.
[男人在笑]
[MEN LAUGHING]
希金斯：只能说蠢货太多了
HIGGINS: A lot of tomfoolery.
这真是巨大的成功
PICKERING: lt was an immense achievement.
噢 希金斯先生？
Well, Mr. Higgins?
凯旋而归 皮尔斯太太 完全是胜利凯旋
A triumph, Mrs. Pearce. A total triumph.
希金斯 你太棒了 绝对是最棒的
Higgins, you were superb. Absolutely superb.
现在跟我们实话说吧 你就没那么一两次有感到紧张吗？
Tell us the truth now, weren't you a bit nervous once or twice?
- 一秒钟都没有 - 整个晚上都没有？
- Not for a second. - Not during the whole evening?
我早就知道胜利对我们而言唾手可得
I saw we were gonna win hands down.
我就像一只笼子里的熊一样什么都不用管
I felt like a bear in a cage with nothing to do.
这真是巨大的成功
lt was an immense achievement.
要不是我自己坚持着 可能两个月前我就放弃了
lf I hadn't backed myself to do it, I'd have given it up two months ago.
- 简直太不可思议了 - 只能说蠢货太多了
- Absolutely fantastic. - A lot of tomfoolery.
希金斯 我得向你致敬
Higgins, I salute you.
噢 愚笨的人总是不知道他们自己有多么愚笨
Oh, silly people don't know their own silly business.
今晚 老兄 你办到了 你办到了 你办到了
[SINGING] Tonight, old man, you did it You did it, you did it
你说过你会办到的 而你也确实办到了
You said that you would do it And indeed you did
我本以为你会后悔同我打赌 我不相信你能够办到
I thought that you would rue it I doubted you'd do it
不过现在我必须承认 你确实成功了
But now I must admit it That succeed you did
你应该得到一枚奖章 甚至应该被授予爵位
You should get a medal Or be even made a knight
噢 这算不得什么 真算不得什么
[SINGING] Oh, it was nothing Really nothing
你独自克服了 面前所有的障碍
AII alone you hurdled Every obstacle in sight
现在 现在
Now wait Now wait
这里边也有属于你的一份 光荣同样属于你
Give credit where it's due A lot of the glory goes to you
你就是那个将这件事办到的人 是谁办到了 是谁办到了
But you're the one who did it Who did it, who did it
如同直布罗陀的峭壁一样坚定 [直布罗陀海峡 北非] 一秒钟也不曾动摇
As sturdy as Gibraltar Not a second did you falter
再也没有什么好怀疑的了 你办到了
There's no doubt about it You did it
今晚我绝对又老了一岁 好几次我都吓得要死
I must have aged a year tonight At times I thought I'd die of fright
丝毫不曾平静过
Never was there a momentary lull
当我们走进会场 我立刻就知道我们会轻松取胜
Shortly after we came in I saw at once we'd easily win
然后 我发觉这太沉闷了
And after that, I found it deadly dull
你应该听到了 那些“哦”还有“啊”的惊叹声
PICKERING: You should have heard The "oohs" and "ahs"
所有人都想知道她是谁
Everyone wondering who she was
你简直会觉得他们好像从未见过 一位女士一般
You'd think they'd never seen A lady before
当特兰西瓦尼亚王子 要求见她
And when the prince of Transylvania Asked to meet her
并向她伸出手 牵着她步入舞池
And gave his arm To lead her to the floor
我对他说 你办到了 你办到了 你办到了
I said to him You did it, you did it, you did it
所有人都觉得她是那样迷人 如此高贵
They thought she was ecstatic And so damned aristocratic
可他们永远也不知道这一切都是因为你
And they never knew that you did it
[男人在笑]
[MEN LAUGHING]
真要感谢佐尔腾 卡帕西
Thank goodness for Zoltan Karpathy.
如果不是因为他 我肯定会无聊死的
lf it hadn't been for him, I would've died of boredom.
卡帕西？那个讨厌的匈牙利人？他也在那儿？
Karpathy? That dreadful Hungarian? Was he there?
是的 他就在那儿 没错 继续玩着他的老把戏
Yes, he was there, all right, and up to his old tricks.
那个流氓 将研究语音的科学
[SINGING] That blackguard Who uses the science of speech
用来勒索与诈骗 而不是教育
More to blackmail and swindle Than teach
他用它做 他那些恶心的勾当
He made it The devilish business of his
只为了查出杜利特小姐到底是谁
To find out who this Miss Doolittle is
每当我们环顾四周 就能看到他
Every time we looked around There he was
那头自布达佩斯来的长毛猎犬
That hairy hound from Budapest
一直紧跟着我们
Never leaving us alone
还以为我不知道他似的 一个无礼的家伙
Never have I ever known A ruder pest
最后我决定既然他是个傻瓜
Finally I decided it was foolish
不妨给他 同她交谈的机会
Not to let him have His chance with her
所以我退到一边 好让他可以同她跳舞
So I stepped aside And let him dance with her
她每个毛孔渗出的魅力 都迷得他晕头转向
Oozing charm from every pore He oiled his way around the floor
即便他使出浑身解数 想要摘下她的面具
Every trick that he could play He used to strip her mask away
直到最终 跳舞结束
And when at last The dance was done
他兴高采烈似乎他知道他已经赢了
He glowed as if he knew he'd won
迫不及待想让人知道 笑得合不拢嘴
And with a voice too eager And a smile too broad
他告诉女主人 说她是个冒牌货
He announced to the hostess That she was a fraud
不！
No.
[说着外语]
[SPEAKS FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
“她的英语说得太好了”他说
[SINGING] "Her English is too good," he said
这清楚地表明 她是个外国人
That clearly indicates That she is foreign
鉴于其他人都是以 自己的母语来接受教导
Whereas others are instructed ln their native language
英国人却不是这样
English people aren't
虽然她也许师从过
And although she may have studied
一位专业的辩证学家 一位文法学家
With an expert dialectician And grammarian
可我还是能说出 她的出生地是 匈牙利
I can tell That she was a born Hungarian
[所有人都在笑]
[ALL LAUGHING]
不单是匈牙利人 而是有着皇室血统的匈牙利人
Not only Hungarian But of royal blood
她是一位公主
She is a princess
她的血统 他说 比多瑙河还要蓝
"Her blood," he said, "is bluer Than the Danube is or ever was
王室身份分明就写在 她的脸上
Royalty is absolutely written On her face
她以为她能骗过我 可事实上我心知肚明
She thought that I was taken in But actually I never was
她怎么可能骗的了 与自己相同民族的人呢？
How could she deceive Another member of her race?"
我知道地球上所有的语言 他说
"I know each language on the map," Said he
她是匈牙利人 就像匈牙利第一狂想曲同样来自匈牙利
"And she's Hungarian As the first 'Hungarian Rhapsody"'
[所有人都在笑]
[ALL LAUGHING]
太精彩了
SERVANTS [SINGING]: Bravo
Bravo
祝贺你 希金斯教授
Congratulations, Professor Higgins
为了你光荣的胜利
For your glorious victory
祝贺你 希金斯教授
Congratulations, Professor Higgins
你将留名青史
You'II be mentioned in history
- 今天晚上 先生 你办到了 - 祝贺你 希金斯教授
- This evening, sir, you did it - Congratulations, Professor Higgins
- 你说过你会办到的 - 为了你光荣的胜利
- You said that you would do it - For your glorious victory
今天晚上 先生 你办到了 你办到了 你办到了
This evening, sir, you did it You did it, you did it
我们知道我们办到了 是你办到了
We know that we have did it But you did it
这成功是属于你的 全都是属于你的
And the credit for it AII belongs to you
[叹息]
[SIGHS]
噢 感谢上帝 终于结束了
Well, thank God that's over.
现在我可以安然入睡 再也不用为明天操心了
Now I can go to bed without dreading tomorrow.
皮尔斯：- 晚安 希金斯先生 - 晚安 皮尔斯太太
PEARCE: Good night, Mr. Higgins. HIGGINS: Good night, Mrs. Pearce.
我想我也要去睡觉了 晚安 希金斯
PICKERING: I think I'II turn in too. Good night, Higgins.
那真是一个伟大的时刻
lt's been a great occasion.
晚安 皮克林
Good night, Pickering.
噢 皮尔斯太太？
Oh, Mrs. Pearce?
噢 该死
Oh, damn.
我应该要她在早上替我准备咖啡而不是茶
I meant to ask her to give me coffee in the morning instead of tea.
你去给她留张纸条吧 好吗 伊莉莎？
Leave a little note for her, will you, Eliza?
顺便把灯关掉
And put out the lights.
[哭泣]
[CRYING]
希金斯：我把拖鞋留在楼下了 噢 真讨厌
HIGGINS: Left them downstairs. Oh, darn it.
总有一天我会连自己脑袋也忘放什么地方了
Leave my head behind one of these days.
该死的我到底把我的拖鞋放哪儿了？
What the devil have I done with my slippers?
你的拖鞋在这儿
Here are your slippers.
这里一只！
There!
这里还有一只！
And there!
把你的拖鞋拿去 希望你今后再也不能这样走运的找到他们
Take your slippers and may you never have a day's luck with them.
这世界怎么了？出什么事了吗？到底出什么事了？
What on earth? What's the matter? ls anything wrong?
不 不是你出了问题 是我替你赢了赌 对吧？
No, nothing wrong with you. I won your bet for you, haven't I?
那样就够了吗 我想 我已经不再重要了
That's enough for you. I don't matter, I suppose.
你替我赢了赌？你这放肆的小人
You won my bet? You presumptuous insect.
是我自己赢的 你为什么朝我扔拖鞋？
I won it. What did you throw those slippers at me for?
因为我想砸烂你的脸 我要杀了你 你这个自私的畜牲
Because I wanted to smash your face. I could kill you, you selfish brute.
为什么你不把我丢回捡到我的那个贫民区去呢？
Why didn't you leave me where you picked me up in the gutter?
你该感谢这一切都结束了 你现在可以把我丢回那个地方了
You thank God it's all over now, you can throw me back again there.
噢 看看这个人发什么神经
Oh, so the creature's nervous after all.
[伊莉莎尖叫]
[ELIZA SCREAMING]
把你的爪子收起来 你这只猫 你怎么能朝着我挥爪子
Claws in, you cat. How dare you show your temper to me.
安静点儿坐下
Sit down and be quiet.
噢 我今后要怎么办？我今后要怎么办？
Oh, what's to become of me? What's to become of me?
我怎么知道你今后怎么样？这跟我有关系吗？
How do I know what's to become of you? What does it matter?
你就不关心吗 我就知道你不会关心的 就算我死了你也不会关心的
You don't care. I know you don't care. You wouldn't care if I was dead.
我对你来说什么都不是 甚至连这双拖鞋都比不上
I'm nothing to you. Not as much as them slippers.
- 这双拖鞋 - 这双拖鞋
- Those slippers. - Those slippers.
我并不认为这有什么区别
I didn't think it meant any difference now.
为什么你突然变得这个样子？
Why have you suddenly begun going on like this?
我能知道你这是在抱怨你在这里受到了虐待吗？
May I ask if you complain of your treatment here?
不是
No.
有人对你不好了？皮克林上校 皮尔斯太太？
Has anybody behaved badly? Colonel Pickering, Mrs. Pearce?
不是
No.
嗯 你不是在说我有对你不好吧？
Well, you don't pretend that I have treated you badly?
- 不是 - 不是 我很高兴听到你那么说
- No. - No. I'm glad to hear that.
也许经过紧张的一天你已经累了
Perhaps you're tired after the strain of the day.
你要来块巧克力吗？
Would you have a chocolate?
不要！
No!
谢谢
Thank you.
嗯 你会感到焦虑是自然的
Well, it's only natural that you should be anxious,
不过现在都结束了
but it's all over now.
再没有什么好担心的了
Nothing more to worry about.
不 是你再没有什么好担心的了
No, nothing more for you to worry about.
噢 上帝啊 我真希望自己死了才好
Oh, God, I wish I was dead.
为什么？究竟是为什么？
Why? In heaven's name, why?
现在 听我说 伊莉莎 所有的这些气话纯粹是你个人主观的想法
Now, listen to me, Eliza. AII this irritation is purely subjective.
我听不明白 我太无知了
I don't understand. I'm too ignorant.
只不过是你自己的想象 你什么都没做错 没人会伤害你
lt's just imagination. Nothing's wrong. Nobody's hurting you.
现在 上床去好好睡一觉吧 轻轻哭一场 念念你的祈祷词吧
Now, you go to bed and sleep it off. Have a little cry and say your prayers
这样你就会觉得舒服多了
and you'II feel very much more comfortable.
我听到了你的祈祷词“感谢上帝一切都结束了”
I heard your prayers, "Thank God it's all over."
噢 难道你不想感谢上帝一切都结束了？
Well, don't you thank God it's all over
现在你自由了 你可以去做自己喜欢的事了
and how you're free and you can do what you like.
噢 我适合做什么？你认为我适合做什么？
Oh, what am I fit for? What have you left me fit for?
我能去哪儿？我能做什么？
Where am I to go? What am I to do?
我以后要怎么办？
And what's to become of me?
噢 你在为这些烦恼 是吗？
Oh, that's what's worrying you, is it?
噢 换做是我 我就不会为这些事烦恼
Oh, I wouldn't worry about that if I were you.
我确信你可以毫不困难
I'm sure you won't have any difficulty
就能让自己找个地方安顿下来
in settling yourself somewhere or other.
我一直都没意识到你终要离去
I didn't quite realize you were going away.
要知道 你可以结婚的
You might marry, you know.
你看 伊莉莎 并不是所有的男人们
You see, Eliza, all men are not confirmed old bachelors
都像我还有上校这样是坚持独身主义的
like me and the colonel.
大多数男人还是会选择结婚的 可怜的家伙们
Most men are the marrying sort, poor devils.
你长得这么好看
And you're not bad-looking.
有时候你看起来真的很漂亮
You're really quite a pleasure to look at sometimes.
噢 可不现在 当你哭泣的时候真是相当难看
Well, not now. When you've been crying you look like the very devil.
我的意思是说 当你一切正常的时候
But I mean when you're all right and quite yourself,
连我都忍不住要称赞你的迷人
you're what I would call attractive.
好了 上床去吧 好好睡一觉
Now, you go to bed, have a good night's rest,
等你起来的时候 再好好看看自己
then get up and have a look at yourself.
你就不会那么难过了
You won't feel so bad.
我敢说我母亲会替你找到一些很不错的人
I daresay my mother might find some fellow or other who'd do very well.
我们可不是在科芬园 [科芬园 伦敦的一个蔬菜花卉市场]
We were above that at Covent Garden.
你什么意思？
What do you mean?
我卖的是花 可不是自己
I sold flowers, I didn't sell myself.
现在 你已经把我变成了一位淑女 我再也不能出去卖东西了
Now, you've made a lady of me, I'm not fit to sell anything else.
哦 胡说 伊莉莎 不要将人与人之间的关系
Oh, tosh, Eliza, don't insult human relations
曲解为买卖关系来侮辱它
by dragging all that cant about buying and selling into it.
要是你不愿意的话 你也可以不用嫁人
You don't have to marry if you don't want to.
- 那我还能做什么？ - 噢 还有好多事情
- What else am I to do? - Well, there are lots of things.
比如你原来想去的那家花店?
What about the old idea of a florist shop?
皮克林会替你安排一家 他相当富有
Pickering would set you up in one. He's got lots of money.
今晚你所穿的衣服全都是他付的钱
He paid for all those togs you're wearing tonight.
而租这些首饰至少要花上200镑
And that with the hire of the jewelry will make a big hole in 200 pounds.
噢 振作点儿 你会没事的
Oh, come on now. You'II be all right.
噢 我必须去睡觉了 我简直困得要死
Well, I must be off to bed. I'm really devilish sleepy.
我刚才好像要找什么东西 对吗？
I was looking for something. What was it?
你的拖鞋
Your slippers.
噢 是的 没错 你把它们扔给我了
Oh, yes, of course. You shied them at me.
- 在你临睡前 先生 - 嗯？
- Before you go, sir, - Hm?
我穿的衣服是属于我还是皮克林上校？
do my clothes belong to me or to Colonel Pickering?
皮克林把它们拿去有什么用？
What the devil use would they be to Pickering?
这么晚了你问这个干什么？
Why do you bother about that in the night?
我想知道我是不是可以把它们带走
I want to know what I may take away with me.
我可不想被指控为盗窃
I don't wanna be accused of stealing.
盗窃？
Stealing?
你不该那么说的 伊莉莎 那让人觉得你想要什么
You shouldn't have said that, Eliza. That shows a want of feeling.
抱歉 我不过是个平凡无知的女孩儿 从我的角度看 我还是小心点好
I'm sorry. I'm a common ignorant girl. ln my station, I have to be careful.
在你这样的人和我这样的人之间是不可能有什么感情的
There can't be any feelings between the likes of you and the likes of me.
所以 你能告诉我哪些属于我而哪些不是吗？
Please, will you tell me what belongs to me and what doesn't?
你想要的话 这该死的一屋子的东西你都可以拿走
Take the whole damned houseful if you want.
除了那些首饰 它们是租来的 你满意了吗？
Except the jewelry, that's hired. Will that satisfy you?
先别走
Stop, please.
你能把这些拿到你的房间去好好保管吗？
Will you take these to your room and keep them safe?
我可不想万一把它们弄不见了
I don't want to run the risk of them being missed.
把它们给我吧
Hand them over.
要是这些都属于我而不是珠宝商
lf these belonged to me and not the jeweler,
我就要把它们都灌进你那不领情的喉咙里
I'd ram them down your ungrateful throat.
这个戒指不是珠宝商的 这是你在布莱顿给我买的
The ring isn't the jeweler's. lt's the one you bought me in Brighton.
现在我再也不想要它了
I don't want it now.
不要拿它打我！
Don't you hit me!
打你？你这个混蛋 你怎么可以这样说？
Hit you? You infamous creature, how dare you suggest such a thing.
是你在打我 是你伤到了我的心
lt's you who've hit me. You've wounded me to the heart.
我真高兴 不管怎样我总算讨回了一点
I'm glad. I've got a little of my own back anyhow.
你快要让我发火了
You've caused me to lose my temper,
我以前很少发火
a thing that's hardly happened to me before.
今晚我不想再继续说下去了 我要睡了
I don't wish to discuss it further tonight. I'm going to bed.
你还是自己去给皮尔斯太太留咖啡的字条吧
You better leave your own note for Mrs. Pearce about the coffee
因为这不该我做
for it won't be done by me.
该死的皮尔斯太太 该死的咖啡 还有该死的你
Damn Mrs. Pearce, damn the coffee and damn you.
我自己也该死 因为我愚蠢的
And damn my own folly for having lavished
将自己辛苦积攒的学识还有最宝贵的注意力和
my hard-earned knowledge and the treasure of my regard
善良都浪费在了一个无情的贫民区女孩儿身上
and intimacy on a heartless guttersnipe.
[留声机上播放的哼元音的声音]
[VOICE SPEAKING VOWELS PLAYING ON GRAMOPHONE]
[留声机停止播放]
[GRAMOPHONE STOPS]
你等着吧 亨利 希金斯 你等着吧
[SINGING] Just you wait, Henry Higgins Just you wait
你会后悔的 可到那时就算你哭得一塌糊涂也太晚了
You'II be sorry But your tears'II be too late
你就是个失败者
You will be the one it's done to
你将再也没有可以拥抱的人
And you'II have no one to run to
你等着吧
Just you wait
我过去常在 这条街上散步
[SINGING] I have often walked Down this street before
过去脚下的人行道 总是那样的平稳
But the pavement always stayed Beneath my feet before
可忽然间 我弹起几层楼高
AII at once am I Several stories high
只因为知道这条街上 有你住着
Knowing I'm on the street Where you live
市中心里 有丁香树吗？
Are there lilac tress ln the heart of town?
在市里的任一个地方 你能听到百灵的鸣叫吗？
Can you hear a lark ln any other part of town?
有什么地方会从每道门里 都弥散出诱人的魔力吗？
Does enchantment pour Out of every door?
没有 只有有在这条 有你住的街上
No, it's just on the street Where you live
噢 这飘然的感觉
And, oh, the towering feeling
只因为知道你就在不远处
Just to know somehow you are near
那是种难以抗拒的感觉
The overpowering feeling
或许在下一秒 你就会出现在我眼前
That any second You may suddenly appear
即便人们停下看着我
People stop and stare
也不会...
They don't...
亲爱的
Darling.
弗雷迪 你在这儿干什么？
Freddy, whatever are you doing here?
没什么 我已在这儿待了大半夜了
Nothing. I spend most of my nights here.
只有在这儿我才能感到快乐 不要笑我 杜利特小姐
lt's the only place where I'm happy. Don't laugh at me, Miss Doolittle.
别叫我杜利特小姐 听见了吗？
Don't you call me Miss Doolittle, do you hear?
叫我伊莉莎就够了
Eliza's good enough for me.
噢 弗雷迪 你不觉得我是个无情的贫民区女孩儿吗？
Oh, Freddy, you don't think I'm a heartless guttersnipe, do you?
亲爱的 你怎么会这么想？你知道我心里的感情
Darling, how could you imagine such a thing? You know how I feel.
我会每天都给你写上两三封信 一页接着一页
I've written two or three times a day telling you. Sheet and sheets.
听你说话 有如整个世界都在歌唱
[SINGING] Speak And the world is full of singing
我好像飞得 比鸟儿们都还要高
And I am winging Higher than the birds
牵着你 我的心都要碎了
Touch And my heart begins to crumble
连天空也翻覆了 亲爱的 我--
The heavens tumble Darling, and I'm--
词语 词语 词语 这些词语我都听厌了
[SINGING] Words, words, words I'm so sick of words
我整天听到的都是这些词语 起先是他 现在是你
I get words all day through First from him, now from you
你们这些讨厌的人是不是就只会这个？
ls that all you blighters can do?
别再说天上亮闪闪的星星
Don't talk of stars burning above
如果你真的爱我 就让我看到
lf you're in love, show me
不要告诉我你的梦
Tell me no dreams
你那满是欲望的梦
Filled with desire
如果你热情如火 就让我看到
lf you're on fire, show me
现在我们就在一起 在这午夜里
Here we are together ln the middle of the night
不要谈论什么春天 现在就将我抱紧
Don't talk of spring Just hold me tight
任何恋爱过的人 都会告诉过你的
Anyone who's ever been in love Will tell you that
现在可不是闲聊的时候
This is no time for a chat
难道你的嘴唇 不愿印在我的脸上?
Haven't your lips Longed for my touch?
别再说有多么爱我 让我看到吧 让我看到吧
Don't say how much Show me, show me
别再说你对我的爱 会有多久
Don't talk of love Lasting through time
不需要对我发誓说永远爱我
Make me no undying vow
让我看到吧 就现在
Show me now
不需要为我歌唱 不需要为我念诗
Sing me no song Read me no rhyme
不要浪费我的时间 让我看到吧
Don't waste my time Show me
不要再说什么6月 也别再谈什么秋天
Don't talk of June Don't talk of fall
别再停留在嘴上
Don't talk at all
让我看到吧
Show me
我再也不想 听到任何一个词
Never do I ever Want to hear another word
我已经全都听厌了
There isn't one I haven't heard
现在我们就在一起 就像一场梦
Here we are together ln what ought to be a dream
再多说一个词儿我就要疯了
Say one more word and I'II scream
难道你的手臂 不渴望将我拥在怀中？
Haven't your arms Hungered for mine?
不用多做解释
Please don't explain
让我看到吧
Show me
不要等到 皱纹渐生
Don't wait until Wrinkles and lines
布满了我的脸
Pop out all over my brow
让我看到吧 就现在
Show me now
- 伊莉莎 你这是要去哪儿？ - 去河边
- Eliza, where are you going? - To the river.
- 去干嘛？ - 在里边溅个水花
- What for? - To make a hole in it.
伊莉莎 亲爱的 你在说什么？
Eliza, darling, what do you mean?
[一辆出租车路过]
[TAXI PASSING]
出租车
Taxi.
弗雷迪：出租车
FREDDY: Taxi.
可我身上没钱
But I've no money.
伊莉莎：我有
ELIZA: I have.
弗雷迪：- 我们这是去哪儿？ - 去我本属于的地方
FREDDY: Where are we going? - Where I belong.
亲爱的 我能同你一起去吗？
Darling, shall I come with you?
有一张大椅子
MAN [SINGING]: With one enormous chair
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
合唱：有好多的巧克力在等着我吃
CHORUS: Lots of chocolate for me to eat
炉子也烧得暖暖的
Lots of coal making lots of heat
温暖了我的脸 我的手 直到我的脚
Warm face, warm hands, warm feet
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
噢 如此...
Oh, so...
买花朵花儿吧 小姐？
Buy a flower, miss?
好的 请给我一朵
Yes, please.
合唱：直到春季来临前
CHORUS: I would never budge
我甚至都不会挪动一下
Till spring crept over me windowsill
心爱的人将头 枕在我的膝上
Someone's head Resting on my knee
尽其所能的温柔的
Warm and tender as she can be
庇护着我
Who takes good care of me
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
噢 早上好 小姐 需要我为您做什么吗？
Oh, good morning, miss. Can I help you?
不会介意我暖一下手吧？
Do you mind if I warm my hands?
请便吧 小姐
Go right ahead, miss.
- 有什么事吗？ - 噢 请原谅 小姐
- Yes? - Oh, excuse me, miss.
我刚才把你错认成别人了
For a second I thought you were somebody else.
谁？
Who?
请原谅我 女士
Forgive me, ma'am.
清晨的阳光让我的眼睛看花了
Early morning light playing tricks with my eyes.
我能替您叫辆出租车吗 夫人？
Can I get you a taxi, ma'am?
像你这样的女士可不该一个人出来
A lady like you shouldn't be walking alone
在凌晨这个时候的伦敦到处走
around London this hour of the morning.
不必了 谢谢
No, thank you.
心爱的人将头 枕在我的膝上
ELIZA [SINGING]: Someone's head Resting on my knee
尽其所能的温柔的
Warm and tender as he can be
庇护着我
Who takes good care of me
噢 这样的生活难道不惬意吗？
Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
惬意 当然惬意
Loverly, loverly
男1：再见 阿尔菲
MAN 1 : Goodbye, Alfie.
男2：- 再见 - 现在我该叫您杜利特先生了
MAN 2: Goodbye. MAN 3: I'II call you Mr. Doolittle now.
男4：下次再来吧 杜利特先生
MAN 4: Do come again, Mr. Doolittle.
我们欢迎您的到来
We value your patronage always.
噢 谢谢 好伙计 谢谢
Oh, thank you, my good man. Thank you.
嘿 过来
Here. Come here.
替我将这位夫人送到布莱顿去 顺便转达我的问候
Take the missus on a trip to Brighton with my compliments.
男4：谢谢 杜利特先生
MAN 4: Thank you, Mr. Doolittle.
这地方真的很迷人 哈利 我们以后可得常来这儿
Charming spot this, Harry. We must visit it more often.
爸爸？
Father?
噢 不
Oh, no.
你看 哈利 他一点儿怜悯都没有
You see, Harry, he has no mercy.
我都这么悲惨了 还让她来调查我 他真是太不仁慈了
Sent her down to spy on me in me misery, he did.
我可是有血有肉的人
Me own flesh and blood.
好了 我依旧生活得很悲惨 你回去直接告诉他好了
Well, I'm miserable all right. You can tell him that straight.
你在说什么？你怎么穿成这个样子？
What are you talking about? What you dressed up for?
好像你好不知道
As if you didn't know.
回去跟告诉那个温珀街的魔鬼
Go on back to that Wimpole Street devil.
他我变成了什么样子
Tell him what he's done to me.
他把你怎么了？
What's he done to you?
他毁了我 就是这样
Ruined me, that's all.
他将我捆起来交到了所谓的中产阶级道德观的手里
Tied me up and delivered me into the hands of middle-class morality.
你不要替他说话了
And don't you defend him.
除了他还会有谁
Was it him or was it not him
会写信给那个名叫瓦林福德的讨厌的美国老头儿
wrote to an old American blighter named Wallingford
那老头儿拿出500万办了个道德重塑社团
who was giving 5 millions to fund moral reform societies
他对那个老头儿说英国最具创新的道德学家
to tell him the most original moralist in England
就是阿尔弗雷德 P 杜利特先生 一位普通的清洁工
was Mr. Alfred P. Doolittle, a common dustman.
听起来确实像他开的玩笑
Sounds like one of his jokes.
也许你只把它当做个玩笑 可它快把我逼疯了
You may call it a joke. lt's put the lid on me proper.
那个老家伙死后给我留下的
The old bloke died and left me 4000 pounds a year
遗嘱中说每年给我4,000镑
in his blooming will.
谁要他把我变成一位绅士的？
Who asked him to make a gentleman out of me?
我原本生活得快乐 自由
I was happy, I was free.
我想要钱的时候我会向周围的每个人伸手要
I touched pretty nigh everyone for money when I wanted it,
就跟我之前找他要那样
same as I touched him.
可现在我却只能等着别人伸手向我要
Now I'm tied neck and heels and everybody touches me.
一年前 我在这个世上一个亲人都没有
A year ago, I hadn't a relation in the world
仅有的一两个亲人连话都不愿同我说 [即未结婚的女友和赫本]
except one or two who wouldn't speak to me.
可现在我有50个
Now I've 50.
几乎每周都跑来向我索要一笔多得不像话钱
Not a decent week's wages amongst the lot of them.
噢 我现在是在为别人而活着了 根本就不是为我自己
Oh, I have to live for others now, not for myself.
中产阶级道德观
Middle-class morality.
来吧 阿尔菲 几小时后我们还得到教堂呢
Come on, Alfie. Another couple of hours, we have to be at the church.
- 教堂？ - 对 教堂
- Church? - Yeah, church.
这是伤我最深的一刀
The deepest cut of all.
噢 你不觉得我穿得像个红衣护柩人？
Well, why do you think I'm dressed up like a ruddy pallbearer?
你的继母想要同我结婚
Your stepmother wants to marry me.
现在我是有身份的人了 她也想有身份
Now I'm respectable, she wants to be respectable.
噢 既然你感觉这样不好 为什么你不把钱退回去呢？
Well, if that's the way you feel about it, why don't you give the money back?
最悲剧的就是这个 伊莉莎
That's the tragedy of it, Eliza.
说放手很容易 可我没那个勇气
lt's easy to say chuck it, but I haven't the nerve.
我们都是被迫的
We're all intimidated.
我们确实都是 被迫的 被钱收买了
That's what we are, intimidated. Bought up.
没错 就是那样
Yeah. That's what I am.
就是你的那位宝贝教授把我弄成了这样子
That's what your precious professor's brought me to.
他不是我的什么宝贝教授
Not my precious professor.
噢 他又把你送回来了 是吗？
Oh, sent you back, has he?
他先是把我硬塞进了中产阶级
First he shoves me in the middle class,
然后他又把你赶出来 好让我来供养你
then he chucks you out for me to support you.
这全都是他的计划
That's all part of his plan.
不过你已经出卖了他
But you double-cross him.
你别想跟我回家
Don't you come back home to me.
从我这里你连两个便士也别想得到
Don't you take tuppence from me.
你得靠你自己 你现在是一位女士了 你可以办到
You stand on your own two feet. You're a lady now, and you can do it.
嗯 就是这样 伊莉莎 你现在是一位女士了
Yeah, that's right, Eliza. You're a lady now.
伊莉莎 出租车里已经很冷了
Eliza, it's getting awfully cold in that taxi.
嘿 伊莉莎 你要来参加我今天上午的婚礼吗？
Here, Eliza, would you like to come and see me turned off this morning?
就在圣 乔治 汉诺威广场 10:00
St. George's Hanover Square, 1 0:00.
我不勉强你 但还是欢迎你来
I wouldn't advise it, but you're welcome.
- 不了 谢谢 爸爸 - 不用谢
- No, thank you, Dad. - No.
这里的事情都办完了吗 伊莉莎？
Are you all finished here, Eliza?
是的 弗雷迪
Yes, Freddy.
我在这里的事儿都办完了
I'm all finished here.
祝你好运 爸爸
Good luck, Dad.
谢谢你 伊莉莎
Thank you, Eliza.
- 该走了 阿尔菲 - 我还有多少时间？
- Come along, Alfie. - How much time have I got left?
就剩下几个小时了
[SINGING] There's just a few more hours
你就还剩这点儿时间
That's all the time you've got
就几小时 他们就要结婚了
A few more hours Before they tie the knot
到处是美酒和姑娘 在整个伦敦里
There's drinks and girls AII over London
我还能追逐他们的时间 就剩下几个小时了
And I gotta track 'em down ln just a few more hours
快把他们准备好 我亲爱的
Set 'em up, me darlin'
我今天上午就要结婚了
I'm gettin' married in the mornin'
叮咚 钟声就要敲响
Ding dong The bells are gonna chime
拔出瓶塞 让我们痛饮一场
Pull out the stopper Let's have a whopper
但得把我准时送到教堂
But get me to the church on time
我上午得在那儿
I gotta be there in the mornin'
装扮整齐 看起来就像我年轻时的样子
Spruced up and lookin' in me prime
姑娘们 过来吻我吧
Girls, come and kiss me
让我看看你们有多想我
Show how you'II miss me
但得把我准时送到教堂
But get me to the church on time
如果我要跳舞 就把地板卷起来
lf I am dancin' Roll up the floor
如果我在吹口哨 就把我轰出去
lf I am whistlin' Me out the door
我今天上午就要结婚了
I'm gettin' married in the mornin'
叮咚 钟声就要敲响
Ding dong The bells are gonna chime
尽情狂欢吧 但可别弄得晕头转向
Kick up a rumpus But don't lose the compass
还要把我准时送到教堂
And get me to the church
把他送到教堂
Get him to the church
看在上帝的面上 把我准时送到教堂
For God's sake Get me to the church on time
[所有人都在笑]
[ALL LAUGHING]
我今天上午就要结婚了
ALL [SINGING]: I'm gettin' married in the mornin'
叮咚 钟声就要敲响
Ding dong The bells are gonna chime
哪个家伙要是能 抬起这张桌子
Some bloke who's able Lift up the table
还要把我准时送到教堂
And get me to the church on time
如果我在飞 那就拿枪把我轰下来
lf I am flyin' Then shoot me down
如果我在勾引谁 就把她赶出城去
lf I am wooin' Get her out of town
因为我今天上午就要结婚了
For I'm gettin' married in the mornin'
叮咚 钟声就要敲响
Ding dong The bells are gonna chime
[大家都在欢呼]
[ALL CHEERING]
给我涂上柏油黏上羽毛 [把我打扮得像只火鸡吧] 把军队都叫来吧
Feather and tar me Call out the army
但得把我送到教堂
But get me to the church
把我送到教堂
Get me to the church
噢 看在上帝的面上 把我准时送到教堂
Oh, for God's sake Get me to the church on time
他今天上午就要结婚了
He's gettin' married in the mornin'
叮咚 钟声就要敲响
Ding dong The bells are gonna chime
来吧 拔出瓶塞 让我们痛饮一场
Come on, pull out the stopper Let's have a whopper
但得把我准时送到教堂
But get me to the church on time
他上午得在那儿
He's got to be there in the mornin'
装扮整齐 看起来就像他年轻时的样子
Spruced up and lookin' in his prime
姑娘们 过来吻我吧 让我看看你们有多想我
Girls, come and kiss me Show how you'II miss me
但得把我准时送到教堂
But get me to the church on time
如果我要跳舞 就把地板卷起来
lf I am dancin' Roll up the floor
如果我在吹口哨 就把我轰出去
lf I am whistlin' [WHISTLES] Me out the door
因为他今天上午就要结婚了
For he's gettin' married in the mornin'
叮咚 钟声就要敲响
Ding dong The bells are gonna chime
给我下药或是把我丢进监狱 要不干脆给我贴张邮票把我邮了
Drug me or jail me Stamp me and mail me
但得把我送到教堂
But get me to the church
把他送到教堂
Get him to the church
看在上帝的面上 把我准时送到教堂
For God's sake Get me to the church on time
杰米：快走吧 阿尔菲
JAMIE: Come on, Alfie.
嗯 走吧
Yeah, go on.
男：啊 他打扮得多光鲜
MAN: Yeah, he's light.
姑娘们快向他献吻
ALL [SINGING]: Girls come and kiss him
让他知道你们有多想他
Show how they miss him
把他准时送到教堂
And get him to the church on time
尽情狂欢吧 但可别弄得晕头转向
Kick up a rumpus But don't lose the compass
把他准时送到教堂
And get him to the church on time
如果我在飞 那就拿枪把我轰下来
lf I am flyin' Then shoot me down
如果我在勾引谁 就把她赶出城去
lf I am wooin' Get her out of town
男：嗷！
MAN: Ouch!
他今天上午就要结婚了
He's gettin' married in the mornin'
叮咚 钟声就要敲响
Ding dong The bells are gonna chime
- 哪个家伙要是能 - 抬起这张桌子
- Some bloke who's able - Lift up the table
把我准时送到教堂
Get me to the church on time
男1：- 这真是个令人愉快的早晨 - 早上好 阿尔菲
MAN 1 : lt's a nice morning. MAN 2: Good morning, Alfie.
男3：让我们欢呼三声
MAN 3: Three cheers.
女：回去吧
WOMAN: Come back.
[所有人都在笑]
[ALL LAUGHING]
星光也到了回去睡觉的时候
ALL [SINGING]: Starlight is reelin' home to bed now
晨辉渐染着天空
Mornin' is smearin' up the sky
伦敦正在醒来
London is wakin'
阳光就要破晓
Daylight is breakin'
祝你好运 老伙计
Good luck, old chum
祝你健康
Good health
再见
Goodbye
我今天上午就要结婚了
I'm gettin' married in the mornin'
叮咚 钟声就要敲响
Ding dong The bells are gonna chime
向我欢呼致意吧 然后都离开好让我启程
Hail and salute me Then haul off and boot me
把他送到教堂 把他送到教堂
And get him to the church Get him to the church
看在上帝的面上 把他送到教堂
For God's sake Get him to the church
准时
On time
希金斯：皮克林 皮克林
HIGGINS: Pickering. Pickering.
她就没说过把她的衣服都送到哪儿？
Didn't she even say where to send her clothes?
我告诉你了 先生 她把它们全带走了
She took them all with her.
- 皮克林 - 出什么事了？
- Pickering. - What's the matter?
出麻烦了 伊莉莎逃走了
Here's a confounded thing. Eliza's bolted.
- 逃走了？ - 逃走了
- Bolted? - Bolted.
昨晚 皮尔斯太太没有通知我就让她离开了
Last night, Mrs. Pearce let her go without telling me.
- 噢 我给弄糊涂了 - 我该怎么做？
- Well, I'm dashed. - What am I to do?
我要的是咖啡不是茶 我根本不知道它们都放在什么地方
I got tea instead of coffee. I don't know where anything is.
- 我不知道我的日程安排 - 伊莉莎知道的
- I don't know my appointments. - Eliza would know.
当然她知道 可她已经跑了
Of course she'd know, but she's gone.
你们两个昨晚不会又把她吓着了吧？
Did either of you frighten her last night?
我们根本就没对她说过一个词儿 你当时也在场的
We hardly said a word to her. You were there.
你就没在我睡了之后去欺负她了？
Did you bully her after I went to bed?
完全相反 她朝我扔拖鞋
The other way around. She threw the slippers at me.
我根本一点儿都没惹她
I never gave her the slightest provocation.
我还没开口 拖鞋就 BANG 的一声砸在我头上了
The slippers came, bang, at my head before I uttered a word.
还说了很多最难听的话 我当时都惊了
Used the most disgraceful language. I was shocked.
- 噢 我给弄糊涂了 - 我也不能理解
- Well, I'm dashed. - I don't understand.
我们替她考虑得很周全啊
We've given her every consideration.
- 她自己也承认的 - 噢 我给弄糊涂了
- She admitted it herself. - Well, I'm dashed.
噢 皮克林 看在上帝的面上 别再装糊涂了赶紧做点儿什么
Oh, Pickering, for God's sake, stop being dashed and do something.
- 什么？ - 好吧 打电话给警察
- What? - Well, phone the police.
不然要他们来干什么？
What are they there for in heaven's name?
希金斯先生 你不能把伊莉莎的名字给警察
Mr. Higgins, you can't give Eliza's name to the police
就像她是个小偷或是丢掉的一把伞
as if she were a thief or a lost umbrella.
为什么不能？我要找回这女孩儿
But why not? I want to find the girl.
她是属于我的 我为她花了5镑
She belongs to me. I paid 5 pounds for her.
安静点好吗 喂 请接苏格兰场
Quite right. Hello. Scotland Yard, please.
能给我端点儿咖啡来吗？
Get me some coffee, would you please?
- 好的 先生 谁啊？
- Yes, sir. MAN: Who's there?
苏格兰场吗？噢 太好了 抱歉
Scotland Yard? Yes, of course. I beg your pardon, yes.
我是皮克林上校 休 皮克林
This is Colonel Pickering speaking. Hugh Pickering.
- 住温珀街27A号 - 温珀街27A号
- 27A Wimpole Street. - 27A Wimpole Street.
- 我想报一个人口失踪案 - 性别？
- I want to report a missing person. - Male or female?
是一位名叫伊莉莎 杜利特的小姐 是的 约21岁
A Miss Eliza Doolittle, yeah. About 21 .
身高呢？
And her height?
- 我想应该是5英尺7英寸[皮克林为赫本做的衣服] - 眼睛颜色呢？
- I should say about 5'7". - What color eyes?
她的眼睛？噢 让我想想 她的眼睛 她的眼睛是
Her eyes? Oh, let me think now. Her eyes, her eyes.
- 棕色的 - 棕色的 对
- Brown. - Brown, yeah.
不 不 不是 她的头发？
No, no, no. Her hair?
噢 老天 让我...
Oh, good Lord. Let me...
噢 是那种偏中性介于--
Well, sort of nondescript neutral sort of--
棕色 棕色 棕色的
Brown, brown, brown.
你听到他说的了吧？棕色 棕色 棕色的 是的
You heard what he said? Brown, brown, brown, yes.
不 不 不是 这是她的住处
No, no, no, this is her residence.
27A号--对
27A-- Yeah.
我想应该在今早3到4点
About between 3 and 4 this morning, I understand.
好的 不 不 没有
Yes. No, no, no.
亲--不 她没有任何亲人 没有
Rela-- No, she's no relation, no.
什么？嗯 只能说是她的一位好朋友吧 是吧？
What? Well, just let's call her a good friend, shall we?
你说什么？
I beg your pardon?
听着 伙计 我可不喜欢你问话的口气
Listen to me, my man, I don't like the tenor of that question.
这姑娘在我们这里做什么是我们自己的事情
What the girl does here is our affair.
你们的事情就是把她找回来 这样她就能回来接着做自己的事情了
Your affair is to get her back so that she can continue doing it.
噢 我真给弄糊涂了
Well, I'm dashed.
这是为什么 天呐 会使得她出走？
[SINGING] What, in all in heaven, Can have prompted her to go?
在舞会上她取得这样大的成功
After such a triumph at the ball?
是什么使她如此不开心？ 是什么能让她如此不开心？
What could have depressed her? What could have possessed her?
我完全弄不明白 这个可怜的人
I cannot understand The wretch at all
希金斯 我有个老同学在内政部
Higgins, I have an old school chum at the Home Office.
也许他能帮忙 我打算给他打个电话
Perhaps he can help. Think I'II give him a ring.
请说接线号码
WOMAN [ON PHONE]: Number, please.
请接白厅 72 44
Whitehall 72-double 4, please.
白厅 72 44
Whitehall 72-double 4.
女人都没有理性 这就是为什么
[SINGING] Women are irrational That's all there is to that
她们脑袋里尽是棉花 稻草还有破布
Their heads are full of cotton Hay and rags
她们就知道发脾气 敏感 优柔寡断
They're nothing but exasperating lrritating, vacillating
喜欢算计 容易焦虑 令人发狂 就是个让人发火的巫婆
Calculating, agitating, maddening And infuriating hags
男：这里是内政部
MAN: The Home Office here.
噢 我想找布鲁斯特 巴金先生
Oh, I want to speak to Mr. Brewster Budgin, please.
- 您能稍等一下吗 先生？ - 布鲁...好的 我会等的
- Would you hold on, sir? - Brew-- Yes, I'II wait.
皮克林
Pickering,
为什么女人就不能更像男人点儿？
why can't a woman be more like a man?
能再说一遍吗？
I beg your pardon?
好的 为什么女人 就不能更像男人点儿？
[SINGING] Yes, why can't a woman Be more like a man?
男人是如此坦率 如此开诚布公
Men are so honest So thoroughly square
永远那么高尚 那么公平
Eternally noble, historically fair
当你成功的时候 他会轻轻的拍拍你的后背
Who, when you win Will always give your back a pat
噢 为什么女人 就不能那样？
Well, why can't a woman Be like that?
为什么所有人 都学着别人那样？
Why does everyone Do what the others do?
女人就不会学着 动动自己的脑子？
Can't a woman learn To use her head?
为什么她们做的每件事 都跟她们母亲一样？
Why do they do everything Their mothers do?
为什么她们就不能长得 噢 像她们的父亲呢？
Why don't they grow up Well, like their father instead?
为什么女人不能 学学男人？
Why can't a woman Take after a man?
男人是如此随和 如此容易满足
Men are so pleasant So easy to please
跟他们在一起的任何时候 你总会觉得轻松
Whenever you're with them You're always at ease
要是我好几小时不说话 你会不会觉得受到轻视？
Would you be slighted lf I didn't speak for hours?
当然不会
Of course not.
要是我喝了一两杯 你会不会觉得生气？
Would you be livid lf I had a drink or two?
废话
Nonsense.
要是我从不给你送花儿 你会不会觉得受伤？
Would you be wounded lf I never sent you flowers?
绝对不会
Never.
噢 为什么女人不能 像你一样？
Well, why can't a woman Be like you?
100万个男人站在一起 也不过是有点儿嘈杂
One man in a million May shout a bit
当然 总会有人有那么些许的缺点
Now and then There's one with slight defects
有个人 也许 对他的坦率 你会有些怀疑
One, perhaps, whose truthfulness You doubt a bit
但大体而言 我们都是了不起的男人
But by and large We are a marvelous sex
为什么女人不能 学学男人？
Why can't a woman Take after a man?
因为他们是如此友善 温厚而和蔼
Because men are so friendly Good-natured and kind
你再也找不到 一位比他更好的伙伴
A better companion You never will find
要是我回家用晚餐晚了几小时 你会不会大喊大叫？
lf I were hours late for dinner Would you bellow?
当然不会
Of course not.
要是我忘记了你那愚蠢的生日 你会不会发火？
lf I forgot your silly birthday Would you fuss?
废话
Nonsense.
要是我同别人外出 你会不会抱怨？
Would you complain lf I took out another fellow?
绝对不会
Never.
噢 为什么女人不能 像我们一样?
Well, why can't a woman Be like us?
噢 您好 布鲁斯特 巴金先生 在吗？
Oh, hello. Mr. Brewster Budgin there?
- 是的 我就是巴金 - 布鲁兹
- Yes, Budgin here. - Bruzzie.
噢 布鲁兹 你绝对猜不到我是谁
Oh, Bruzzie, you'II never never guess who this is.
噢 别傻了 是皮克林啊
Oh, don't be silly. lt's Pickering.
说的太对了 没错 是我 天呐
You're quite right, yes, it is. Good heavens.
以圣乔治之名起誓 你记性真好
By George, what a memory.
你好吗 布鲁兹？
How are you, Bruzzie?
很高兴能听到你说话
Nice to hear your voice.
什么？噢 不会吧 真的已经有30年了？天呐
What? Oh, don't say that. ls it already 30 years? Good heavens.
你说的没错 是啊 真是沧海桑田啊
You're quite right. Yes, oceans of water.
听我说 布鲁兹 我给你打电话是有事要你帮忙
Listen, Bruzzie, I'II tell you why I rang up.
发生了一件不太愉快的事 我能同你见个面吗？
Something rather unpleasant's happened. Could I come and see you?
嗯 我会的 好的 就现在 马上来
Well, I could. Yes, now, straight away.
很 噢 好的 谢谢 谢谢
Right-o, good. Thank you, thank you.
再见 布鲁兹 非常感谢
Goodbye, Bruzzie. Thank you very much.
噢 皮尔斯太太 我要去趟内政部
Oh, Mrs. Pearce, I'm going along to the Home Office.
噢 我真希望您能找到他 皮克林上校
Oh, I do hope you find her, Colonel Pickering.
希金斯先生会想念她的
Mr. Higgins will miss her.
希金斯先生会想念她 嗯？
Mr. Higgins will miss her, eh?
去他的希金斯先生 是我会想念她
Blast Mr. Higgins. I'II miss her.
希金斯：皮克林？
HIGGINS: Pickering?
皮克林？
Pickering?
噢 皮尔斯太太？
Oh, Mrs. Pearce?
皮尔斯：- 什么事 先生？ - 上校去哪儿了？
PEARCE: Yes, sir? - Where's the colonel?
他去内政部了 先生
He's gone to the Home Office, sir.
噢 你在这儿
Oh, there you are.
我心里很乱而他出去找人帮忙 现在 这儿就有一位令人感到亲切的人
I'm disturbed and he runs for help. Now, there's a good fellow.
皮尔斯太太 你也是女人
Mrs. Pearce, you're a woman.
为什么女人 就不能更像男人点儿？
[SINGING] Why can't a woman Be more like a man?
男人是如此正派 如此衣着得体
Men are so decent Such regular chaps
随时准备帮助你 度过任何灾难
Ready to help you Through any mishaps
随时准备帮助你 在你阴郁的时候重新振作
Ready to buck you up Whenever you are glum
为什么女人就不能同男人成为亲密的朋友？
Why can't a woman be a chum?
为什么思考这件事 有些女人永远都不会做？
Why is thinking Something women never do?
为什么她们从不试着去梳清条理？
Why is logic never even tried?
而梳理她们的头发 就是她们唯一做的事情
Straightening up their hair Is all they ever do
为什么她们就不能理清 她们脑子里的那团乱麻？
Why don't they straighten up The mess that's inside?
为什么女人 举止不能像个男人？
Why can't a woman Behave like a man?
如果我是个女人 我才不会参加什么舞会
lf I was a woman Who'd been to a ball
被所有人 赞为公主一般
Been hailed as a princess By one and by all
我就要激动的哭得 像个溢满水的浴缸？
Would I start weeping Like a bathtub overflowing?
或者换句话说 要是我的家就像一棵树的话？
Or carry on As if my home were in a tree?
我会匆忙跑掉 甚至都不跟自己说一声要去什么地方吗？
Would I run off And never tell me where I'm going?
为什么女人不能像我一样？
Why can't a woman be like me?
你是说你为他们做了
Do you mean to say that after you'd done
这么了不起的事 没出一点错
this wonderful thing for them without making a single mistake,
而他们就坐在那里 一个词儿也没对你说吗？
they just sat there, never said a word to you?
既没有喜欢你 也没有赞美你 或是对你说你真的是太优秀了？
Never petted you, or admired you, or told you how splendid you'd been?
一个词儿都没有 他们只是坐在那里互相道贺
Not a word. They just sat there congratulating each other
他们取得了多么非凡的成就
on how marvelous they'd been.
他们有多高兴这一切都结束了 这应该得到怎样的奖励
How glad they were it was all over and what a bore it had all been.
真是令人惊讶
This is simply appalling.
是我的话我不会朝他扔拖鞋的
I should not have thrown my slippers at him,
我会朝他扔烙铁
I should've thrown the fire irons.
希金斯：- 噢 母亲你在吗？ - 是谁啊？
HIGGINS: Oh, is mother in? - What's that?
亨利
Henry.
我知道这不会很久
I knew it wouldn't be too long.
现在 你要记住
Now, remember,
你昨晚并不只是同王子跳了支舞
you not only danced with a prince last night,
是你表现得就像个公主
you behaved like a princess.
母亲 这事情真是太奇怪了 你也会...？
Mother, the most confounded thing. Do you...?
是你？
You?
下午好 希金斯教授 您还好吗？
Good afternoon, Professor Higgins. Are you quite well?
- 问我吗？ - 当然是问您
- Am I--? - Of course you are.
您从来都不得病的 您要来点儿茶吗？
You are never ill. Would you care for some tea?
你怎么敢跟我玩这种游戏 是我教你的
Don't you dare try that game on me. I taught it to you.
现在 起身跟我回去 别再犯傻了
Now, get up and come home and stop being a fool.
你给我惹的麻烦够多了
You've caused me enough trouble.
真是非常漂亮的出击 亨利 [这老太太的台词太犀利了]
Very nicely put indeed, Henry.
有哪个女人可以拒绝这样的邀请
No woman could resist such an invitation.
这个货物是怎么到这儿来的 居然还待为上宾？
How did this baggage get here in the first place?
伊莉莎今早来看我 我也很高兴她来
Eliza came to see me this morning and I was delighted to have her.
要是你再不规矩点儿 我就只有请你离开
And if you don't promise to behave, I must ask you to leave.
你是说我穿上自己的周日礼服
You mean to say I'm to put on my Sunday manners
就为了这个自己从科芬园的一匹烂菜叶
for this thing that I created out of the squashed cabbage leaves
打造出来的东西？
of Covent Garden?
我正是这个意思
That's precisely what I mean.
噢 那我要先请她滚出去
Well, I'II see her damned first.
你是怎么从我儿子那里学到这么好的礼仪呢？
However did you learn good manners with my son around?
说起来真的很难啊
lt was very difficult.
我可能永远都不知道淑女与绅士应有怎样的举止
I should never have known how ladies and gentlemen behave
要不是因为皮克林上校
if it hadn't been for Colonel Pickering.
他一直都让我感到他对我的感觉和思维
He always showed me that he felt and thought about me
都只不过比普通卖花女稍好一点儿罢了
as if I were something better than a common flower girl.
您也看见了 希金斯夫人 抛开装扮来看
You see, Mrs. Higgins, apart from the things one can pick up,
一位淑女同卖花女的区别
the difference between a lady and a flower girl
并不在于她的举止 而在于她受到怎样的对待
is not how she behaves, but how she is treated.
对希金斯教授来说我永远都是个卖花女
I shall always be a flower girl to Professor Higgins
因为他一直并将永远把我当卖花女一样对待
because he always treats me as a flower girl and always will.
可我知道 对皮克林上校来说我永远都是位淑女
But I know I shall always be a lady to Colonel Pickering
因为他一直并将永远把我当淑女一样对待
because he always treats me as a lady and always will.
[咆哮]
[GROWLS]
亨利 别在那里咬牙
Henry, don't grind your teeth.
主教大人来了 夫人 我先请他去花园吗？
The bishop is here, madam. Shall I show him into the garden?
主教大人还有这位教授？天呐 绝对不行
The bishop and the professor? Good heavens, no.
我会被开除教籍的 我在书房里见他
I should be excommunicated. I'II see him in the library.
伊莉莎 要是我儿子敢摔东西 [英国人果然喜欢搞不平等条约 赫本可以砸…这就开始护着媳妇了]
Eliza, if my son starts breaking up things,
我全权授予你 你可以把他赶出去
I give you full permission to have him evicted.
亨利 亲爱的 我建议你只谈两个话题：
Henry, dear, I suggest you stick to two subjects:
天气还有你的健康
The weather and your health.
噢 你已经讨回了一点了 就像你说的那样
Well, you've had a bit of your own back, as you call it.
要是你已经闹够了 你总该冷静下来
Have you had enough and are you going to be reasonable
或者你还想要什么？
or do you want any more?
你要我回去不过是替你捡拖鞋
You want me back only to pick up your slippers
继续忍受你对我发脾气 还要不断的伺候你
and put up with your tempers and fetch and carry for you.
- 我根本就没说我想要你回去 - 噢 是吗？
- I didn't say I wanted you back at all. - Oh, indeed?
- 那我们还谈什么？ - 嗯 谈关于你的事 而不是关于我的事
- Then what are we talking about? - Well, about you, not about me.
如果你回来 你得到的还会跟原来一样
lf you come back, you'II be treated as you've always been treated.
我不可能改变我的性格 我也不打算改变我的礼仪
I can't change my nature. I don't intend to change my manners.
我的礼仪同皮克林上校的是完全一样的
My manners are exactly the same as Colonel Pickering's.
不是那样的
That's not true.
他对一个卖花女就像对待一位公爵夫人
He treats a flower girl as if she were a duchess.
噢 我对待一位公爵夫人就像对待卖花女一样
Well, I treat a duchess as if she was a flower girl.
噢 我明白了 你对谁都是这样
Oh, I see. The same to everybody.
是那样
Just so.
要知道 最关键问题 伊莉莎 并不在于良好的礼仪
You see, the great secret, Eliza, is not a question of good manners
或是不好的礼仪 或是别的什么礼仪
or bad manners or any particular sort of manners,
而是对所有人都是同样的礼仪
but having the same manner for all human souls.
问题不在于我对你是否粗暴
The question is not whether I treat you rudely,
或是你是否听说我有对谁更好过
whether you've ever heard me treat anyone else better.
我才不在乎你怎么对待我
I don't care how you treat me.
我不在乎你骂我
I don't mind your swearing at me.
也不在乎你对我冷淡 我过去已经受够了
I shouldn't mind a black eye. I've had one before this.
可你不能这样抛弃我
But I won't be passed over.
噢 别缠着我 我是不会为你停下脚步的
Well, then get out of my way, for I won't stop for you.
你谈起我就好像我是辆公共汽车
You talk about me as though I was a motor bus.
你就是辆公共汽车
So you are a motor bus.
只知道摁着喇叭向前冲 根本不考虑搭任何人
AII bounce and go and no consideration for anybody.
就算我没有你我也能生活 你别以为我不行
But I can get along without you. Don't you think I can't.
我知道你行 我也说过你可以
I know you can. I told you you could.
我想 你从没想过 没有你我是否也能生活
You've never wondered, I suppose whether I could get along without you.
你这不是要缠着我吧
Don't you try to get around me.
是你自找的
You'II have to.
我当然可以 即便没有你或是这世上任何人
So I can, without you or any soul on earth.
我会想你的 伊莉莎
I shall miss you, Eliza.
我已经从你那愚蠢的观点中有所收获
I've learned something from your idiotic notions.
我得谦逊与感激的承认这一点
I confess that, humbly and gratefully.
噢 在你的留声机里有我的声音
Well, you have my voice on your gramophone.
当你没有我在身旁感到孤独的时候 你可以打开它
When you feel lonely without me, you can turn it on.
它没有感情可以让你伤害
lt has no feelings to hurt.
噢 但我不能打开你的灵魂
Well, I can't turn your soul on.
噢 你真是个魔鬼
Ooh. You are a devil.
你轻易伤害一个女孩儿的心
You can twist the heart in a girl just as easily
就像扭伤自己的手臂一样容易
as someone can twist her arms to hurt her.
我为什么要回去？
What am I to come back for?
因为你很有趣 这就是为什么我要带你回去
For the fun of it. That's why I took you on.
要是我没有满足你的要求 也许你明天就会把我丢出去
And you may throw me out tomorrow if I don't do everything you want me to.
好吧 要是我没有满足你的要求 你明天就可以走
Yes, and you may walk out tomorrow if I don't do everything you want me to.
去跟我父亲一起生活？
And live with my father?
是的 要么卖花儿 要么你愿意的话就嫁给皮克林？
Yes, or sell flowers. Or would you rather marry Pickering?
就算你求我 我也不会嫁给你
I wouldn't marry you if you asked me,
就算你比他年轻
and you're nearer my age than what he is.
- 比他年轻 - 我爱怎么说就怎么说
- Than he is. - I'II talk as I like.
你已经不是我的老师了
You're not my teacher now.
我才没那么想过 你不要乱想
That's not what I want, and you don't think it is.
愿意追我的绅士太多了
I've always had chaps enough wanting me that way.
弗雷迪 希尔一天每天都给我写两三封信
Freddy Hill writes me twice and three times a day.
一页接着一页
Sheets and sheets.
简单点儿说 你要我也像他那样对你迷得一塌糊涂
ln short, you want me to be as infatuated about you as he is.
- 是想那样吗？ - 不 我不想
- Is that it? - No, I don't.
我想从你那里得到的不是那样的感觉
That's not the sort of feeling I want from you.
我只想你对我亲柔一点
I want a little kindness.
我知道自己不过是个平凡无知的女孩儿 而你是位博学的绅士
I know I'm a common ignorant girl and you're a book-learned gentleman.
可我也不是你脚下的尘土
But I'm not dirt under your feet.
我所做的--
What I done--
我所做的 不是为了能坐出租车还有穿好衣服
What I did was not for the taxis and the dresses,
而是因为我们在一起是如此快乐 所以我开始--
but because we were pleasant together and I've come to--
开始喜欢你
Came to care for you.
不是为了要你向我表达爱意
Not to want you to make love to me
也不是忘记了我们之间的差距
and not forgetting the difference between us,
而是能更像朋友一些
but more friendly-like.
嗯 当然 我也这样想
Well, of course. That's how I feel.
皮克林也是
And how Pickering feels.
- 伊莉莎 你这个傻瓜 - 这不是我要的回答
- Eliza, you're a fool. - That's not the proper answer.
你别再犯傻了 这是唯一的答案
lt's the only answer till you stop being an idiot.
要是你是位女士 就不能有被忽视的感觉
lf you're a lady, give up feeling neglected
如果你所认识的那些男人不花上他们一半的时间
if the men you know don't spend half their time
为你落泪而另一半时间又对你冷淡
sniveling over you and the other half giving you black eyes.
你认为我冷酷 无情 自私 对吗？
You find me cold, unfeeling, selfish, don't you?
那就找你喜欢的那种人去吧
Be off with you to the sort of people you like.
嫁给一个有钱的 情感丰富的肥猪
Marry some sentimental hog with lots of money
用肥厚的嘴唇吻你 用厚重的靴子踢你
and a thick pair of lips to kiss you and a thick pair of boots to kick you.
既然你不感激你所拥有的一切 那就找你喜欢的去吧
lf you can't appreciate what you've got, get what you can appreciate.
噢 我不和你谈了
Oh, I can't talk to you.
我永远说不过你 永远都是我不对
You always turn everything against me. I'm always in the wrong.
但你别太过自信自己已经把我踩在脚下
But don't be too sure that you have me under your feet
任你践踏和说教
to be trampled on and talked down.
我会嫁给 弗雷迪 我会的 当我能够供养他的时候
I'II marry, Freddy, I will, soon as I'm able to support him.
弗雷迪？
Freddy?
那个可怜的家伙甚至连个跑腿的工作都找不到
That poor devil who couldn't get a job as an errand boy
就算这样他还有胆量要娶你？
even if he had the guts to try for it?
我说你这个女人 你还不明白吗？ 我把你变得足够嫁给国王
Woman, don't you understand? I've made you a consort for a king.
弗雷迪爱我 因为他爱我 所以足够做我的国王
Freddy loves me. That makes him king enough for me.
我不要他去工作 他跟我长大的环境是不一样的
I don't want him to work. He wasn't brought up to it as I was.
我可以做一名教师
I'II go and be a teacher.
天呐 你能教什么？
What will you teach, in heaven's name?
你教给我的东西 我会教语音学
What you taught me. I'II teach phonetics.
哈 哈 哈
Ha, ha, ha.
我可以自荐做那位了不起的匈牙利人的助手
I'II offer myself as an assistant to that brilliant Hungarian.
什么 那个冒牌货？那个骗子？那个只知谄媚的不学无术的家伙？
What, that impostor? That humbug? That toadying ignoramus?
把我的方法 我的发明都教给他？
Teach him my methods, my discoveries?
你要敢朝那个方向迈出一步 我就要拧断你的脖子
You take one step in that direction and I'II wring your neck.
拧啊 我还怕吗？我就知道你有一天会打死我的
Wring away. What do I care? I knew you'd strike me one day.
你不敢了吧 亨利 希金斯 对吧
That's done you, Henry Higgins, it has.
现在 我再也不会在意你的欺负还有你的大话了
Now, I don't care that for your bullying and your big talk.
我曾经多么傻 多么容易被人操纵
[SINGING] What a fool I was What a dominated fool
竟以为你就是我的天与地
To think you were the earth and sky
我曾经多么傻 多么容易被人哄骗
What a fool I was What an elevated fool
我曾经就像一个长了羊脑袋的傻瓜
What a mutton-headed dolt was I
不 我爱斗嘴的朋友
No, my reverberating friend
你既不是开始 也不是结束
You are not the beginning And the end
你这放肆的泼妇
You impudent hussy.
你脑子里没有一点儿思想 嘴里也没有一个词儿
There's not an idea in your head or a word in your mouth
这都是我给你的
that I haven't put there.
春天依然会来 即便没有你
There'II be spring every year Without you
英格兰依然存在 即便没有你
England still will be here Without you
树上依然会结果 海滩也依然还在海边
There'II be fruit on the tree And a shore by the sea
依然会有煎饼和茶 即便没有你
There'II be crumpets and tea Without you
美术与音乐仍将繁盛 即便没有你
Art and music will thrive Without you
诗人依然会存在 即便没有你
Somehow Keats will survive Without you
还有雨依然会落在 西班牙的平原上
And there still will be rain On that plain down in Spain
既然他们都能依然存在 即便没有你
Even that will remain Without you
我也可以
I can do
即便没有你
Without you
噢 亲爱的朋友
You, dear friend
你说的太好了
Who talk so well
你可以去 哈特福德 赫里福德还有汉普郡 [即离开伦敦]
You can go to Hartford, Hereford and Hampshire
他们依然可以统治这片土地 即便没有你
They can still rule the land Without you
温莎堡依然矗立 即便没有你
Windsor Castle will stand Without you
不必太过惊慌
And without much ado
我们也能应付过去 即便没有你
We can all muddle through Without you
你这无耻的泼妇
You brazen hussy.
用不着你推动 潮水依然会涨
Without your pulling it The tide comes in
用不着你拨动 地球依然会转
Without your twirling it The Earth can spin
用不着你牵动 云彩依然会飘
Without your pushing them The clouds roll by
既然没有你他们都可以 那太好了 我也可以
lf they can do without you Ducky, so can I
我不会感到孤独 即便没有你
I shall not feel alone Without you
我可以靠自己生活 即便没有你
I can stand on my own Without you
所以回到你的龟壳子里去吧 我可以做得相当好
So go back in your shell I can do bloody well
-即便没有-- 以圣乔治之名起誓 我真的办到了
- Without-- [SINGING] By George, I really did it
我办到了 我办到了
I did it, I did it
我说过我要创造一个女人 我确实办到了
I said I'd make a woman And indeed I did
我知道我可以办到 我就知道 我就知道
I knew that I could do it I knew it, I knew it
我说过我要创造一个女人 我成功了
I said I'd make a woman And succeed I did
伊莉莎 你真是太美了
Eliza, you're magnificent.
5分钟前 你还像绕在我脖子上的一块石头
Five minutes ago, you were a millstone around my neck
可现在你却像矗立的高塔
and now you're a tower of strength.
一艘全副武装的战舰
A consort battleship.
我喜欢你这样
I like you this way.
再见 希金斯教授
Goodbye, Professor Higgins.
你再也不会见到我了
You shall not be seeing me again.
母亲！
Mother!
怎么了 亨利？出什么事了？
What is it, Henry? What's happened?
她走了
She's gone.
噢 当然了 亲爱的 你以为会怎样？
Well, of course, dear. What did you expect?
噢...
Well...
- 我该怎么办？ - 将就过吧 我想
- What am I to do? - Do without, I suppose.
我会的
And so I shall.
如果希金斯的氧气会让她那狭小的肺燃烧
lf the Higgins' oxygen burns up her little lungs,
那就让她去找那些适合她的惰性气体
let her seek some stuffiness that suits her.
她就像只猫头鹰让我原本充满阳光的生活变得阴森 [呵呵 每天扯着嗓子练到那么晚]
She's an owl sickened by a few days of my sunshine.
那好吧 就随她去吧 没有她我可以的
Very well, let her go. I can do without her.
没有任何人我都可以 我还有自己的灵魂
I can do without anyone. I have my own soul.
我自己神圣的火焰迸发出的火花
My own spark of divine fire.
太精彩了 伊莉莎
Bravo, Eliza.
该死 该死 该死 该死
[SINGING] Damn, damn, damn, damn
我已经看惯了她的脸庞
I've grown accustomed to her face
仿佛是她让新一天开始
She almost makes the day begin
我已经听惯了她的音调 那些她日夜练习的音调
I've grown accustomed to the tune That she whistles night and noon
她的一颦 一笑 她的快乐与忧伤
Her smiles, her frowns Her ups, her downs
如今已渗入我的习惯
Are second nature to me now
就像呼吸一样
Like breathing out and breathing in
我曾过着平静的独身生活 这样的生活在我们见面之前我很满足
I was serenely independent And content before we met
当然我还是可以 重回那样的生活
Surely I could always Be that way again
可现在我已经习惯了 她的模样
And yet I've grown accustomed To her look
听惯了她的声音
Accustomed to her voice
看惯了她的脸庞
Accustomed to her face
嫁给弗雷迪 多么幼稚的想法
Marry Freddy. What an infantile idea.
这是多么无情 可恶 不明智的做法
What a heartless, wicked, brainless thing to do.
她会后悔的 她一定会后悔的
But she'II regret it. She'II regret it.
甚至他们还没念结婚誓词前 就已经结束了
lt's doomed before they even take the vow.
我现在就能看到她 弗雷迪 埃恩斯福德-希尔夫人
[SINGING] I can see her now Mrs. Freddy Eynsford-Hill
住在一个可怜的小公寓里 就在一家商店楼上
ln a wretched little flat Above a store
我现在就能看到她 放钱的抽屉里一个便士也没有
I can see her now Not a penny in the till
一位收债人 正在敲门
And a bill collector Beating at the door
她试过教授那些 我教给她的东西
She'II try to teach the things I taught her
可最后还是只能去卖花儿
And end up selling flowers instead
为了面包和水而乞讨
Begging for her bread and water
而她的丈夫 却在床上吃早餐
While her husband Has his breakfast in bed
要不了一年 当她的头发变得花白
In a year or so When she's prematurely grey
脸颊上的红晕 也变得惨白
And the blossom in her cheek Has turned to chalk
当她回到家 却
She'II come home, and lo
发现他早已起床
He'II have upped and run away
跟一个纽约来的 暴发户的女儿逃得无影无踪
With a social-climbing heiress From New York
可怜的伊莉莎
Poor Eliza
多么可怕
How simply frightful
多么丢人
How humiliating
多么解气
How delightful
那将是多么辛辣的讽刺 在那个必然的夜晚
How poignant it'II be On that inevitable night
当她敲打着我的房门 用破布擦着眼泪
When she hammers on my door ln tears and rags
悲惨又孤独 后悔并向我认错的时候
Miserable and lonely Repentant and contrite
我该让她进来 还是把她丢给那些色狼？
Will I take her in Or hurl her to the wolves?
是温柔待她 还是给她应有的惩罚？
Give her kindness Or the treatment she deserves?
我该让她回来 还是把这个货物扔出去？
Will I take her back Or throw the baggage out?
噢 我真是个最宽容的人
Well, I'm a most forgiving man
那种永远不能 也不愿
The sort who never could Ever would
认准了立场 就坚定不移
Take a position And staunchly never budge
一个最宽容的人
A most forgiving man
不过我再也不会让她回来
But I shall never take her back
就算她爬着求我
lf she were crawling on her knees
任她答应赎罪 任她颤抖 任她呻吟
Let her promise to atone Let her shiver, let her moan
我也会关上门 任这个泼妇被冻死
I'II slam the door And let the hellcat freeze
嫁给弗雷迪 哈！
Marry Freddy. Ha!
可我已经如此听惯了她 每天对我说早上好
But I'm so used to hear her say Good morning every day
她的一颦 一笑 她的快乐与忧伤
Her joys, her woes Her highs, her lows
如今已渗入我的习惯
Are second nature to me now
就像呼吸一样
Like breathing out and breathing in
我很庆幸她是个女人
I'm very grateful she's a woman
太容易忘记了
And so easy to forget
就像是个坏习惯 总能改掉
Rather like a habit One can always break
可我已经习惯 嗅到
And yet I've grown Accustomed to the trace
空气中的某种味道
Of something in the air
看惯了她的脸庞
Accustomed to her face
噢 我们都是有自尊心的
ELIZA [ON RECORDING]: Oh, we are proud.
噢 他不打算给教我了 他反悔了 他之前说要教我的
He ain't above giving lessons, not him. I heard him say so.
好吧 我可不是来这儿 听你们说这些客气话的
Well, I ain't come here to ask for any compliment,
要不是因为我的钱不够的话 我也不会来这儿
and if my money's not good enough, I can go elsewhere.
希金斯：不够什么？
HIGGINS: Good enough for what?
伊莉莎：付你的还是够了
ELIZA: Good enough for you.
现在 你明白了吗？
Now you know, don't you?
我是来学习的 听清楚了 我还会付学费
I'm come to have lessons, I am, and to pay for them too,
别搞错了
make no mistake.
你为什么要这样做呢 小姑娘？
PICKERING: What is it you want, my girl?
伊莉莎：我希望自己能像一位女士一样在花店里工作
ELIZA: I want to be a lady in a flower shop
而不是在托特纳姆考特路的街角卖花
instead of selling at the corner of Tottenham Court Road.
但除非我说话能更有教养些 否则他们是不会要我的
But they won't take me unless I can talk more genteel.
他说过他会教我
He said he could teach me.
所以 我就来了
Well, here I am.
我准备付钱给他 也不要他白教我
Ready to pay, not asking any favor.
可他却当我是垃圾一样的对待我
And he treats me as if I was dirt.
我知道你上课收多少钱 我愿意掏钱
I know what lessons cost as well as you do, and I'm ready to pay.
我最多出1个先令 随便你要不要
I won't give more than a schilling. Take it or leave it.
希金斯：这赌注很难拒绝 她的品味如此低俗
HIGGINS: lt's almost irresistible. She's so deliciously low.
如此肮脏可怖
So horribly dirty.
我愿意同您打这个赌
I'II take it.
我会将她从贫民区的邋遢女孩儿 变为一位公爵夫人
I'II make a duchess of this draggle-tailed guttersnipe.
[关掉留声机]
[TURNS GRAMOPHONE OFF]
我来之前洗过脸还有手 真的
I washed my face and hands before I come, I did.
伊莉莎？
Eliza?
该死的我的拖鞋到底哪去了？
Where the devil are my slippers?